Prolegomena [= Preliminaries]

to any Future Metaphysic

that can Present itself as a Science

Immanuel Kant

Copyright ©2010–2015 All rights reserved. Jonathan Bennett
[Brackets] enclose editorial explanations. Small ·dots· enclose material that has been added, but can be read as though it were part of the original text. Occasional •bullets, and also indenting of passages that are not quotations, are meant as aids to grasping the structure of a sentence or a thought. Every four-point ellipsis .... indicates the omission of a brief passage that seems to present more difficulty than it is worth. Longer omissions are reported between brackets in normal-sized type.
First launched: July 2004 Last amended: April 2007
[This single-column (but otherwise unrevised) version by Philosophy Ink derives from the original two-column PDF version at http://www.earlymoderntexts.com. Even Bennett's pagination has been retained since he sometimes makes in-text references to his own page numbers.]

Contents

Introduction 1
Preamble on the special features of all metaphysical knowledge 7
General Problems 12
Main transcendental Problem 1: How is pure mathematics possible? 16
Main transcendental problem 2: How is pure natural science possible? 25
Main transcendental problem 3: How is metaphysics possible in general? 45

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant

Conclusion: Determining the boundaries of pure reason 61
Solution of the general question of the Prolegomena: How is metaphysics possible as a science? 72
Appendix: On what can be done to make metaphysics actual as a science 76

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Introduction

Introduction

These Preliminaries are meant for the use not of learners but of future teachers; and even the teachers shouldn’t expect this book to help them by neatly laying out a ready-made science. Rather, it is to help them to discover this science. [Throughout this work, ‘science’ means ‘branch of knowledge that is theoretically organised, highly structured, and soundly based’.]

For some learned people, philosophy is just the history of philosophy (ancient and modern); these preliminaries aren’t written for them. They must wait their turn. When those who work to draw ·truth· from the well of reason itself have done their work, then the historians can give the world the news about their results. ·But they won’t regard it as news, because· nothing can be said now that the historians won’t think has been said already! And it is safe to predict that they’ll think the same about anything said in the future; human understanding has busied itself for centuries with countless topics in many ways, so it is to be expected that every new idea will resemble something that has been said in the past.

If you think that metaphysics is worth studying, my aim is to convince you of the following:

It is absolutely necessary that you stop your work for a while, regard anything that has been done as not having been done, and face up to the preliminary question of whether such a thing as metaphysics is even possible.

If it is a science, why can’t it get universal and lasting approval, like other sciences? If it is not, what enables it to go on giving itself airs with its pretence of being a science, keeping men’s minds in suspense with hopes that never die but are never fulfilled? If we are to show that there’s knowledge to be had from metaphysics, or to show that there isn’t, we must once and for all reach a conclusion about the nature of this would-be science, for it can’t go on as it has been doing. It seems close to ridiculous, when every other science makes steady progress, that this one—claiming to be wisdom personified, the oracle that everyone consults—goes on circling around the same spot, never taking a step forwards. Its fringe hangers-on have scattered; and people who are sure enough that they can shine in other sciences won’t be found risking their reputations in this one, where there are no objective standards for distinguishing sound knowledge from mere chatter, so that any ignoramus can feel entitled to pass judgment.

There’s nothing extraordinary in the idea that when people have worked hard at a science they should wonder •how much progress it has made, and be led from that to wonder •whether such a science is possible at all. Human reason so loves building that it has repeatedly built a tower ·of theory· and then dismantled it to check the soundness of the foundation. It is never too late to become reasonable and wise; but if an insight comes late, it will be that much harder to make use of it.

When we ask whether a certain science is possible, that presupposes that we have doubts about whether it is actual. That doubt will shock anyone whose whole fortune, perhaps, consists in this supposed jewel ·called ‘metaphysics’·; and so anyone who voices the doubt can expect to be attacked on all sides. Some of the attackers—clutching their big metaphysical books, and proudly conscious of their ·intellectual· possessions, which they think are legitimate because they are old!—will look down on him with contempt. Others, for

1

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Introduction

whom everything they see is all of a piece with something they have seen before, won’t understand him. And for a while things will stay as they were, as though nothing had happened to raise the hope or the fear of an impending change.

Nevertheless, I confidently predict that if you read these preliminaries and think for yourself,

not only will you come to doubt the ·supposed· science that you have practised ·under the name of metaphysics·, but eventually you’ll become quite sure that nothing like that can exist without satisfying the demands that I shall state here—demands on which its possibility depends. You will also become sure that since the demands never have been met, there has up till now been no such thing as metaphysics.

But the search for metaphysics will continue, because the interests of human reason are so closely bound up with it; so you’ll agree that metaphysics is unstoppably on the road to a total reform (or, better, a new birth) on a wholly new plan, even if people struggle against it for a while.

David Hume’s attack on •metaphysics was more decisive for •its fate than any other event since the Essays of Locke and Leibniz—actually, since the earliest recorded beginnings of metaphysics. Hume threw no light on this kind of knowledge, but he struck a spark from which a light could have been kindled if it had fallen on something flammable and the resultant smoulder had been nursed into flames.

Hume’s primary starting-point was a single important metaphysical concept, namely that of the connection of cause with effect (including derivative concepts like those of force and action and so on). Reason purports to have given birth to this concept, but Hume challenged reason thus:

Explain to me what entitles you to think there could be a thing x such that: given that there is x, there must necessarily also be something else y—for that’s what the concept of cause says.

He showed beyond question that it is completely impossible for reason to have—in an a priori way and purely through concepts ·with no input from experience·—the thought of such a union ·of x with y·, because the thought of such a union includes the thought of necessity. We cannot at all see why, given that one thing exists, some other thing necessarily must exist, or how the concept of such a connection could arise a priori. From this he inferred that reason is utterly deluded regarding the concept of cause, wrongly thinking it to be among her own children when really it is a bastard child of the imagination that was got in the family way by experience. What the imagination did ·according to Hume· was to consider certain sense-impressions that were related to one another by the law of association

—·so that after experiencing many F impressions followed by G ones, you get into the habit of expecting a G whenever you experience an F, the habit becoming strong enough so that any new experience of an F compels you to expect a G·—

and to mistake a •subjective necessity (habit) for the •objective necessity arising from grasping what must be the case. He inferred that reason can’t form a thought of the form x is necessarily and objectively connected with y, or even with the general thought of that kind of connection. If reason did produce any such thought (Hume held), the concepts it involved would be fictitious, and all reason’s claims to a priori knowledge would be merely the mis-labelled deliverances of ordinary experience. He was saying in effect that metaphysics couldn’t possibly exist. [At this point Kant has a footnote, as follows:] Yet Hume called this destructive science of his ‘metaphysics’ and put a great price on it. ‘Metaphysics and morals’, he says, ‘are the most important branches of

2

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Introduction

learning. Mathematics and natural science are not half so valuable.’ But all that this brilliant man had in his view was the negative work involved in damping down the extravagant claims of speculative reason and thus settling many endless and vexatious controversies that lead mankind astray. He lost sight of the positive harm that is done when reason is robbed of its most important vistas—which it needs if it is to mark out for the will its highest goal in all its endeavours. [End of footnote. That last remark reflects views of Kant’s about reason’s link with freedom, and freedom’s link with morality.]

His inference was hasty and wrong, but at least it was based on investigation; and this investigation thoroughly deserved ·a better response than it got. It ought· to have brought together the intelligent people of the time to search for a happier solution of Hume’s problem as he had formulated it; and if that had happened, a complete reform of the science ·of metaphysics· would have quickly followed.

But metaphysicians have always suffered the misfortune of not being understood by anyone, and this is what happened to Hume. It really hurts to see how totally Hume’s opponents—Reid, Oswald, Beattie, and finally Priestley too—missed the point of his problem. They kept taking for granted things that he had called into question, and offered furious and often arrogant demonstrations of things he had never thought of questioning; so they didn’t pick up the pointer he had given to an improvement ·that metaphysics might undergo·. In this they failed so completely that at the end of the debate the status quo was still standing: it was as though nothing had happened!

Hume had never cast doubt on the proposition that the concept of cause is proper, useful, and even indispensable for our knowledge of nature; that wasn’t in question. What was in question was whether reason could think that concept a priori. If it could, the concept of causation would be the source of an inner truth—truths coming just from itself, not from anything outside it given through experience—so that it could be applied to things other than merely the objects of experience. That was Hume’s problem. He wasn’t challenging our indispensable need for the concept of cause, but merely asking what its origin is. If the origin was settled, questions about the conditions governing the use of the concept, and about the domain in which it can be validly used, would automatically have been answered also.

To deal adequately with this problem, however, Hume’s opponents would have had to dig deeply into the nature of reason, considered as the faculty of pure thinking: not a job to their taste! They were more comfortable with a different approach, one that let them defy Hume without bringing any insight to his problem, namely by appealing to common sense. It is indeed a great gift from heaven to have plain common sense. But this common sense must be shown in practice, through judicious and reasonable thoughts and words, not by appealing to it as an oracle when one has no rational arguments to offer. Appeal to common sense when insight and science have failed you, but don’t appeal to it before then!—that ·rule of intellectual conduct· is one of the devious inventions of recent times, and it enables a shallow ranter to join battle with a solid thinker, and hold his own. But anyone with a flicker of insight left to him would be careful not to grasp at this straw. If you place this appeal to common sense in a clear light you will see that it is nothing but an appeal to the opinion of the mob—whose applause embarrasses the philosopher but brings joy and reassurance to the popular smart alec. I should think that Hume had as much claim to sound common sense as Beattie did, and he also had something that Beattie lacked, namely a critical reason that restrains common sense so that •it doesn’t speculate or, if speculations are the topic of discussion, •it doesn’t crave for

3

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Introduction

any decision when it isn’t satisfied that it has the arguments to support one. This is the only way someone’s common sense can remain sound. Chisels and hammers can serve very well in working wood, but for copperplate we need an engraver’s needle.

Thus •sound common sense and •speculative understanding are both useful, but each in its own way: •the former serves in judgments that apply immediately to experience, •the latter comes into play when universal judgments from mere concepts are to be made, as in metaphysics. In the latter environment sound common sense has absolutely no right to judge.

Here is an open confession about something that happened many years ago: it was my recollection of ·the thought of· David Hume that broke into my dogmatic slumber, and pointed my work in speculative philosophy in a completely new direction. I was nowhere near accepting his conclusions. He had reached them by looking at only a part of his problem—a part that by itself can give us no information. ·Still·, if we start from a well-founded but undeveloped thought that someone else has left to us, we can hope that by continuing to think it through we shall get further than did the brilliant man to whom we owe the first spark of light.

So I tried first to see whether Hume’s objection could be put into a general form, and I soon got a result:

The concept of the cause-effect connection is far from being the only idea by which the understanding has a priori thoughts about the connections of things. On the contrary, metaphysics consists purely of such concepts—·i.e. concepts of the connections of things·.

I tried to find out how many such concepts there are, and succeeded in this in the desirable way, namely by starting from a single principle. Then I proceeded to the deduction of these concepts, which I was now certain didn’t come from •experience (which is all that Hume provided for them) but rather from •pure understanding. [By the phrase ‘the deduction of these concepts’ Kant refers to a theoretically grounded and justified list of the concepts in question]—something that proves and explains why the metaphysical concepts of the connections of things are just exactly the ones on the list. This deduction had seemed impossible to Hume; and apart from him nobody had even thought of it, although everyone had confidently used the ·metaphysical· concepts, without asking what their objective validity was based on. The deduction was the hardest task that anyone could tackle in the service of metaphysics; and the worst of it was that I couldn’t get help from metaphysics as it then was, because this deduction is what’s needed to make metaphysics possible. But ·despite getting no help from metaphysics· I did succeed in solving the Humean problem, not merely for a particular case ·of the cause-effect connection· but with respect to the whole faculty of pure reason. With that done, I could safely—though always slowly—go on to map out the whole domain of pure reason, establishing its boundaries and its contents. I did all this completely, and from general principles, which is what metaphysics needed if its system was to be securely built.

I expounded the Humean problem in its most general possible form in my book Critique of Pure Reason; but I am afraid that that work may go the same way as the problem did when Hume first propounded it. The book will be misjudged because misunderstood; and people will misunderstand it because they are inclined to skim through the book rather than thinking it through. That is ·admittedly· a disagreeable task, because the work conflicts with all ordinary concepts, as well as being dry, obscure, and long-winded! ·Despite those drawbacks·, I confess that I didn’t expect to hear a philosopher complain that the book isn’t a crowd-pleaser, not entertaining, not an easy read, given that what’s at issue

4

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Introduction

in it is no less than the existence of a highly prized and indispensable kind of knowledge—a question that can’t be settled except by working strictly according to rule and with great precision. Such work might in the course of time please the crowd; but ·a concern for· popularity is quite inappropriate at the start. Still, one of the complaints is justified: the book’s plan is diffuse, making it hard for the reader to keep in mind the chief points of the investigation; and that contributes to a certain obscurity. I intend to remedy that with these Preliminaries.

The earlier work, which maps out the entire faculty of pure reason, will be the foundation to which the Preliminaries are to be related. But the latter work—·the book you now hold in your hands·—is only a preparatory exercise ·and not a contribution to metaphysics itself·; because we can’t think of letting metaphysics appear on the scene, or even have a faint hope of attaining it, until our critique has been established as a science that is complete in every detail.

We have long been used to seeing dreary old knowledge spruced up as new by being taken out of its former context and turned into a system in fancy new clothing with new terminology; and that’s all that most readers will initially expect my critique to be. But these Preliminaries may help the reader to see that it is ·not old stuff in new clothes, but· a wholly new science that no-one has ever thought of—indeed, the very idea of which was unknown—and to which no previous work has made the slightest contribution. The only exception to that is the pointer one could get from Hume’s doubts; but even he didn’t suspect ·there could be· such a possible formal science; instead, he played safe by running his ship onto the shore (scepticism), and letting it lie there and rot. I prefer to give the ship a pilot who can safely sail it anywhere he likes, by means of secure principles of navigation drawn from a knowledge of the globe, and equipped with a complete chart and compass.

Suppose we are confronted by a new science that is wholly isolated and the only one of its kind. If we start with the assumption that we can make judgments about it in terms of knowledge that we have already gained—which is precisely what has first to be called in question ·when considering a new science·—all we shall achieve is to see everywhere things we already know, with the •words sounding familiar but everything seeming (·so far as the •content is concerned·) to be pushed out of shape, senseless, gibberish. That’s because we’ll be relying on •our own notions, which long habit has made second nature for us, instead of relying on •the author’s. But the long-windedness of the work, to the extent that it comes from the science itself and not merely from the exposition, as well as the unavoidable dryness and by-the-rules precision, are qualities that can bring credit to the science—though not to the book!

It isn’t given to many of us to write with the subtlety and grace of David Hume, or with the solidity and elegance of Moses Mendelssohn. Yet I flatter myself that I could have written in a crowd-pleasing way if my aim ·in the Critique of Pure Reason· had been merely to outline a plan and leave it to others to complete, rather than having set my heart on the good of the science that had occupied me for so long. Indeed it took a lot of perseverance and a good deal of self-denial to put •the prospect of later but more lasting applause ahead of •the enticements of an immediate success.

The making of plans is often an arrogant and boastful activity through which someone •gives himself airs as a creative genius by demanding what he doesn’t himself supply, •finds fault with what he can’t improve, and •makes proposals that he himself doesn’t know how to carry out—though a sound plan for a general critique of pure reason, if it isn’t to amount only to the usual spouting of pious hopes, will have to have

5

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Features of metaphysical knowledge

more content than one might expect. But the domain of pure reason is so •separate from everything else, and so •inter-connected within itself, that we can’t lay a finger on one part without affecting all the others, and can’t build anything there without first determining where each part is and how it relates to the rest. That’s because our judgment •within this domain can’t be corrected by anything •outside it, and so the validity and use of every part of the domain depends on how it relates to all the rest—just as with the structure of an organism we can work out the purpose of each part only from a full conception of the whole. So it can be said that •such a critique shouldn’t be trusted unless it is perfectly complete, down to the smallest elements of pure reason, and that •in the domain of reason you must settle everything—or you’ll settle nothing.

As for a mere plan or sketch of the critique of pure reason: its usefulness as a sequel to the critique is a measure of how useless—how unintelligible and unreliable—it would be if given in advance. Taken as a sequel, it gives us a vantage-point from which we can take in the whole thing, can test—one by one—the chief points of the science, and can make the exposition of it much better than it was the first time around.

[In the next paragraph Kant uses ‘analytic’ and ‘synthetic’ to mark a distinction between two methods of presentation of some doctrine. An •analytic presentation starts with things we all know to be true and works its way from those to the theory or doctrine that explains and is supported by them. A •synthetic presentation goes in the opposite direction: it starts with the fundamental theses of the doctrine to be expounded, and works from those to various of their consequences, which could include the things-we-already-know that are the starting-point for the analytic format. This use of ‘analytic’ and ‘synthetic’ occurs only here and on pages 15 and ??. Everywhere else in this work and throughout the Critique of Pure Reason Kant uses the terms in an utterly different sense, in which it distinguishes not •expository methods but •kinds of proposition. This use of the terminology is the one that is still current; Kant explains it in section 2 below.]

With my critique of pure reason completed, I now offer a plan of it as a sequel. The plan is to be laid out in the •analytic manner, whereas the critique itself had to be composed in the •synthetic style so that readers could command a view of all the joints of the science—the natural hanging-together of the structural parts of ·pure reason·, an utterly special cognitive faculty. But if you also find this too obscure—this plan that I offer as the Preliminaries to any future Metaphysic—bear in mind •that it’s not necessary for everyone to study metaphysics, •that many people have the aptitude to succeed very well in sciences (even deep ones) that are closer to sense-experience, yet can’t succeed in investigations dealing with highly abstract concepts, •that such people should employ their talents on other subjects; •that someone who undertakes to make judgments in metaphysics—let alone to construct a metaphysical system—must satisfy the demands I have made here, which he can’t do by rejecting them, so he must either adopt my solution or thoroughly refute it and put another in its place; and, finally, •that this notorious obscurity (·allegations of which are· often a cloak to cover the accuser’s laziness or stupidity) also has its uses ·as a defence against insolent intruders. There’s no shortage of them in metaphysics!· People who maintain a cautious silence in relation to other sciences approach metaphysics in a spirit of bold pronouncements and snap judgments, because in this area their ignorance is not contrasted with the knowledge of others.

6

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Features of metaphysical knowledge

Preamble on the special features of all metaphysical knowledge

1: The sources of metaphysics
If a domain of knowledge is to be exhibited as a science, we need to know exactly what features are special to it, marking it off from all other sciences. Otherwise the boundaries of all the sciences run into one another and none of them can be treated soundly according to its own nature. Our idea of a possible science and of the territory it covers is based on its special features—whether they have to do with its •subject matter, or its •sources of knowledge, or the •kind of knowledge it involves, or of some or all of these together.

Let us consider first the sources of metaphysical knowledge. The very concept of metaphysics ensures that the sources of metaphysics can’t be empirical. ·If something could be known through the senses, that would automatically show that it doesn’t belong to metaphysics; that’s an upshot of the meaning of the word ‘metaphysics’·. Its basic propositions can never be taken from experience, nor can its basic concepts; for it is not to be physical but metaphysical knowledge, so it must lie beyond experience. •Outer experience is the source of physics properly so-called, and •inner experience is the basis for empirical psychology; and metaphysical knowledge can’t come from either of these. It is thus knowledge a priori—knowledge based on pure understanding and pure reason.

Mathematics also answers to that description. To mark off metaphysics from mathematics as well as from empirical enquiries, we’ll have to call it pure philosophical knowledge. In this phrase, ‘pure’ means ‘not empirical’; and ‘philosophical’ stands in contrast to ‘mathematical’. The difference between these two ways of using reason—the mathematical and the philosophical—is something I needn’t go into here; I have adequately described it in my Critique of Pure Reason. So much for the sources of metaphysical knowledge.

2: The only kind of knowledge that can be called metaphysical
(a) The distinction between synthetic and analytic judgments in general.
Because of what is special about the sources of metaphysical knowledge—·namely, that they don’t include experience·—all such knowledge must consist in judgments that are made a priori. However, a priori judgments can be divided into two groups, according to their content: (1) those that merely spell out what’s already there, adding nothing to the content of the knowledge, and (2) those that add something, and enlarge the given knowledge. We can call (1) analytic judgments, and (2) synthetic.

Analytic judgments say nothing in the predicate that wasn’t already thought—though less clearly—in the concept of the subject. If I say ‘All bodies are extended’, I haven’t added anything to my concept of body, but have merely analysed it. Extension was already implicitly thought of in the concept of body, before I made the judgment. So the judgment is analytic. On the other hand the proposition ‘Some bodies are heavy’ contains something in the predicate that isn’t thought—even unclearly or implicitly—in the concept of body. It thus enlarges my knowledge in that it adds something to my concept, and hence must be called a synthetic judgment.
(b) The common principle of all analytic judgments is the law of contradiction.
All analytic judgments rest wholly on the law of contradiction.

7

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Features of metaphysical knowledge

The predicate of an affirmative analytic judgment has already been thought in the concept of the subject, so it can’t be denied of the subject without contradiction. This is the case with the proposition ‘Every body is extended’. ·That’s equivalent to something of the form ‘Everything that is F and extended is extended’, so that to deny it would be to say that something is F and extended and not extended, which is an outright contradiction. The law of contradiction, which says that no contradiction is true, thus underlies the truth of the analytic proposition that all bodies are extended·.

So all analytic propositions are a priori judgments, even those that contain empirical concepts as does the judgment ‘Gold is a yellow metal’. ·I must have experience if I am to have the concepts of gold, of yellow, and of metal; but· to know that gold is a yellow metal I need no further experience; all I need is to analyse my concept of gold, which contains the concept of being a yellow metal.
(c) Synthetic judgments need a different principle from the law of contradiction.
Some synthetic judgments have an empirical origin, and can be known only a posteriori; other synthetic judgments have a priori certainty, and originate in pure understanding and reason. No synthetic judgment can come from the law of contradiction alone. Such judgments must conform to that principle (which is just to say that they mustn’t be self-contradictory), but they can’t be deduced from it.

·In the rest of this section four kinds of synthetic judgment will be identified and discussed. Although they are all synthetic—meaning that none of them can be established merely by analysing concepts—three of the four kinds can be learned a priori·.

(1) Judgments of experience are always synthetic. It would be absurd to base an analytic judgment on experience: why go to experience when the judgment can be derived purely from my concept? That every body is extended is a proposition that holds a priori, and not a judgment of experience. For before I look to experience I already have in the concept of body all that I need for that judgment: I need only to extract the predicate (‘extended’) from that concept according to the law of contradiction. In doing that, I also become conscious of the necessity of the judgment—and ·that’s further evidence that this analytic judgment isn’t based on experience, because· experience can never teach me that something is necessary.

(2) Mathematical judgments are all, without exception, synthetic. This is certainly true and is very important, but it seems to have escaped the notice of all previous analysers of human reason, and indeed to be directly opposed to all their theories. Those earlier thinkers saw that all the inferences of mathematicians proceed according to the law of contradiction, and wrongly slipped into thinking that mathematical truths were known from the law of contradiction. This was a great mistake. The law of contradiction can lead one to a synthetic proposition, but only from another synthetic proposition. (Still, it must be borne in mind that mathematical propositions are always a priori judgments, not empirical ones. They carry necessity with them, and that can’t be learned about from experience. If you disagree, I shan’t argue; I shall merely make this claim about the propositions of pure—i.e. non-empirical—mathematics!)

One might think that the proposition 7 + 5 = 12 is analytic, and that it follows according to the law of contradiction from the concept of

the sum of 7 and 5.

But if we look more closely, we find that the concept of the sum of 7 and 5 contains only

the uniting of 7 and 5 into a single number;

8

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Features of metaphysical knowledge

and in thinking this we don’t have the least thought of what this single number is in which the two are combined. I can analyse my concept of the uniting of seven and five as long as I please—I shall never find 12 in it. I have to go outside these concepts and—with the help of an intuition that corresponds to one of them (my five fingers for instance)—add the 5 given in intuition to the concept of 7, adding them one by one. Thus in this proposition 7 + 5 = 12 we really amplify our concept ·of 7 + 5·, adding to it new concept that wasn’t thought in it. That is to say, arithmetical propositions are always synthetic. It will be easier to grasp this if we take larger numbers. It is obvious that however we might turn and twist our concept of

the sum of 38976 and 45204

we could never find 84180 in it through mere analysis, without the help of intuition.

[Kant’s use of the term ‘intuition’ needs to be explained. Traditionally, the word has had two meanings. •In one it contrasts with ‘demonstration’—you know something intuitively if it is immediately self-evident to you, whereas demonstrative knowledge involves a series of deductive steps. •In the other meaning—which alone is relevant to Kant—our faculty of ‘intuition’ is our ability to be mentally confronted by individual things, to have in our minds representations of the things and not merely of certain features or properties of them. Kant uses ‘intuition’ to stand not just for the faculty but also for the mental representations that it involves. Thus, for example, when you see the Lincoln Memorial you have an intuition of it, and this is an exercise of your faculty of intuition. That intuition is a ‘sensible’ one, meaning that you get it through your senses. It stands in contrast with a concept of the Lincoln Memorial—such as the concept or abstract thought of a large white memorial to a great American statesman. Having in your mind a (conceptual) representation of a large white memorial etc. is quite different from having in your mind an (intuitive) representation of the Lincoln Memorial, that one particular individual object.

[Now, Kant holds that we are also capable of having in our minds intuitions that don’t come from the senses; he calls them ‘pure’ or ‘a priori’ intuitions. When in the previous paragraph he speaks of the intuition of my five fingers, that is a •sensible intuition: I feel or look at the fingers. But he believes—as we’ll see in section 7—-that pure mathematics involves •pure intuitions: for example, a geometer works out the properties of circles not by merely taking the abstract concept circle and analysing it, but by somehow giving himself a pure intuition of a circle, and working out the properties of all circles from that. This is something like imagining-a-circle, but it isn’t ordinary imagination, which is copied from sense experience.

[The basic idea is something like this: Every time you see or feel something circular, various aspects of your mental state are contributed by the sensations that come from outside you, and others are contributed by your understanding, i.e. the concept-using faculty. If all of that were somehow stripped off, what would be left is a very thin, abstract intuition of the circular thing just as a circle. That is, nothing would be left of it but its purely spatial or geometrical properties; they will be the same for every circular thing; so the stripped down intuition will be the same in each case. That stripped down intuition is what Kant calls a ‘pure intuition’ of a circle. According to him, this isn’t contributed by sensation from outside you; rather, it is conferred on your mental state by your own mind, specifically by your own faculty of sensible intuition. You are so built, he thinks, that you have to experience the world outside yourself as spatial, not because the outer world is spatial but because you impose spatiality on the intuitions you have of it. Kant puts this, sometimes, by saying that what’s represented in a pure intuition is the form of your sensibility or of your sensible intuition.

[For the geometer to establish synthetic truths about circles, Kant holds, he must not only have •the concept circle but must also have •a pure intuition of a circle. This pure intuition, he sometimes says, exhibits the concept; it illustrates or exemplifies it; it shows the geometrician what a circle is, taking him from the merely conceptual thought of circles to a kind of abstract non-sensory view of a circle.

[The same story can be re-told about the perceptions of events: strip off everything empirical, and everything conceptual, and you are left with a mere, bare, pure intuition of time. As •space is a form of your sensibility in experiencing things outside yourself, •time—Kant thinks—is a form of your sensibility in relation not only to things outside you but also to the flow of your mental history. Just as geometry is based on pure intuitions of space (or of spatial figures), Kant says, arithmetic is based on pure intuitions of time; see section 10. We now return to Kant’s text.]

9

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Features of metaphysical knowledge

Nor is any principle of pure geometry analytic. That a straight line is the shortest path between two points is a synthetic proposition. For my concept of straightness contains nothing having to do with •quantity—it is purely a •qualitative concept—so it can’t contain the thought of what is shortest, ·because that is quantitative·. Here again, we need help from intuition if we are to have a basis for putting shortest together with straight.

Why are we so prone to believe that in such a judgment the predicate is already contained in our concept so that the judgment is analytic? The source of this mistake is a certain ambiguity. We ought to join in thought a certain predicate (’shortest’) to a given concept (’straight’), and this requirement is inherent in the concepts themselves. But the question isn’t what we •ought to think along with the given concept but what we •do think in it, even if unclearly. Once we distinguish those, we can see that while the predicate is indeed attached to the subject concept necessarily, it is attached only through an intuition that must also be present; it isn’t to be found in the subject concept itself.

Some other principles that geometers use are indeed really analytic and rest on the law of contradiction: for example ‘Everything is equal to itself’, and ‘The whole is greater than its part’. These identical propositions can be useful in setting out arguments, but they don’t actually say anything; they can be useful methodologically, but they don’t contribute to the content of what is said. Furthermore, even these analytic propositions, though they are indeed validated purely by our concepts, wouldn’t be allowed into mathematics if they couldn’t be illustrated by propositions that are connected with intuition. ·For example, ‘The whole is greater than its part’ is allowed into mathematics because it can be applied to numbers, areas and lengths, which are given to us in intuition·.

Pure mathematical knowledge differs from all other a priori knowledge in this: it never proceeds from concepts, but is always achieved by construction of concepts. Mathematical propositions must therefore go beyond the concept to what the corresponding intuition contains, ·because this intuition guides the construction of the concept·; hence they can’t and shouldn’t come from the analysis of concepts, and are therefore one and all synthetic.

This may seem a small and unimportant point; but the neglect of it has done harm to philosophy. Hume had the worthy philosophical aim of surveying the whole domain of pure a priori knowledge—a domain in which the human understanding lays claim to great possessions—but he carelessly sliced off a large part of the territory, its most considerable province, namely pure mathematics. He thought that mathematics rested on the law of contradiction alone. Although he didn’t classify propositions in quite the way that I do here, or with the same names, he in effect said: Pure mathematics contains only analytic propositions, but metaphysics contains a priori synthetic propositions. Now this was a great mistake, which infected his whole system of thought. If he hadn’t made this mistake, he would have taken his question about the origin of our ·a priori· synthetic judgments to cover not only •metaphysics (e.g. the concept of causality) but also •mathematics. He had too much insight to base mathematics on mere experience, so ·if he had likened metaphysics to mathematics in the way I have been defending· he would have spared metaphysics from the vile mistreatment to which he subjected it, because that attack would have hit on mathematics as well, which Hume can’t have wanted to do. And then, fine thinker that he was, he would have been drawn into lines of thought like those that I am now offering—though he would have presented them in his own uniquely elegant style.

10

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Features of metaphysical knowledge

(3) [following (2), which began on page 8.] Natural science also contains synthetic judgments that can be known a priori, for example:

•In all changes in the physical world the quantity of matter remains unchanged.

•When one body collides with another, action and reaction must always be equal.

Clearly these are not only necessary and a priori in origin but are also synthetic. ·I shall show this of the first of them. It says that the total amount of matter in the universe never changes, which is to say that matter is permanent·. Now, in ·thinking· the concept of •matter I do not think its •permanence but only its •presence in the space that it fills. ·Thinking that matter is permanent isn’t like thinking that women are female, or that tigers are animals·. In judging that matter is permanent, therefore, I go beyond the concept of matter in order to add to it something that I didn’t think in it. So the proposition isn’t analytic but synthetic; yet it is thought a priori, as are the other propositions of the pure part of natural science—·the ‘pure’ part being the part that owes nothing to experience·. [This paragraph on natural science is brought across from the Critique of Pure Reason. There’s evidence that Kant intended such a paragraph to occur here, and omitted it by accident.]

(4) Properly metaphysical judgments are all synthetic. The whole aim of metaphysics is to arrive at conclusions that are synthetic. Analytic judgments are also involved, but only as aids to constructing •arguments; what metaphysics, properly so-called, is really about is the establishment of •conclusions, which are always synthetic. If a concept (such as that of substance) belongs to metaphysics, then the ·analytic· judgments that analyse this concept also belong there—for example the judgment that substance is that which exists only as subject etc.–and a set of such judgments can be used to work towards a definition of the concept in question. But such a •judgment belongs to metaphysics only because the analysed •concept does; the process of analysis is just the same as we use when analysing empirical concepts that don’t belong to metaphysics. The only judgments that are really strictly metaphysical are synthetic ones.

When the a priori concepts that are the building-bricks of metaphysics have been gathered together in a systematic way, the analysis of them is of great value. The analytic judgments that are arrived at in this way can be separated out from the rest of metaphysics, and presented as a separate part of the whole system. The only use that these analyses have in metaphysics is as a useful preliminary to the procedure of arriving a priori at synthetic propositions involving the concepts that have been analysed.

The upshot of this section is that metaphysics is centrally concerned with a priori knowledge of synthetic propositions. These are what metaphysics is for. We are helped to arrive at them by analyses and analytic judgments—indeed, ones using the very same process of analysis as we do when trying to clarify our concepts in other branches of knowledge. But the essential content of metaphysics is the generation of knowledge a priori, both according to intuition and according to concepts, leading ultimately to synthetic propositions a priori—philosophical knowledge.

3: A note about the analytic/synthetic distinction
The distinction between analytic and synthetic is essential in the present kind of enquiry into the human understanding; it isn’t much used anywhere else, so far as I know. The reason why dogmatic philosophers overlooked this apparently obvious distinction is that they didn’t look for the sources of metaphysics in the pure laws of reason in general ·and so they didn’t see how metaphysical truths could be known a priori

11

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant General Problems

and yet be synthetic·. [By ‘dogmatic’ philosophers Kant means, broadly speaking, ones who plunge ahead doing metaphysics without first raising the question of how—or indeed whether—metaphysics is possible.] Thus two recent German philosophers tried to derive the law of sufficient reason, which is obviously synthetic, from the law of contradiction. [The law of sufficient reason says that there’s a reason for everything that is the case, i.e. that there’s a correct answer to every ‘Why?’-question.] Still, there is a hint of this distinction in Locke’s Essay at IV.iii.9ff. Having previously discussed the different kinds of judgments and how we arrive at them, including

•judgments of ‘identity or contradiction’ (which are analytic), and

•judgments of ‘co-existence’ (which are synthetic),

he admits that our a priori knowledge of the latter is very narrow and almost nothing at all. ·Grudging as that is, it does at least admit the possibility of some synthetic a priori knowledge·. But what he says of this kind of knowledge is so skimpy and unsystematic that it’s not surprising that it didn’t prompt anyone—and in particular didn’t prompt Hume—to consider propositions of this kind. It is hard to learn universal and yet definite truths from someone who only had them floating obscurely before him in his thought! One needs to discover them for oneself, in one’s own thinking; then one can find them elsewhere, where one would certainly not have found them before because the authors weren’t clear in their own minds about what they were saying. ·That’s how I found the analytic/synthetic distinction in Locke’s pages when Hume didn’t find it there: the crucial point is that I had first worked out the distinction for myself·.

General Problems

4: The general problem of the Preliminaries: is metaphysics possible at all?
If we had a real metaphysics that could claim to be a science—if we could say ‘Here is metaphysics, all you have to do is to learn it, and it will convince you of its truth’—then we wouldn’t have to ask whether metaphysics is possible, ·just as we don’t have to ask whether geometry, say, is possible·. Our only question would concern how it is possible, and how reason should set about doing metaphysics; and this would be •a test of our mental skills, not •a challenge to the existence of the thing itself.

However, things haven’t turned out so well for human reason. There’s no single book that one can point to....and say, ‘This is metaphysics; here you will find knowledge of a highest being and of a future world, which is the noblest aim of this science, proved from principles of pure reason.’ Many propositions have been agreed without dispute to be necessary and certain, but they are all analytic, and concern the materials and building-stones of metaphysics rather than the enlargement of our knowledge. You may point to some synthetic propositions (e.g. the law of sufficient reason) which are widely accepted, though you have never proved them through mere reason, a priori, as you ought to have.

12

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant General Problems

Help yourself to them; but when you want to use them for some serious purpose you will find yourself caught up in wrong or dubious assertions—the sort of thing that has set metaphysical systems against one another in their doctrines or in their arguments, destroying their claims to be believed.

Indeed, the very attempts to create a science of metaphysics were the first cause of early scepticism—a way of thinking in which reason attacks itself so violently that it could never have arisen except in complete despair about our ability to carry out reason’s most important designs. Men began to investigate reason itself, long before starting methodically to investigate nature ·in the physical sciences·. Even at that stage, reason had already been employed in connection with ordinary experience; and reason is always present to us, whereas laws of nature have to be laboriously sought out. So metaphysics floated to the top like foam, which dissolved the moment it was scooped off. But as soon as one lot of foam dissolved, more came frothing up to the surface. Some philosophers eagerly collected foam; some tried to show their wisdom by ridiculing the vain efforts of others; none looked for the cause of the foam down in the depths.

We are tired of dogmatism that teaches us nothing, and just as tired of scepticism that promises us nothing (not even permission to rest comfortably in ignorance). The knowledge we need is important, and that’s a challenge to us; but we have had centuries of bad experience with things we thought we knew through ‘pure reason’ that turned out not to be knowledge at all, and that fact makes us suspicious. ·So we are •under pressure to push on forwards, and also •nervous about doing so·. Where do we go from here? That depends on the answer to the question ‘Is metaphysics possible at all?’ We should try to answer this not by picking away sceptically at particular doctrines of this or that actual system of metaphysics—for we don’t yet admit that there are any systems of metaphysics—but by considering the concept of such a science.

In the Critique of Pure Reason I tackled this problem by looking into pure reason itself: by establishing the nature of reason, I was able to work out what its materials and methods must be. This is hard to do. It demands a reader who is resolved to think himself gradually into a system based on reason itself and on nothing else, aiming to develop knowledge out of that alone, without help from any fact. Because the present work is called Preliminaries, on the other hand, it ought to consist of preliminary exercises; they should aim not to •expound the science itself but rather to •show what’s needed for the science to be brought into existence. Preliminaries should try to get help from something that is already known to be reliable, from which one can confidently work back to the ultimate sources that aren’t yet known.

Although we can’t take it for granted that there is any such science as metaphysics, we can—fortunately—say with confidence that some pure synthetic a priori knowledge is real and that we already have it. I refer to pure mathematics and pure natural science. Each of these contains propositions that are everywhere recognized—partly through reason that shows them to be necessary and certain, and partly through universal agreement arising from experience (though not actually based on experience). So we have some a priori synthetic knowledge that is, at least, unchallenged; we don’t have to ask whether such knowledge is possible (for it is real), but only how it is possible. When we can answer that, we’ll know how to go about showing the possibility of all other kinds of synthetic a priori knowledge.

13

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant General Problems

5: The general problem: how can there be knowledge based on pure reason?
We have seen the vast difference between analytic and synthetic judgments. It is easy to see how there can be

analytic propositions:

they come purely from the law of contradiction. There is also no special problem about how there can be

synthetic propositions that are known a posteriori,

i.e. known from experience: experience itself is nothing but a continual joining together of perceptions, ·so it isn’t surprising that it enables us to join concepts in a synthetic way. Returning to an example used earlier, the synthetic proposition that some bodies are heavy can be established through experiences in which •perceptions of body are joined with •perceptions of weight·. What we do have a problem about is the possibility of

synthetic propositions that are known a priori.

Whatever makes this sort of knowledge possible, it isn’t the law of contradiction ·and it isn’t experience·, so we must search to find out what it is.

But we cannot rightly start by asking whether synthetic a priori propositions are possible. For there are plenty of them, really given to us with undisputed certainty; and as our present procedure involves starting with what we already know, we shall start from the premise that there is human a priori knowledge of some synthetic propositions. But then we still have to ask how this knowledge is possible, i.e. what makes it possible. When we know this, we can learn how to use such knowledge and can learn what its limits are. Stated precisely, then, the crucial question is this:

How is it possible to have a priori knowledge of synthetic propositions?

·In the title of this section· I expressed this as a question about ‘knowledge based on pure reason’. It wouldn’t have done any harm to use that same formulation here, for it must be clear to every reader that when I speak here of ‘knowledge based on pure reason’ I always mean knowledge of synthetic propositions, never of analytic ones; ·and of course knowledge through pure reason is always a priori·. [At this point Kant has a footnote commenting on the shift from the old senses of ‘analytic’ and ‘synthetic’ (explained on page 6 above) to his new senses for those terms.]

Metaphysics stands or falls with the solution to this problem. Someone may propound his metaphysical claims as plausibly as he likes, smothering us with conclusions piled on conclusions; but if he hasn’t first answered this question properly, we are entitled to say to him:

‘This is all pointless ungrounded philosophy and false “wisdom”. You purport to be using pure reason to create a priori knowledge, not by merely analysing concepts but by making new connections that don’t rest on the law of contradiction; and you think you have insight into these connections independently of all experience. But how do you get such insight? How can you justify your claims?’

He can’t answer by appealing to the common sense of mankind, for that isn’t evidence—it’s mere hearsay....

The question must be answered, but that is hard to do. One reason why an answer wasn’t attempted long ago is that a satisfactory answer to this one question demands much deeper, more persistent and more careful thought than goes into the most lengthy and ambitious metaphysical works ever published. (A weightier reason is that nobody thought to ask the question!) Every reader who looks hard at the problem will initially be frightened by how hard it is. Indeed, if it were not that there really is synthetic a priori knowledge, the thoughtful person would think such knowledge to be impossible. This is what happened to David

14

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant General Problems

Hume, although he didn’t put the question to himself in this general form (which is the form we need if we are to get an answer that is decisive for the whole of metaphysics). Hume asked an intelligent question: How can I arrive at a judgment in which one concept is connected necessarily with another, even though the one doesn’t contain the other? He thought it couldn’t be done; which led him to conclude that only experience can provide us with such connections. In other words, he thought that this supposed necessity (which is the same as this supposed a priori knowledge) is merely a long-standing habit of accepting something as true, and hence of taking •a necessity in our thought—·a mere mental compulsion·—to be •a necessity in the world.

If you want to complain about the toil and trouble that I am going to give you in solving this problem, I invite you to try solving it in an easier way! Perhaps that will make you grateful to the man who has taken this deep task over for you, and you may even come to be surprised—given how difficult the problem is—that the solution isn’t even harder than it is. I have had to work for many years •to solve this problem in its full scope—i.e. covering all the cases—and finally also •to be able to present it in the analytic form, as you will find it here. [This is the old sense of ‘analytic’, explained on page 6]

All metaphysicians are therefore solemnly and legally suspended from their business until they have satisfactorily answered the question: How is a priori knowledge of synthetic propositions possible? Only an answer to this will provide them with the credentials they must produce if we are to credit them with teaching us things in the name of pure reason. If they can’t produce those credentials, we—as reasonable men who have often been deceived—should flatly refuse to listen to them, without asking any more about what they are offering.

They may want to carry on their business not as a science but as an art of swaying people with pronouncements that are good for them and agreeable to ordinary common sense. They are entitled to ply this trade; but then they should speak the modest language of rational belief, admitting that they mustn’t claim to •know—and shouldn’t even •conjecture—anything about what lies beyond the bounds of possible experience. The most they can legitimately do is to •assume things; and even then they aren’t making assumptions for theoretical purposes (for they must renounce those), but solely for practical use, assuming whatever is needed to guide our thought and behaviour in everyday life. That’s their only chance of being useful and wise. It will be better, too, if they give up the name ‘metaphysician’; for metaphysicians, properly so-called, aim to be theoretical philosophers; they try to establish judgments a priori, which means necessary judgments; so they can’t fool around with conjectures. What they assert is science or it is nothing at all....

In now proceeding to the answer to the question ‘How is a priori knowledge of synthetic propositions possible?, according to the analytic [old sense] method in which we presuppose that such knowledge through pure reason is real, we can appeal to only two sciences, namely pure mathematics and pure natural science. Only these can represent objects to us in intuition. If one of them should yield an item of a priori knowledge, it could show that this knowledge is real by showing that it fits with the intuited object; and we could then work back from the reality of this knowledge to whatever it is that makes it possible.

In order to move on from these kinds of pure a priori knowledge, which are both real and grounded, to the possible kind of knowledge that we are seeking, namely to metaphysics as a science, we must take our question a little more broadly. As well as enquiring into •the possibility

15

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure mathematics possible?

of metaphysics as a science, we must also investigate •the natural human disposition to pursue such a science. That involves looking into the a priori thoughts that are uncritically accepted, developed, and called ‘metaphysics’. The truth of such thoughts is under suspicion, but the thoughts themselves are natural enough; they fall within the scope of our question because they involve the natural conditions out of which metaphysics arises as a science.

So our main problem splits into four questions, which will be answered one by one:

(1) How is pure mathematics possible?

(2) How is pure natural science possible?

(3) How is metaphysics possible in general?

(4) How is metaphysics possible as a science?

It may be seen that the solution of these problems, though chiefly designed to present the core of the Critique, also has an odd feature that is worth attending to separately. We are looking to reason itself for the sources of certain sciences, doing this so that from its performance we can assess reason’s powers as a faculty of a priori knowledge. This procedure also brings benefit to those sciences, in respect not of their content but of their proper use; and they throw light on the higher question about their common origin, while also giving an occasion better to explain their own nature.

Main transcendental Problem 1:

How is pure mathematics possible?

6
Mathematics is a great and proved domain of knowledge; it already has a large scope, and there’s no limit to how far it can be extended in the future; and its results are absolutely necessary and certain, which means that they owe nothing to experience. Mathematical propositions are pure products of reason, yet they are thoroughly synthetic. How can human reason create such knowledge wholly a priori? Doesn’t our mathematical faculty, which isn’t and can’t be based on experience, presuppose some basis for a priori knowledge? This basis must lie deeply hidden, but we might be able to discover it through its effects—i.e. through our mathematical knowledge—if we can track down that knowledge’s sources.

7

We find that all mathematical knowledge has this special feature: it must first exhibit its concept in intuition, doing this a priori in an intuition that isn’t empirical but pure. [See the explanation of ‘pure intuition’ on page 9.] Without resorting to a priori intuitions, mathematics can’t take a single step. So its judgments are always intuitive. (In contrast with philosophy, which has to be satisfied with conceptual judgments. Philosophy may illustrate its necessary doctrines through intuition, but can never deduce them from it.) This fact about mathematics points us to the absolutely basic

16

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure mathematics possible?

thing that makes mathematics possible, namely that it is grounded in pure intuitions in which it can construct all its concepts—that is, can represent them in a manner that is •concrete rather than abstract, and •a priori rather than empirical. If we can discover this pure intuition and what makes it possible, we will then be able to explain how there can be synthetic a priori propositions in pure mathematics, and thus how mathematics itself is possible. Empirical intuition provides us with experiences that enable us to connect concepts with other concepts, forming a posteriori judgments that are empirically certain. Pure intuition also lets us connect concepts with other concepts, but in their case the synthetic judgment is a priori certain and necessary, ·not merely empirically certain·. Empirical judgments contain only what we •happen to have encountered in •empirical intuition, whereas mathematical judgments contain what •must necessarily be met with in •pure intuition. ·The plates or coins or moons that I happen to have seen or felt may be significantly unlike the ones that you have encountered; but there can’t be any such difference between my a priori intuition of a circle and yours·. An a priori intuition is inseparably joined with the concept before all experience, independently of every particular perception.

8
Now we seem to have made the problem worse than ever, for now we have to ask: How can one intuit anything a priori? An intuition is a representation of a sort that ·ordinarily· depends directly on the presence of the object. ·There’s no problem about an intuition of an object that is present to one at the time, or of an object that has been present at an earlier time and is still remembered·. It seems impossible, though, to intuit something a priori without help from any outer stimulus. Such an intuition would have to occur without any object •being present or •having been present, to which the intuition could refer; and in that case it couldn’t be an intuition—·or so it seems·. We can form some concepts a priori, without being related in any immediate way to an object: we can do this with the concepts that contain only the thought of an object in general, without any detail—for example the concepts of quantity, cause, and so on. (Though even these have meaning for us only if we use them concretely, applying them to intuitions through which we confront actual instances of quantity and cause in our experience.) But how can an intuition of an object precede the object itself?

9

If our intuition had to represent things as they are in themselves, no intuition could ever take place a priori; intuition would be empirical every time. ·Here is why·. If an intuition takes place a priori, then no object of it is present and given to me; but if the object isn’t present and given to me, I can’t know what it is like in itself. Actually, even if an object is intuitively present to me, it is incomprehensible how I could know a thing as it is in itself, for a thing’s properties cannot migrate into my mind! ·Since I can’t get the thing’s own properties into my mind, the most I can do is to have in my mind my representations of them; but that means that I am taking in the thing not •as it is in itself but •as I perceive and think about it·. Never mind that just now; let us pretend that this is possible. My present point is that such an intuition wouldn’t take place a priori, i.e. before the object was presented to me; for if the object were not present, there would be nothing that connected my representation—·my intuition·—in any way with that object in particular.

There’s only one way to have an intuition that precedes the reality of the object, and thus occurs as a priori knowl-

17

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure mathematics possible?

edge. I could have such an intuition if it contained nothing but the form of my sensibility. ·My sensibility is my capacity for being affected by particular real things. Through it I come to have sensible intuitions. In any such transaction with an object, the faculty of sensibility makes its own contribution; the intuitions that occur in my mind depend not only on •what the objects are like but also on •the characteristic marks left on them by my faculty of sensibility; these constitute its form·. The form of my sensibility is available to me in advance of any of the impressions in which I am affected by objects. ·That’s because I know in advance that, whatever my particular experience turns out to be like, it will reflect the form of my sensibility; which is to say that· I can know a priori that I can intuit objects of the senses only in accordance with this form of sensibility. It follows •that there can be, ·and we can know·, propositions that concern merely this form of sensibility, •that such propositions are valid for objects of the senses, and •that they can’t be applied to anything except objects of our senses.

10
Thus it is only through the form of sensible intuition [= ‘form of sensibility’] that we can intuit things a priori. Such a priori knowledge, however, concerns objects only as they appear to us through our senses, and not as they may be in themselves. If a priori knowledge of synthetic propositions is to be possible, and we are to understand how it is possible, it must be subject to this ·limitation to how things •appear as distinct from how they •are in themselves·.

Now, space and time are the two intuitions on which pure mathematics bases all its judgments that present themselves as certain and necessary. Pure mathematics must construct its concepts on the basis of pure intuition, ·i.e. the kind of intuition that is conducted a priori, with no reliance on the senses·. Mathematics can’t proceed analytically by dissecting concepts, but only synthetically; so without pure intuition it can’t take a single step, since only pure intuition provides the material for synthetic a priori judgments. Geometry is based on the pure intuition of space. Arithmetic forms its own concepts of numbers by successively adding units in time. Our representations of space and time are merely intuitions, however, ·rather than concepts·; and here is why. Start with empirical intuitions of bodies and their changes, and strip them of everything empirical—i.e. everything you know about them through sensation—and what you are left with is space and time. These are therefore pure intuitions. They must be involved in all empirical intuitions, and can never be omitted, because they underlie everything empirical. But just because they are themselves pure a priori intuitions, they must be mere forms of our sensibility. They precede all our empirical intuition, i.e. all our perceptions of real objects; through them we can know objects a priori, though indeed only as they appear to us ·and not as they are in themselves·.

11

That solves the problem about how mathematics is possible. Pure mathematics is possible only because it bears on mere objects of the senses. The empirical intuition of such objects is grounded a priori in a pure intuition of space and time, and this pure intuition is merely the form of our sensibility. It precedes the actual appearance of objects, since it makes it possible for them to appear to us. ·Objects can appear to us only through our sensibility; and anything we get through our sensibility bears the marks of the form of sensibility·. Our a priori intuitions don’t involve the content of the appearance, the element of sensation in it, for that belongs to the empirical realm; they involve the form of the

18

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure mathematics possible?

appearance, namely space and time. If you suspect that space and time are features of things in themselves rather than mere features of how things relate to sensibility, then tell me: How in that case could we know a priori—in advance of any experience of things—what the intuitions of space and time must be like? Yet we do know this. There’s no problem about this knowledge so long as space and time are taken to be nothing more than formal conditions of our sensibility, and the objects are taken to be merely appearances. For then the pure intuition that embodies the form of sensibility can be understood as coming from us—from our side of the transaction with objects—which means that it can be had a priori rather than empirically.

12
To clarify and confirm all this, we need only to look at how geometers do (and absolutely must) go about proving that two figures are completely congruent, meaning that one can be replaced at all points by the other. All such proofs ultimately come down to this: The two figures coincide with each other; which is obviously a synthetic proposition resting on immediate intuition. This intuition must be given pure and a priori, otherwise the proposition couldn’t hold as absolutely certain and necessary. If it rested on an empirical intuition, it would only have empirical certainty, and would mean: So far as our experience has shown us, this proposition has held until now. That space has three dimensions, and that no space could have more, is built on the proposition that not more than three lines can intersect at right angles in a point. This proposition can’t be shown from concepts, but rests immediately on intuition, and indeed (because it is necessary and certain), on pure a priori intuition. That a line can be drawn to infinity, or a series of changes continued to infinity, presupposes a representation of space and time as not bounded by anything; and this can only come from intuition, and could never be inferred from concepts. Thus mathematics is really grounded in pure a priori intuitions; they are what enable it to establish synthetic propositions as necessary and certain.

[In this paragraph Kant speaks of a certain ‘transcendental deduction’ of certain concepts. A ‘deduction’ is a theoretically grounded or justified list; it is ‘transcendental’ in Kant’s main sense of that word if it is based on considerations about what makes some kind of a priori knowledge possible]. Hence our transcendental deduction of the concepts of space and time—·i.e. our establishing that whatever is given to us in experience must be in space and in time·—also explains the possibility of pure mathematics. If we didn’t have such a deduction, and couldn’t take it for granted that whatever is presented our senses—whether outer (space) or inner (time)—is experienced by us only as it appears, not as it is in itself, we could still do mathematics but we wouldn’t have any insight into what it is.

13

If you can’t help thinking that space and time are real qualities attached to things in themselves, try your intelligence on the following paradox. When it has defeated you, you may be free from prejudices at least for a few moments, and then you may be more favourably disposed towards the view that space and time are mere forms of our sensible intuition.

If two things are completely the same in every respect of quantity and quality that can be known about each separately, you would expect it to follow that each can be replaced by the other in all cases and in all respects, without the exchange causing any recognizable difference. That is the case with two-dimensional figures in geometry, but not with three-dimensional ones: it can happen that two of them have a complete inner agreement yet also have an outer relation

19

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure mathematics possible?

such that one can’t be replaced by the other.... What can be more like my hand, and more equal in all points, than its image in the mirror? Yet I can’t put such a hand as is seen in the mirror in the place of its original: for if the original was a right hand, the hand in the mirror is a left hand, which could never serve as a substitute for the other. Here are no inner differences that any understanding could think—·that is, no differences that can be expressed in concepts·—and yet the differences are inner as far as the senses tell us, for the left hand can’t be enclosed in the same boundaries as the right (they aren’t congruent), despite all their equality and similarity. For example, the glove of one hand can’t be used on the other. So the two hands are intrinsically different in a manner that can’t be captured in concepts—it can only be shown through the fact that a spatial region that exactly contains one won’t contain the other.

How can this be? Well, these objects are not representations of the things as they are in themselves, but are sensible intuitions, i.e. appearances, which come about through the relation to •our sensibility of •certain things that are unknown in themselves. When this sensibility is exercised as outer intuition, its form is space; and the intrinsic nature of any region of space is fixed by how that region relates to space as a whole, the one big space of which it is a part. (The part is made possible by the whole: ·a small region of space can exist only if there’s a larger region of which it is a part·. This never happens with things in themselves, but it can happen with mere appearances.) Thus, to make intelligible to ourselves the difference between similar and equal yet incongruent things (e.g. snails winding opposite ways), we must relate them to the right and the left hand. That means that it must be done through intuition; it can’t be done through any concept. ·That is, it must be done by showing, and can’t be done by telling·.

Note I

The propositions of geometry aren’t mere fantasies that might have nothing to do with real objects. Pure mathematics, and in particular pure geometry, is objectively valid, but only in application to objects of the senses. When we represent such objects through our sensibility, we represent them not as they are in themselves but only as they appear to us. So they must have any features that are conferred on them by the form of our sensibility—and in particular they must be in space, because space is simply the form of all outer appearances. Outer appearances are possible only through sensibility, the form of which is the basis for geometry; so outer appearances must conform to what geometry says about them.

If the senses had to represent objects as they are in themselves, the situation would be quite different. For then the facts about our representation of space would provide no guarantee about how things are in reality. The space of the geometer—a mere representation—would be a fiction with no objective validity, for there would be no reason why things should have to conform to the picture that we make of them in advance of being acquainted with them. But if

•this picture, or rather this formal intuition, comes from the essential nature of our sensibility, through which objects must be given to us,

and if

•what this sensibility represents aren’t things in themselves but only their appearances,

it then becomes conceivable—indeed undeniable—that

•all outer objects of the world of the senses must agree exactly with the propositions of geometry.

It is a remarkable fact that at one time mathematicians who were also philosophers began to have doubts about

20

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure mathematics possible?

their geometrical propositions—not about whether they were true of space, but about they held good in application to nature, that is to things in space. They feared that a line in nature might consist of physical points, in which case the space of the natural object would consists of simple parts, although the space the geometer thinks about can’t be like that. ·That is, they feared that the space of natural objects might not be infinitely divisible, and might instead be made up of atoms of space, so to speak; whereas geometrical space is infinitely divisible·. They didn’t realize that the spatiality of outer things must exactly conform to the space the geometer thinks about, because:

•all objects in space are mere appearances, i.e. not things in themselves but representations of our sensible intuition; and

•the space the geometer thinks about—space in thought, we might call it—is just a form of our faculty of sensible representation.

·Putting these two together: an outer thing must be given to us through our sensibility, so it must conform to the form—the essential nature—of our sensibility, so it must obey the propositions of geometry·. This is the only way to defend the objective validity of geometrical propositions against shallow metaphysical attacks....

Note II

Anything that is to be presented to us as an object must be given in intuition. But all our intuition happens through the senses—the understanding doesn’t intuit anything. Now, we have just seen that the senses never ever enable us to know things as they are in themselves; all we encounter through the senses are the appearances of things; and these appearances are mere representations of sensibility. What follows is this: All bodies, along with the space that contains them, are merely representations in us, and exist only in our thoughts. ‘Isn’t this blatant idealism?’ ·No, it is not, and I now explain why·. Idealism says this:

Only minds exist, and the other things we think we perceive are only representations in us, with no external object corresponding to them.

I say the contrary:

Things are given to us as objects of our senses, existing outside us, but we know nothing of what they are in themselves; all we know are their appearances, i.e. the representations they cause in us by affecting our senses.

So I say that there are bodies outside us—i.e. things of whose nature in themselves we know nothing, knowing them only through our representations of them. We call such a thing a ‘body’, meaning ‘the appearance to us of an unknown thing which is nevertheless real’. Can this be called idealism? It is the very opposite of it!

Long before Locke’s time, but more so afterwards, it was generally accepted that although outer things are perfectly real, many of their properties belong not to things in themselves but only to their appearances. These properties, including heat, colour, taste etc., were agreed to have no existence of their own outside our representations. I go further. I count also as mere appearances the remaining qualities of bodies—the ‘primary’ qualities of extension, place, and space in general with all that depends on it (impenetrability or materiality, shape, etc.). I have weighty reasons for this view, and there isn’t the slightest reason to reject it. A man who holds that •colours are aspects of the sense of sight and not qualities of the object in itself should not on that account be called an idealist. So I should not be called idealist either, merely because I hold that •all the qualities that make up

21

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure mathematics possible?

the intuition of a body belong merely to its appearance. This doctrine of mine doesn’t destroy the existence of the thing that appears, as genuine idealism does; it merely says that we can’t through our senses know the thing as it is in itself.

What would I have to say to stop people from accusing me of idealism? It wouldn’t be enough for me to say:

Our representations of outer objects are perfectly appropriate, given how our sensibility relates to those objects;

for that’s what I have said ·and still the accusations continue·. I would also have to say:

Our representations of outer objects are exactly like the objects themselves.

But that, to me, makes as little sense as the assertion that the sensation of red is like the property of the pigment that causes this sensation in me.

Note III

‘When you admit the ideality of space and time, you turn the whole world of the senses into pure illusion’—it is easy to foresee that this complaint will be levelled, and easy to show, from what I have said, that it is futile. At first all philosophical insight into the nature of knowledge through the senses was tainted by taking sensibility to be a mode of representation which, though confused, lets us know things as they are without our being able to get the whole content of this representation clear in our minds. ·Replacing that disastrous mistake·, I showed •that sensibility has to be understood in terms not of this logical clear/obscure distinction but of something genetic, having to do with where knowledge comes from—sense-perception represents things not as they are but only the mode in which they affect our senses—and consequently •that what sense-perception provides for the understanding to think about are appearances only, not things themselves. Now that I have given this necessary corrective, it would be an unpardonable misunderstanding—almost a deliberate one—to say that my doctrine turns all the contents of the world of the senses into pure illusion.

When an •appearance is given to us, it is up to us to choose how to •judge the matter. The •appearance depends on the senses, but the •judgment depends on the understanding, and the only question is whether a given judgment is true or not. But the difference between truth and dreaming isn’t ascertained by •the nature of the representations in question (for they are the same whether or not one is dreaming), but by •their inter-connections according to the rules that bring representations together under the concept of an object and settle whether or not they can co-exist in a single experience. And it isn’t the appearances’ doing if our mind takes illusion for truth, i.e. if it takes the intuition through which we are given an object to be a concept of the thing or even to be the thing itself—these being items that the understanding can think ·but the senses can’t present·. The senses represent the planets to us as moving backwards and forwards, and in this there’s neither falsehood nor truth, because as long as we take this ·planetary· path to be nothing but appearance, we make no judgment about the objective nature of the planets’ movements. But when the understanding isn’t on its guard against this subjective representation’s being taken to be objective, a false judgment can easily arise—‘They seem to be moving backward’, we may say. The illusion mustn’t be charged to •the senses, however, but to •the understanding, whose job it is to render an objective judgment on the basis of the appearances.

Thus, even if we gave no thought to where our representations come from, when we connect our sensory intuitions (whatever their content) in space and in time, according to

22

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure mathematics possible?

the rules governing the way all knowledge hangs together in experience, we will encounter illusion if we are negligent and truth if we are careful. The difference between illusion and truth turns on how sensory representations are handled in the understanding, not on where they come from. In the same way, if I

•take all the representations of the senses to be nothing but appearances,

•take space and time also to be appearances and as a mere form of sensibility that isn’t to be met with outside its borders, and

•use these representations only in relation to possible experience,

then my regarding them as appearances won’t involve me in the slightest temptation to think in terms of error or illusion; for appearances can hang together according to rules of truth in experience. ·Whether they do so hang together is something I can determine without bringing in their ultimate status, i.e. the question of whether space and its contents are appearances·. That’s how all the propositions of geometry hold good for space as well as for all the objects of the senses and consequently of all possible experience, whether I •take space to be a mere form of the sensibility or •regard it as something that clings the things themselves; though it is only in the former case that I can grasp how I can know a priori that these propositions are true of all the objects of external intuition. Apart from that one matter of knowing how geometry can be known a priori, all my dealings with space and its contents are just what they would have been if I hadn’t departed from the common view.

But there’s a way in which an error could arise. If I pass off space and time as qualities inherent in things in themselves, there will be nothing to stop me from thinking that those two concepts would hold good for the same things that they now apply to even if my senses were different and couldn’t present those things to me; and so I shall be led to venture to carry my notions of space and time out beyond all possible experience; and then I can fall victim to an illusion that would generate a grave error, namely that of passing off as valid for everything something that is merely a subjective condition of the intuition of things and valid only for all objects of sense, i.e. for all possible experience. I would be led into this error by thinking of space and time as containing •things in themselves, rather than as restricting them to the •conditions of experience.

So my doctrine of the ideality of space and of time ·(i.e. my doctrine that space and time are appearances) comes nowhere near to turning the whole world of the senses into mere illusion. I shall offer two graphic illustrations of this. Firstly, the doctrine· is so far from •turning the sensible world into illusion that it is the only means of •saving something from being regarded as mere illusion; what it saves is one of the most important kinds of knowledge (the kind that mathematics propounds a priori), which the doctrine guarantees does apply to actual objects. ·Here is why it is the only way of securing this result·. Without the ideality of space and time it would be quite impossible to decide whether the intuitions of space and time—which we don’t take from any experience, and which nevertheless lie in our representations a priori ·so that we take them to every experience·—aren’t mere phantoms thrown up by our brain, with nothing adequately corresponding to them, in which case geometry itself is a mere illusion; whereas we have been able to prove geometry’s unquestionable validity with respect to all the objects of the sensible world, just because they are mere appearances.

Secondly, it is so far from being the case that these principles of mine turn the truth of experience into mere ·sensory

23

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure mathematics possible?

illusion· by making appearances of the representations of the senses, that they are rather the only means of preventing the transcendental illusion by which metaphysics has hitherto been deceived, leading to an infantile snatching at bubbles by metaphysicians who took appearances—which are mere representations—to be things in themselves. [By ‘transcendental illusion’ Kant here means something like ‘abstract philosophical illusion’. His more special sense of ‘transcendental’, explained near the end of section 12, will come up again in the next paragraph.] That illusion is what brought on stage the remarkable antinomy [= ‘contradiction’] of reason that I shall return to in sections 51–3. All it takes to clear up this ·internal contradiction into which reason falls· is a single observation: that appearance, as long as it is employed in experience, produces truth, but as soon as it goes beyond bounds of experience and consequently becomes transcendent [= ‘freed from any constraints having to do with the senses’; not the same as ‘transcendental’ in either of the latter’s senses], it produces nothing but illusion.

Thus, in letting things as we confront them through the senses retain their actuality, and limiting our sensory intuition of these things only by saying this:

In no respect—not even in the pure intuitions of space and of time—do they represent anything more than mere appearance of those things, never their constitution in themselves,

I am not imputing to nature a sweeping illusion. [For the phrase ‘pure intuition’, see the explanation on pages 9-9.] My rejection of all such imputations is so obviously valid and convincing that one might think there was no need for it. And there wouldn’t be, if it weren’t for the existence of incompetent judges who—liking to have an old name for everything that diverges from their own wrong-headed though common opinions, and always clinging to the letter of what is said with no thought for its spirit—are ready to deform and distort well-defined notions by putting their own follies in the place of them. I have myself given this theory of mine the name •‘transcendental idealism’, but that can’t entitle anyone to muddle it either with the •empirical idealism of Descartes or with the •mystical and visionary idealism of Berkeley. (My critique ·of pure reason· contains the proper antidote to phantoms like Berkeley’s. As for Descartes: all he had was an insoluble problem, which led him to think that everyone is at liberty to deny the existence of the corporeal world because it could never be proved satisfactorily.) Doubting the existence of things constitutes ‘idealism’ in the ordinary sense; but the doctrine I have labelled as ‘idealism’—·in the phrase ‘transcendental idealism’·—doesn’t concern the existence of things, since it never entered my head to doubt that they exist. Rather, it concerns the sensory representation of things, especially of space and time. All I have shown regarding space and time, and thus more generally regarding all appearances, is that they aren’t •things but mere •features of how we represent things, and aren’t qualities of things in themselves. But the word ‘transcendental’ was meant to guard against this misconception. (For me, ‘transcendental’ signifies a reference to our knowledge not •of things but only •of our ability to have knowledge. ·I characterized my idealism as ‘transcendental’ because it offers an explanation of how we can know certain things a priori·.) But rather than furthering the misunderstanding, I now retract the label ‘transcendental’ and ask that my idealism be called ‘critical’. But if it really is an objectionable idealism to convert actual things (not appearances) into mere representations, by what name shall we call the idealism that goes the opposite way and changes mere representations into things? It may, I think, be called ‘dreaming idealism’, in contrast to the former, which may be called ‘visionary’. Both are refuted by my transcendental idealism—or, better, critical idealism.

24

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure natural science possible?

Main transcendental problem 2:

How is pure natural science possible?

14
·The word ‘nature’ has two senses. I shall use it in what I shall later call its ‘formal’ sense in this section and the next; and then in section 16 I shall start to use ‘nature’ in what I call its ‘material’ sense. Both will be in play in section 36·. Nature is the existence of things insofar as it is governed by universal ·causal· laws. If this meant the existence of things in themselves, we couldn’t know nature either •a priori or •a posteriori. ·One way of knowing things a priori is knowing them through the analysis of concepts·. We couldn’t know nature as it is in itself in that way, because knowledge of what things are like in themselves can never come from analytically dissecting our concepts: we aren’t asking what is contained in our concept of the thing, but rather about what is added to this concept in the reality of the thing itself. ·Some synthetic propositions can be known a priori because their truth is assured by the nature of our understanding, somewhat in the way that mathematical truths can be known a priori because our sensibility assures their truth. But this is also not applicable to the supposed ‘knowledge of nature as it is in itself’, which we are discussing·. My understanding ·has an effect on how things appear to me, but it· can’t dictate what things are like in themselves. They don’t have to conform to it; so if I am to know about things in themselves, my understanding must conform to them, ·not vice versa·. That means that I couldn’t know about them until they had somehow been presented to me; which is to say that I couldn’t know them a priori.

Nor could I have a posteriori knowledge—·i.e. knowledge through experience·—of the nature of things in themselves. If I am to bring things under ·causal· laws, these laws must apply to them necessarily, and experience could never show me how things must be—only what there is and how it is. So it can never teach me the nature of things in themselves.

15

Yet we do have pure natural science, which discovers a priori certain laws that govern all of nature, and discovers them to be necessary. One part of it is what we call ‘general natural science’, which is a preliminary to empirical physics. In this we find •mathematics applied to appearances ·on the basis of •intuition·, and also •conceptual principles that make up the •philosophical part of pure knowledge of nature. ·A couple of qualifications should be mentioned·. •It isn’t strictly pure, because there are things in it that are based on experience, such as the concepts of motion, of impenetrability, of inertia. •Nor is it ‘general’ in the strictest sense, because it concerns only the objects of the outer senses, whereas a truly general natural science would apply laws to the whole of nature—not only outer objects (physics) but also inner ones (psychology).

Still, some principles of this general physics are strictly universal, for instance the propositions ‘Substance is permanent’ and ‘Everything that happens is determined by a cause according to constant laws’. These really are universal laws of nature that we can know a priori. So pure natural science does exist, and we have to ask: How is it possible?

16

I now want to use the word ‘nature’ in a broader sense, its material sense, in which it refers to ·every aspect of· •the totality of all objects of ·possible· experience, i.e. the whole

25

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure natural science possible?

perceivable world. Up to this point I have been using ‘nature’ in its narrower sense, making it refer only to •the way all things fall under the system of laws.

The perceivable world is all we have to concern ourselves with. If we tried to learn about things that couldn’t be objects of experience, we would have to think about them through concepts that couldn’t be illustrated or cashed out in terms of any possible experience. Such concepts would be empty; we ·could play around with them in our minds, but· we could never know whether they applied to anything rather than being mere fictions contrived by us. Knowledge of something that couldn’t be an object of experience would be supernatural ·in the quite literal sense of being above nature·, and the supernatural is no part of our present concern. The knowledge that we care about is the sort which, although it •precedes experience ·rather than •arising out of it·, can •be confirmed by experience.

17
It has just been shown that the laws of nature can never be known a priori of objects considered in themselves (rather than in terms of possible experience of them). But we aren’t concerned here with things in themselves; their properties don’t interest us. Our concern is with things considered as objects of a possible experience, and the totality of these things is what we here call ‘nature’ in the broad sense. Now, we are going to enquire into what enables us to have a priori knowledge of nature, and we have to choose between two ways of framing our problem.

•How can we know a priori that experience itself must conform to law?

•How can we know a priori that things (considered as objects of experience) must conform to law?

The two questions turn out to be equivalent. The laws that govern our •ways of knowing also govern •the objects that we know, as long as these are considered as objects of experience and not as they are in themselves. There are two things we can say:

(1) A judgment of perception can’t count as valid for experience unless the mind in which it occurs conforms to the following law: When any event is observed to happen, it is connected with some earlier event that it follows according to a universal rule.

(2) Everything that we experience as happening must be caused to happen.

It makes no difference which we say: they come down to the same thing.

Still, we’ll do better if we start with (1). We can make a priori discoveries about what the conditions are under which experience is possible, but we can’t make such discoveries about laws that apply to things in themselves independently of our experience of them. So our only way of studying •the nature of things a priori is by studying •the conditions under which experience is possible, including the universal laws of the mind that make it possible. ·What I am saying, in effect, is that we should tackle (2) by tackling (1)·. If I chose to start with (2), I would risk falling into error by imagining that I was talking about nature in itself. That would set me whirling around in endless circles, trying in vain to discover laws governing things that aren’t given to me ·as things are given to me in experience·.

So our only concern here will be with experience and with what universal conditions have to be satisfied for experience to be possible—conditions that we can know about a priori. On that basis we are to establish the characteristics of nature as the whole object of all possible experience. You will understand, I think, that I am not talking about •rules that we learn by observing a nature that is already given,

26

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure natural science possible?

for such rules already presuppose experience; so I am not talking about how through experience we can study the laws of nature, for laws learned in that way wouldn’t be laws a priori, and wouldn’t supply us with a pure natural science. Rather, my topic is the question of how •the conditions that we can know a priori have to be satisfied if experience is to be possible are at the same time •the sources from which all the universal laws of nature must be derived.

18
The first thing to make clear is this: although all judgments of experience are empirical (i.e. have their ground in immediate sense-perception), the converse doesn’t hold: not all empirical judgments are judgments of experience. That’s because a judgment of experience must contain more than merely an empirical component, given through sensory •intuition. It must also involve particular •concepts that ·don’t come from sense-experience, but· originate a priori in the pure understanding—concepts under which every •perception must first be brought and then by means of them changed into •experience.

Empirical judgments fall into two kinds: •judgments of experience and •judgments of perception. The former are objectively valid. They are based on immediate sense perception, but they add to it: when something is given to sensible intuition, a •judgment of experience applies to it certain special concepts that pure understanding gives rise to, completely independently of experience. Perceptions are turned into experience by being brought under these concepts. •Judgments of perception are only subjectively valid: all they need is that the perceptions hang together in the right way in mind of the person concerned (the subject); they don’t involve any of the pure concepts of the understanding.

All our judgments start out by being judgments of perception, and thus as valid only for us (i.e. for our subject). Later on we make them refer to an object, and mean them to be valid for all people and for ourselves at all times. A judgment’s being about an object connects with its being universally valid, and the connection runs both ways. On the one hand: if my judgment is about an object, then anyone else’s judgment about that same object should agree with mine, which is to say that mine must be universally valid. On the other hand: if a judgment of mine is universally valid, agreeing with the judgments of all others, this agreement has to be explained. The explanation must be that the judgments agree with one another because they all refer to the same object.

19

So something’s being true of an object is equivalent to its having to be the same for everyone: •objective validity and •necessary universal validity stand or fall together. When we regard a judgment as universally valid and necessary, we mean by this that it is objectively valid, even though we don’t know the object in itself. We know the object through this judgment—i.e. through the judgment that anyone who has perceptions of kind F with respect to the object must also have perceptions of kind G. So judgments of experience get their objective validity not from immediate knowledge of the object but from how perceptions are connected with one another; and these connections come not from anything empirical but from pure concepts of the understanding. ·They can’t have an empirical basis because they involve necessity; the judgments in question say that certain perceptions must be associated with certain others; and experience never tells us what must be the case·. The object in itself always remains unknown; but it gives us perceptions through our

27

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure natural science possible?

sensibility, and these are connected; and when a concept of the understanding settles it that the connection is universally valid, the result is an objective judgment—something that doesn’t merely report on perceptions but says things about an object.

Here is an illustration. That the room is warm, sugar is sweet, wormwood is nasty, are merely subjectively valid judgments.^1 ·In making such judgments·, I don’t expect that I shall find the room to be warm or sugar sweet or wormwood nasty at all times, or that everyone else will find them to be so. All that such a judgment does is to connect two sensations to a single subject (myself) at a particular time; they aren’t intended to be valid of the object. I call them judgments of perception. Matters are quite different with judgments of experience. What experience teaches me under certain circumstances it must teach me and everybody always; its validity isn’t limited to one person or one time; so its judgments are objectively valid. For example, when I say that air is elastic, this starts out as a judgment of •perception, which merely connects two of my sensations to one another. But if I mean it as a judgment of •experience, I require that this connection be universally valid, i.e. that I and everybody must always conjoin the same sensations under the same circumstances.

20
So experience is a product of the senses and of the understanding, and we have to discover how these two faculties combine to produce it. One of them is simply intuition of which I am conscious, i.e. perception, which belongs merely to the senses. The second element that goes into experience is judging, which belongs entirely to the understanding. There are two kinds of judging. (1) I may merely compare perceptions and conjoin them in a consciousness of my state. (2) I may conjoin them in consciousness in general. What I have in (1) is merely a judgment of perception, a subjectively valid connecting of perceptions in my mind, without reference to an object. People often think that all you need for experience is to compare perceptions and to connect them in your consciousness by means of judgments about them; but they are wrong. That procedure doesn’t lead to judgments that are universally valid and necessary, and that’s what is needed for objective validity and for real experience.

To turn perception into experience, therefore, we need (2) a different kind of judging. An intuition (or perception) must be brought under a pure a priori concept of the understanding; this concept settles what kind or form of judgment can be made about this intuition; thus it connects the individual person’s intuition with a frame of mind that •anyone must be in when making judgments about such intuitions; and in this way it provides the empirical judgments with •universal validity. Such a concept, I repeat, merely fixes a general way in which judgments can be brought to bear on the intuition. It might be the concept of cause, for instance. To bring this to bear on one’s intuition (or perception) of air, for example, is to be disposed to make hypothetical judgments of the form ‘If air is compressed, then...’.

Before a judgment of perception can become a judgment of experience, the perception must be brought under such a concept of the understanding—as when air is brought under

^1 Actually, these judgments of perception could never become judgments of experience, even if a concept of the understanding were added. They refer merely to feeling, which is incurably subjective and can never become objective. Still, they serve my immediate purpose of illustrating judgments that are merely subjectively valid, involving no relation to an object. In the next footnote I shall give an example of judgments of perception that can become judgments of experience.

28

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure natural science possible?

the concept of cause, yielding judgments of the form ‘If air is..., then...’. The judgment that air is elastic can become universally valid, and thus be turned into a judgment of experience, because of certain preliminary judgments that bring the intuition of air under the concept of cause and effect. (An easier example is: ‘When the sun shines on the stone, it grows warm.’ This is a mere judgment of perception and contains no necessity, no matter how often I and others may have perceived this. But if I say ‘The sun warms the stone’, ·which means that the sun causes the stone to become warm·, the concept of cause is added to the perception and connects the concept of warmth necessarily with the concept of sunshine.)

If all our objectively valid synthetic judgments are analysed, it turns out that they never consist in mere intuitions that are brought together in a judgment through mere comparison. Always, a pure concept of the understanding has been added to the concepts that are abstracted from intuition. This applies even to the judgments of pure mathematics, including its simplest axioms. The principle ‘A straight line is the shortest path between two points’ presupposes that the line has been brought under the concept of size. That concept doesn’t come from intuition; it has its seat solely in the understanding, and serves to get the intuition (of the line) ready for quantitative judgments to be made about it.

21
If we are to prove that experience is possible insofar as it rests on pure a priori concepts of the understanding, we need a •list of these concepts. We arrive at this list through a •list of basic kinds of judgments that we can make, because the pure concepts of the understanding run parallel to those judgment kinds....

Logical table of judgments
1 | 2
QUANTITY | QUALITY
Universal | Affirmative
Particular | Negative
Singular | Infinite
  |
3 | 4
RELATION | MODALITY
Categorical | Problematic
Hypothetical | Assertoric
Disjunctive | Apodictic

Table of concepts of the understanding
1 | 2
QUANTITY | QUALITY
Unity (measure) | Reality
Plurality (size) | Negation
Totality (whole) | Limitation
  |
3 | 4
RELATION | MODALITY
Substance | Possibility
Cause | Esistence
Causal interaction | Necessity

29

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure natural science possible?

Pure physical table of the universal principles of natural science
1 | 2
Axioms of Intuition | Anticipations of Perception
3 | 4
Analogies of Experience | Postulates of empirical thinking generally

* * * * *

21a
If we are to grasp all this in a single thought, I must first remind you that our topic isn’t where experience comes from but what experience contains. The former topic belongs to empirical psychology, though even that wouldn’t suffice without the latter topic, which belongs to the critique of knowledge and especially of the understanding.

Experience consists of intuitions, which belong to the sensibility, and of judgments, which are entirely a work of the understanding. But the •judgments that the understanding forms from sensory intuitions alone are not •judgments of experience. They merely connect the perceptions as given in sensory intuition, while a judgment of experience must express •what is contained in experience in general, and not merely •what is contained in the mere perception (which has only subjective validity). So a judgment of experience must •add something to •the sensuous intuition and •the logical tie-up of that intuition to others in a judgment (after it has been made universal by comparing ·this intuition with others·). It must •add something implying that the synthetic judgment is necessary and therefore universally valid—·not merely universal in the weak way that comes from comparing intuitions with one another·. This added element can only be the concept that represents the intuition as a suitable subject for one form of judgment rather than another.

22

Summing up: The business of the senses is to intuit; that of the understanding, to think. Now, thinking is unifying representations in a consciousness, and this can be done either in •a contingent and subjective way or in •a manner that is necessary and objective. Since thinking is the same as judging, it follows that judgments are of two kinds: a judgment may be merely

•subjective (when representations are inter-related only with respect to one person’s consciousness),

or it may be

•objective (when the representations are related with respect to consciousness in general, i.e. with respect to every possible conscious mind).

The basic kinds of judgment are simply possible ways of unifying representations in a consciousness; and when they serve as concepts, they are concepts of the necessary unifica-

30

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure natural science possible?

tion of representations in any consciousness, which means that the judgments that involve them are objectively valid. In experience, perceptions are synthetically but necessarily connected in a consciousness; for them to be connected in this manner, they must be brought under pure concepts of the understanding; so these concepts are required if any judgments of experience are to be made.^2

23
•Judgments can be seen as ways of unifying representations in a consciousness. Looked at in this way, they are •rules. When they represent the perceptions as necessarily united, they are a priori rules; and when they stand on their own feet, not being derived from something more fundamental, they can be called ‘principles’. The broad kinds of judgment that bring intuitions under pure concepts of the understanding aren’t derived from anything; they stand on their own feet. So they’re the a priori principles of possible experience.

Now the •principles of possible experience are at the same time •universal laws of nature, which can be known a priori. This solves the problem raised by our second question, ‘How is pure natural science possible?’ Here is how. Logic offers us only one set of basic kinds of judgment (and thus one set of basic rules); no other is possible. These constitute a logical system. The concepts that emerge from it, which make synthetic necessary judgments possible, constitute a transcendental system [meaning, roughly, ‘a system that has to do with grounds for a priori knowledge’.] And, lastly, the principles according to which these concepts are applied to all appearances constitute a physical system, i.e. a system of nature. This system precedes all empirical knowledge of nature, and is what first makes such knowledge possible; so it can properly be called universal and pure natural science.

24

Of the physical principles listed in section 21, the first brings all phenomena, as intuitions in space and time, under the concept of quantity, which makes it a principle governing the application of mathematics to experience. The second principle takes up the genuinely empirical element, namely sensation, which signifies what is real in intuitions. It doesn’t bring sensation directly under the concept of quantity, because sensation isn’t an intuition that contains either space or time, though it places the sensed object in both space and time. But still there’s a quantifiable difference between sense-representation and a total absence of intuition in time, the difference between reality and zero. For we can conceive of intermediate degrees separating

any given degree of •light from darkness,

any degree of •heat from absolute cold,

any degree of •weight from absolute lightness,

any degree of •fullness of space from total vacuum;

^2 But how does this proposition that Judgments of experience require that perceptions be brought together necessarily square with my often-made statement that Experience as a posteriori knowledge can only provide contingent judgments? When I say that experience teaches me something, I mean only that I learn something from the perception that lies in experience—for example, that

Heat always follows the shining of the sun on a stone

—and to that extent the proposition of experience is always accidental ·or contingent·. The proposition that

This heat necessarily follows the shining of the sun

is indeed contained in the judgment of experience (by means of the concept of cause), but it is not a fact learned from experience. On the contrary, this addition of the concept of cause to perception is what creates experience in the first place.

31

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure natural science possible?

just as there are intermediate degrees—as small as you like—separating

•consciousness from total unconsciousness (psychological darkness).

So there’s no perception that can prove an absolute absence; for instance, there’s no psychological darkness that can’t be considered as a kind of consciousness, which is merely relatively dark, by comparison with some other stronger consciousness—and that’s how it is in all cases of sensation. Sensation is what gives each empirical representation (each appearance) its own particular flavour. ·It might be thought to be all content, with no form, and so not to be something that the understanding could say anything about in advance·. But the account I have been giving shows how the understanding can •anticipate even sensations—·i.e. •say something about them in advance of their actually occurring·—by means of the principle Every sensation has a degree, from which it follows that what’s real in all phenomena has a degree. This is the second application of mathematics to natural science.

·In discussing those two (sets of) principles of natural science, I have been implicitly discussing the corresponding (sets of) concepts, listed just before the list of principles in section 21. In the next section I shall take up the other two sets of concepts, and their associated principles·.

25
In the table of the concepts of the understanding, one of the headings is Relation. This refers not to mathematical relations, but rather to dynamic ones (relations having to do with how things exist in time). ·Firstly·, appearances must be brought under the concept of •substance; this is the concept of a thing, and any judgment about what exists must involve it. Secondly, when appearances involve events following one another in time, they must be brought under the concept of •cause and effect. Thirdly, judgments of experience about things that exist together must involve the concept of •two-way causal interaction. [Kant’s word for this is Gemeinschaft, which is usually but unhelpfully translated by ‘community’.] Thus a priori principles are involved in objectively valid though empirical judgments; they are needed if we are to have real experience, which connects objects in nature. These principles are the real laws of nature, and can be called ‘dynamic’.

Finally, judgments of experience include ·ones expressing· knowledge of correspondences and connections; but their topic isn’t how appearances relate to one another in experience, but rather how they relate to experience in general. This has to do with

•whether they satisfy the formal conditions that the understanding recognizes,

or with

•whether they fit with the materials of the senses and of perception,

or

it •brings both of those considerations together under a single concept.

So it has to do with •possibility, •actuality, and •necessity according to universal laws of nature.

26

My third table ·on page 30·—the table of principles that the critical method has extracted from the nature of the understanding itself—has a completeness that raises it far above every other table that anyone ever did or ever will offer in a vain attempt to extract principles by non-critical methods from things themselves. What makes my table complete is this: so far as the understanding is concerned, the essence of experience lies in the •judgments that can be made about

32

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure natural science possible?

it, and I have used ·properties of· the faculty of •judgment as a single guiding rationale for what is included in my table of principles, namely all the synthetic a priori principles. So we can be certain that there are no more principles of that sort, and that certainty affords a satisfaction that the dogmatic method can never achieve. [Kant’s use of ‘dogmatic’ is explained in a note on page 12.] Yet this is not all: my table of principles has another much greater merit ·that I shall now explain·.

We must carefully bear in mind the premise •that enables us to infer that there can be a priori knowledge ·such as the table of principles involves·, and •that at the same time subjects all such principles to the constraint that they are only about the conditions of possible experience in general so far as it conforms to laws a priori. If we lose sight of this constraint, we risk the principles’ being misunderstood, and their being extended in use beyond the original sense that the understanding attaches to them. So I don’t say

that things in themselves have a quantity,

that their actuality has a degree,

that their existence has a connection of qualities in a substance,

or the like. Nobody could prove any of those propositions, because they are synthetic—·connecting things with quantity, degree-of-actuality, and so on·—and it is utterly impossible to prove such synthetic propositions on the basis of mere concepts, ·because what is proved from mere concepts is always analytic·. The above propositions have only concepts to work with, because they purport to be about things in themselves; that prevents them from referring to how sensory intuitions are inter-connected in a possible experience, which is the basis on which synthetic propositions can be proved a priori. So the essential constraint on the concepts used in these principles is: It is only as objects of experience that things necessarily a priori satisfy the conditions laid down in the principles.

From this it also follows that the proof of these principles has a unique feature: namely that they aren’t directly concerned with appearances and their ·inter·-relations, but with the possibility of experience. Appearances ·on their own aren’t the whole story; they· constitute only the matter of experience, not its form. That is, the principles I’m talking about are concerned with objectively and universally valid synthetic propositions, in ·the context of· which we distinguish judgments of experience from judgments of perception. ·I shall now add a little detail about how this happens—how the principles are proved—in connection with three of the four groups of principles listed on page 30.·

(1) ·Re the Axioms of Intuition·: Appearances, as mere intuitions occupying a part of space and time, come under the concept of quantity, which can be used in a rule-guided way in synthetic a priori propositions which generalize over these intuitions.

(2) ·Re the Anticipations of Perception·: Insofar as a perception contains not only intuition but sensation (which always differs from its own total absence by ever-smaller differences), the reality of appearances must have a degree.

^3 Small areas of heat and light can be just as great in degree—·that is, just as intense·—as large ones; similarly, brief pains or other states of consciousness can be equal in degree ·or intensity· to long-lasting ones. ·Where degrees of intensity are concerned·, the quantity at a point in space and at a moment in time can be just as great as in any space or time of whatever size or duration. So degrees are quantities, but what is quantified is not •an intuition but rather •the mere sensation which is the intuition’s content. The only way to measure them, therefore, is through the relation of 1 to 0, that is. by their capability of decreasing by infinite intermediate degrees to disappearance, or of increasing from nothing through infinite gradations to a determinate sensation in a certain time. The quantity of a quality is a degree ·of intensity·.

33

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure natural science possible?

Now, sensation doesn’t itself occupy any part of space or of time,^3 but it takes time to get from empty space or time to ·something involving· sensation. Thus, although sensation (taken as that quality of empirical intuition that specifically distinguishes it from other sensations) can never be known a priori, it can nonetheless be intensively distinguished from any of the same kind as a quantity of perception in any possible experience. That’s what makes it possible to apply mathematics to nature as regards the sensory intuition through which nature is given to us.

But pay special attention to the mode of proof of (3) the principles that occur under •the title of ‘Analogies of Experience’. Unlike the principles of applied mathematics, these refer not to the genesis of intuitions but to how they are interconnected, as they actually occur, in experience; which can only be the story of how they are made to occur in time according to necessary laws—laws that make the conditions objectively valid and thus create experience. So the proof of these principles doesn’t turn on connections amongst things in themselves but merely amongst perceptions; and it doesn’t involve the matter or content of the perceptions, but only how they are related to one another in time according to universal laws....

In these preliminaries I can’t go on longer about this, except to say one thing to my reader. You have probably been long accustomed to regarding experience as a mere empirical hanging-together of perceptions, and so haven’t had the thought that it must go much beyond them, conferring universal validity on empirical judgments and for that purpose requiring a pure and a priori unity of the understanding. So I recommend to you that you pay special attention to my distinction between experience and a mere aggregate of perceptions, and to judge the mode of proof from this point of view.

27

Now we have reached the place where Humean doubt can be removed. Hume rightly said that reason can’t give us insight into

•causality, i.e. the notion that the existence of one thing might necessitate the existence of another.

I add that we have equally little insight into the concept of

•substance, i.e. the notion that the existence of things must be based on a subject that cannot itself be a predicate of anything else.

Indeed, we can form no concept of the possibility of such a thing, although we can point to examples of its use in experience. Nor have we any insight into

•two-way causal interaction, i.e. into how substances that have their own entirely separate existences can necessarily depend on one another.

None of these three concepts is supplied by reason; they have—as I have shown—their seat in the understanding. These concepts and the principles drawn from them stand a priori before all experience; they are applicable only to experience, but within that domain they have undoubted objective rightness. That doctrine saves me from having to conclude that the concepts in question are borrowed from experience, which would mean that the necessity they involve is fictitious—a mere illusion resulting from long habit.

28

I can’t conceive how (1) things in themselves could

•exist as substances, or

•be causes, or

•be in two-way causal interaction with others as parts of a real whole.

34

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure natural science possible?

Still less can I conceive how any of these could be true of (2) appearances considered as raw and unprocessed perceptions or sensory states, not brought under concepts of the understanding. But we can conceive of such connections of (3) representations in our understanding. These representations figure in one kind of judgment as

•subject related to predicates,

in a second kind as

•source related to upshot,

and in a third kind as

•parts that are inter-related to make up a knowable whole.

We also know a priori that unless we take the representation of an object to be related in one of these ways, we can’t have any knowledge that would be valid of the object. Of course if we attend to the object in itself, we are lost: there is no possible way for me to recognize that a thing in itself is related in one of those ways, i.e. that it belongs under the concept of •substance or of •cause or (in relation to other substances) under the concept of •two-way causal interaction. But things in themselves aren’t my topic. What I am concerned with is how experiential knowledge of things involves those three types of judgment, i.e. how objects of experience can be brought under those concepts of the understanding. I have perfect insight into that: I grasp not merely that we can bring appearances under these concepts but that we must do so, in that way using the concepts as principles of the possibility of experience.

29
Let us apply all this to Hume’s problematic concept, namely the concept of cause. Sheer logic tells me a priori that there can be conditional judgments—ones of the form ‘If..., then...’—in which one piece of knowledge is treated as a source and another as an upshot. I may have occasion to make such a judgment, reporting that in my perceptions one kind of appearance is regularly followed by another, as when I say ‘If the sun shines long enough on a body, then the body grows warm’. This doesn’t connect the two necessarily, and it doesn’t involve the concept of cause; so far, it is merely a subjective connection of perceptions. For it to be a proposition of experience, it must be regarded as necessary and as universally valid, like the proposition ‘The sun through its light is the cause of heat’. The empirical generalization with which I started is now regarded as a law, and as being valid for appearances in a manner that is required if experience is to be possible—for there can’t be experience without rules that are universally and therefore necessarily valid. So I do have insight into the concept of cause, as a concept necessarily belonging to the possibility of experience. What about the concept of things ·in themselves· as causes? I have no conception of that, because the concept of cause doesn’t correspond to anything in •things but only to a •fact about experience, namely that if experience is to be objectively valid knowledge of appearances and of their sequence in time, some appearances must be related to later ones in conditional judgments.

30

Hence the pure concepts of the understanding have absolutely no meaning if they are pulled away from objects of experience and applied to things in themselves (noumena). [Kant uses ‘noumenon’ (plural ‘noumena’) to mean ‘thing that can only be thought’, in contrast to ‘phenomenon’ (plural ‘phenomena’), meaning ‘thing that can be experienced’. Things in themselves are noumena because although we can perhaps think about them, we can’t possibly experience them.] The role of pure concepts of the understanding is to spell out appearances, so to speak, enabling them to be

35

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure natural science possible?

read as experience. When these concepts are applied to the world of the senses, the principles that arise from this use help our understanding to manage our experience. Beyond the bounds of experience they are arbitrary connections with no objective reality: there is no a priori guarantee that they apply to anything, and no examples can be given of their applicability to objects. Indeed, we don’t even know what such an example could be like. We have no conception of it, because examples have to be drawn from some possible experience. Possible experience is the proper domain of the pure concepts of the understanding.

So the Humean problem is completely solved, though in a way that would have surprised its inventor. The solution secures an a priori origin for the pure concepts of the understanding, and for the universal laws of nature it secures a status as valid laws of the understanding; but it does this in such a way as to limit the use of these concepts to experience only, and it grounds them in a relation between the understanding and experience that is the complete reverse of anything that Hume envisaged—instead of the concepts being derived from experience, that experience is derived from them.

My line of argument yields the following result: All synthetic a priori principles are simply principles of possible experience; they can never be applied to things in themselves, but only to appearances as objects of experience. Hence pure mathematics as well as pure natural science can never bear on anything except appearances.

31
Until now, metaphysicians have proceeded boldly enough, but always trampling over everything blindly, without making any distinctions. My work gives us, at last, something definite to rely on as a guide in metaphysical enterprises. It never dawned on the dogmatic thinkers that the goal of their efforts might be so near; nor did it dawn on the philosophers who, proud of their supposedly sound reason, set out on their quest for results, equipped with concepts and principles of pure reason (which were legitimate and natural, but fit only for merely empirical use). These philosophers did not and could not know any fixed boundaries to the territory within which results might be gained, because they hadn’t and couldn’t have ever reflected on the nature of such a pure understanding or even on its possibility.

Many a naturalist of pure reason (by which I mean someone who thinks he can settle metaphysical questions without any theoretical grounding in the subject) may claim that the prophetic spirit of his sound reason enabled him, long ago, not merely to suspect but to know and understand the doctrine I have been advancing with so much ado (or, as he may prefer to say, with long-winded pomp), namely that with all our reason we can never reach beyond the domain of experience. But when he is questioned about his principles of reason individually, he must admit that many of them haven’t been taken from experience and are therefore independent of it and valid a priori. But then what basis will he have for putting limits on the dogmatist who uses these concepts and principles beyond all possible experience because he sees them to be independent of it? And even he, this expert in sound reason, in spite of all his assumed and cheaply acquired wisdom, risks wandering inadvertently beyond objects of experience into the domain of fantasies. He is often deeply enough involved in it, though he colours his groundless claims by adopting popular language and announcing everything as ‘mere probability’, ‘rational conjecture’, or ‘analogy’.

36

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure natural science possible?

32
Since the earliest times of philosophy, enquirers into pure reason have thought that in addition to the things of the senses, or appearances (phenomena) of the world of the senses, there are things of the understanding (noumena), and have thought that only the latter are real. That’s because they took the former—i.e. appearances—to be illusory; a mistake, but an excusable one in a primitive age.

In fact, when we (rightly) regard the objects of the senses as mere appearances, we thereby admit that they have a thing in itself as their ground—·namely, the thing of which they are appearances·. We don’t know what this thing is like in itself; all we know is its appearance, i.e. how this unknown something affects our senses. In accepting appearances, therefore, we also admit the existence of things in themselves: the thought of such ·noumena, i.e.· ‘things of the understanding’, isn’t merely allowed but is unavoidable.

[In this paragraph, Kant refers to the Aesthetic. That’s the first part of the Critique of Pure Reason, concerning the status of time and space and their relation to sensibility.] My critical deduction limits the principles of the Aesthetic so that they hold good only for objects of possible experience, because extending them to all things would be turning everything into mere appearance; my deduction doesn’t at all imply that there are no noumena. So these beings of the understanding are allowed, subject to this rule, to which there can be no exceptions: We don’t and can’t know anything determinate about these beings of the understanding. That’s because our pure concepts of the understanding and our pure intuitions bear on objects of possible experience—i.e. things of the senses—and on nothing else. As soon as we move away from the senses, those concepts are drained of all their meaning.

33

Indeed, there’s something seductive in our pure concepts of the understanding, which tempts us to use them in a transcendent manner—that being my label for a use that goes beyond all possible experience [not = ‘transcendental’; see explanation on page 24]. Our concepts of substance, of power, of action, of reality, and others are quite independent of experience, containing nothing of sensory appearance, and so they seem to be applicable to things in themselves (noumena). And this impression is strengthened by the fact that those concepts contain within themselves an element of necessity which experience never matches up to. The concept of cause implies a rule according to which one state follows another necessarily; but experience can only show us that one state of affairs often or usually follows another, so it can’t provide us with either strict universality or necessity.

So the concepts of the understanding seem to have content and significance that spreads beyond their empirical use, and the understanding unknowingly builds for itself a much larger addition to the house of experience, and fills it with merely notional entities, without once noticing that ·in doing this· it has carried its otherwise lawful concepts beyond the bounds of their ·legitimate· use.

34

Because of all this, the Critique of Pure Reason had to contain two important though extremely dry investigations. In one of them, contained in the chapter entitled ‘The Schematism of the Pure Concepts of the Understanding’, I show that what the senses provide for are not •concrete applications of the pure concepts of the understanding, but only the •schemas for their use, and that the corresponding object occurs only in experience (as something the understanding makes out of the materials of the senses). In the second indispensable

37

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure natural science possible?

chapter, ‘On the Basis for Distinguishing all Objects into Phenomena and Noumena’, I show that, although our pure concepts and principles of the understanding are independent of experience, and despite their seemingly greater sphere of use, we still can’t use them to have any thoughts whatsoever beyond the domain of experience, because their only role is to fix the logical forms of judgments that we make about given intuitions. But as there’s absolutely no intuition outside the domain of the senses, these pure concepts have no meaning outside that domain; and all these noumena, together with the intelligible^4 world that they compose, are nothing but the representation of a problem, ·namely the problem or question: What are noumena like? What is the intelligible world like?· What the question is about is something possible; but answering it in terms of the concepts of our understanding is quite impossible. That’s because of the nature of our understanding, whose role isn’t to deliver intuitions but to connect intuitions that are given in experience; ·i.e. it doesn’t present us with real particular things, but only enables us to inter-connect particulars that we get from elsewhere, namely from our senses·. So experience must contain all the materials to which we apply our concepts; and beyond it no concepts have any significance, as there’s no intuition that might offer them something to grip onto.

35
The •imagination may perhaps be forgiven for sometimes wandering, not keeping carefully within the limits of experience; for such roaming gives it life and vigour, and ·that’s an advantage, because· it is always easier to moderate the imagination’s boldness than to rouse it from lethargy. But the •understanding’s job is to think, and it can never be forgiven if it wanders instead, for it is our only resource for setting limits, when they are needed, to the wanderings of the imagination.

The understanding begins its misbehaviour very innocently and soberly. First it brings to light the elementary items of knowledge that it contains in advance of all experience, though they must never be applied outside experience. It gradually discards these limits, and what’s to prevent it from doing so when it has quite freely drawn its principles from itself? ·Then, having dropped the restriction to experience·, it proceeds first to newly-thought-up powers in nature, and soon after that to beings outside nature. In short, it proceeds to a ·non-natural· world; and there can be no shortage of materials for constructing such a world, because fertile fiction-making provides them in abundance—and though it isn’t confirmed by experience it is never refuted by it either. This is why young thinkers arc so partial to metaphysics of the truly dogmatic kind, devoting to it their time and talents that could be better employed.

But it is no use trying to damp down these fruitless efforts of pure reason by •offering all sorts of reminders of how hard it is to answer such deep questions, by •complaining about how limited our reason is, and by •down-playing our assertions as mere conjectures. The only way to get these fruitless efforts to be completely abandoned is to •show clearly that they are impossible, and to allow reason’s knowledge of itself to become a true science in ·terms of· which the domain of reason’s right use is distinguished with mathematical certainty from that of its worthless and idle use.

^4 Not the intellectual world (as the usual expression is). For cognitive •operations of the understanding are intellectual, and some of them are thinkings about the world of our senses. The term ‘intelligible’ applies to •objects insofar as they can be represented by the understanding all on its own, without our sensible intuitions coming into it in any way....

38

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure natural science possible?

36: How is nature itself possible?
This question is the highest point that transcendental philosophy can ever touch. [Reminder: by ‘transcendental’ Kant means ‘having to do with grounds for a priori knowledge’.] It is a point that transcendental philosophy must reach, because it is its boundary and completion. Really it contains two questions.

First: What makes it possible for there to be nature—in the material sense of that word, in which it stands for the totality of appearances? That is to ask: How are space and time and their contents possible in general? The answer is: What makes them possible is •the way our sensibility is—the special way in which it is affected by objects that are in themselves unknown and aren’t in themselves spatial or temporal. This answer has been given in the Critique (in the Transcendental Aesthetic), and here in the Preliminaries through the solution ·in sections 6–13· of the first problem ·raised at the end of section 5·.

Secondly: What makes it possible for there to be nature in the formal sense, in which nature involves the totality of rules that must apply to all appearances if they are to be connected by thought in an experience? The answer must be this: What makes nature possible is •the way our understanding works. ·In the background is the crucial fact that· all the representations of the sensibility have to be related to a consciousness; ·for different items to be held in a single consciousness, they must be related to one another in certain ways, and these relations are imposed upon them by the understanding. And so all the representations that we are discussing must fall within the scope of our understanding. And the answer to our question is that there can be a rule-governed nature (in the formal sense) because· our understanding demands that items that are thought about be brought under rules. This rule-governedness is what makes experience possible; don’t mistake this for an insight into the objects in themselves! This answer is given in the Critique itself (in the Transcendental Logic), and in these Preliminaries in the course of the solution ·in sections 14–32· of the second main problem ·raised at the end of section 5·.

Why is our sensibility like that? Why is our understanding like that? We cannot address these questions, because we have to use our sensibility and our understanding in all the questions we ask and all the thinking we do in looking for answers.

There are many laws of nature that we can know only through experience; but experience can’t teach us the general truth that appearances are connected in conformity with laws, because the application of such laws is what makes experience possible in the first place.

So the possibility of experience—of any experience—is at the same time the universal law of nature, and the principles of the experience are themselves the laws of nature. For we know nature only as the sum-total of appearances, i.e. of representations in us, and so the only source from which we can derive

the laws governing •how nature’s parts are interconnected

is

the principles governing •how they are connected in us,

that is

•the conditions that have to be satisfied if they are to be united in a single consciousness.

If they weren’t united into one consciousness there couldn’t be any experience.

The main thesis of this part of the Preliminaries, namely that universal laws of nature can be known a priori, leads all by itself to this conclusion:

39

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure natural science possible?

The source of the highest laws of nature lies in ourselves, i.e. in our understanding. Rather than using •experience to find the universal laws of nature in •nature, we must go in the opposite direction. That is, we must look for •nature itself—as a system that universally conforms to laws—in the features of our sensibility and understanding that make •experience possible.

How else could the laws of nature be known a priori, given that they aren’t analytic but synthetic?

Why must the principles of possible experience agree with the laws that govern what is possible in nature? We have a choice of two answers: either (1) these laws are drawn from nature by means of experience, or conversely (2) nature is deduced from the conditions that make experience possible. But (1) is self-contradictory, for the universal laws of nature must be known independently of all experience, because all empirical use of the understanding is based on them; so only (2) remains.^5

Empirical laws of nature always rely on particular perceptions. We must distinguish such laws from the pure or universal laws of nature, which aren’t based on particular perceptions and simply lay down the conditions that enable perceptions to be unified so as to constitute experience. So far as the laws are concerned, nature and possible experience are one and the same. •The law-abidingness of possible experience—·i.e. the holding of laws that are valid not just for actual but for all possible experience·—depends on •the necessary connection of appearances in experience (a connection without which ·there would no unified consciousness, and so· we wouldn’t be able to know any object whatever in the sensible world), and so it depends on •the original laws of the understanding. Because of this, we can say—though it sounds strange at first—that The understanding doesn’t draw its laws from nature, but prescribes them to nature.

37

I shall illustrate this seemingly bold proposition by an example that is meant to show that laws that we discover in objects of sensory intuition (especially laws that we know to be necessary) are already held by us to have been placed there by the •understanding, even though they are otherwise just like the laws of nature that we ascribe to •experience. ·Actually, I shall do rather more than that. I shall show that laws that we are already willing to ascribe to our understanding (namely, those of geometry) lead to one of the laws (namely, the inverse-square law of gravitation) that we wouldn’t think of as contributed by our understanding unless we had been introduced to my critical philosophy·.

38

If we consider the properties of the circle, through which this figure provides a unity for ever so many arbitrary spatial configurations all under a single universal rule, we can’t help crediting this geometrical thing with having a constitution. (·Analogously, when we think about the properties of iron, through which it enters into countless law-governed interactions with all sorts of other kinds of stuff, we can’t help crediting it with a constitution or inner nature·.) For example, take any two straight lines that intersect one another and intersect some circle (any circle you like):

^5 Crusius was alone in suggesting a middle way. It could be (he said) that these laws of nature were originally implanted in us by a spirit who can’t err or deceive. But there is so much human error—including plenty of it in Crusius’ own system!—that it seems very dangerous to rely on this line of thought. Even if some things have been instilled in us by the Spirit of Truth, we have no reliable way of distinguishing these from ones put there by the Father of Lies.

40

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure natural science possible?

The rectangle constructed with the two segments of one of the lines is equal to the rectangle constructed with the two segments of the other.

Now I ask: Does this law lie in the circle or in the understanding? That is: Is the basis for this law something contained in the figure itself, independently of the understanding, or is the situation rather that the understanding, having constructed the figure according to its concepts (a set of points equidistant from a given point) introduces into it this law about the chords cutting one another in geometrical proportion? When we follow the proofs of this law, we soon see that it can only be derived from the equality of the circle’s radii, which is the basis for the understanding’s construction of this figure. But we can replace the concept on which the circle is based by a more general one that fits every sort of conic section (the circle being just one sort); that will advance the project of unifying various properties of geometrical figures under common laws; and if we take that step we’ll find that all the chords that intersect within the ellipse, parabola, and hyperbola, always intersect in such a way that the rectangles of their segments always •bear a constant ratio to one another (the circle is the special case where they •are equal).

If we proceed still further, to the fundamental laws of physical astronomy, we find that the whole of the material world is governed by a physical law of mutual attraction for which the rule is: The force of attraction decreases inversely as the square of the distance from each attracting point, i.e. as the spherical surfaces increase over which the force spreads. [Kant’s line of thought is as follows. Think of gravity as radiating out from a point, exerting the same total force evenly across the surface of each imaginary sphere with that point as centre. The •surface-areas of the spheres differ with the squares of their radii, i.e. their distance from the central point; that’s simple geometry. Then •the amount of gravitational force received by an object of a given size will vary with the proportion of its sphere-surface that it occupies, which means that it will vary inversely with the square of its distance from the gravitational source.] The simplicity of the sources of this law, which rest merely on the relation of spherical surfaces of different radii, is matched by what follows from it, namely such a splendid variety and harmony of consequences that not only are all possible orbits of the celestial bodies conic sections, but these orbits are inter-related in such a way that no law of attraction other than the inverse-square one can be imagined as appropriate for a cosmic system.

So here’s a nature that rests on laws that the understanding knows a priori, and chiefly from the universal principles of the geometry of space. Now I ask: •Do the laws of nature lie in space, and does our understanding learn them merely by trying to discover the great wealth of meaning that lies in space; or •do they inhere in the understanding and in its way of configuring space....?

Because it is so uniform and so indeterminate in its particular properties, one wouldn’t look to space for laws of nature. ·In contrast with that, there’s no threat of uniformity in the understanding!· What imposes circles, cones and spheres on space is the understanding, in its role as provider of the basis for of the constructions of those figures.

So the mere universal form of intuition that we call ‘space’ is the underlay of all intuitions of particular objects. There’s no denying that •space makes the •intuitions possible in all their variety; but the unity of the •objects—·or rather the unity among the intuitions that lets them qualify as intuitions of objects·—comes ·not from space but· from the understanding, in accordance with conditions that lie in its own nature. And so the understanding is the origin of the universal order of nature, in that it brings all appearances

41

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure natural science possible?

under its own laws, and thereby constructs the formal aspects of experience a priori, so that nothing can be known by experience except what conforms to the understanding’s laws. The nature of •things in themselves is independent of the conditions of our sensibility and our understanding; but our concern is not with that but rather with •nature considered as an object of possible experience; and here the understanding, by making experience possible, brings it about that the world of the senses either is nature (·in my sense, as given in section 14 above·) or is not an object of experience at all.

39: Appendix to the pure science of nature: the system of the Categories
Nothing can be more desirable for a philosopher than to take the multitude of concepts or principles that he has found himself applying in particular cases, and to derive them a priori from a single principle, thus uniting them all into a single cognition. Before that, all he had was the belief that he had gathered together all ·the concepts or principles· that remained after a certain abstraction and seemed to resemble one another enough to constitute a specific kind of knowledge; but what he had gathered was only an aggregate—·a disorderly heap·. Now, ·after his derivation from a single principle·, •he knows that this kind of knowledge involves just these ·concepts or principles·, neither more nor less, •he understands that his classification of them is necessary, and, at last, •he has a system.

You don’t need harder thought or more insight to

search out in our daily knowledge the concepts which, though they don’t rest on any particular experience, occur in all experiential knowledge of which they are (as it were) the mere form of connection,

than you do to

search out in a language the general rules of the actual use of words, and thus collect elements for a grammar.

In fact the two researches are very closely related. Though ·a difference between them arises from the following fact·: we can’t give a reason why each language has just this and no other grammatical structure, let alone why its formal rules are just these, neither more nor less.

Aristotle collected ten pure elementary concepts under the name of ‘categories’ and also ‘predicaments’. He then found that he had to add to his list five ‘post-predicaments’ (though some of them were already contained in the first ten); but this random collection should be applauded more as a hint for future enquirers than as an idea developed according to a rule; which is why in philosophy’s present more advanced state it has been rejected as quite useless.

In my research into the elements of human knowledge that are pure (contain nothing empirical), my first success—achieved after long thought—was to distinguish and separate the pure elementary concepts of sensibility (space and time) from those of the understanding. Thus Aristotle’s categories of time, space, and place had to be excluded ·because they pertain to sensibility, not understanding, and so are not categories·. And the others on his list were useless to me, because ·associated with them· there was no principle on the basis of which the understanding could be surveyed in its entirety, making possible a complete and precise account of all the things it can do from which arise its pure concepts—·its categories·.

Wanting to discover such a principle, I looked about for •an act of the understanding that contains all its other acts. With the help of that •one kind of act I could bring all the variety of representations into a unified theory of thinking in general. The desired •act of the understanding turned

42

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure natural science possible?

out to be: judging. Then I availed myself of the work of the logicians, imperfect though it was. With its help I was able to present a complete list of the pure functions of the understanding [= ‘basic kinds of thing the understanding can do’], considered ·at first· without any reference to any object to which they might be applied. The last step was to relate these functions of ·the understanding—i.e. these ways of·—judging, to the conditions that settle whether a given judgment is objectively valid. And so there arose the pure concepts of the understanding, concerning which I could make certain that just exactly these ·on my list·—neither more nor less—settle what knowledge of things we can have on the basis of pure understanding. It was all right for me to call them by their old ·Aristotelian· name, categories....

What distinguishes this system of categories from the old unprincipled random collection of concepts, and what alone entitles it to be considered as philosophy, is this essential fact about it: By means of it the true significance of the pure concepts of the understanding, and the condition of their use, could be precisely determined. For here it became obvious that in themselves •the categories are nothing but •logical functions, ·corresponding to •logical kinds of judgment, such as conditional, negative, universal and so on·; which means that they don’t by themselves yield the slightest concept of an object. For that they need some sensory intuition as a basis. So their only role is to shape up empirical judgments.... enabling them to become judgments of experience.

Such an insight into the nature of the categories, which limits them to merely experiential use, never occurred to their first author [Aristotle] or to any of his successors; but without this insight they are quite useless and only a wretched list of names, with no explanation and no rule for their use. If the ancients had ever conceived such a notion, doubtless the whole study of pure rational knowledge, which under the name ‘metaphysics’ has through the centuries spoiled so many sound minds, would have reached us in quite another shape, and would have enlightened the human understanding instead of—as has actually happened—exhausting it in obscure and pointless speculations, making it useless for true science.

This system of categories exhausts all the possible actions of the understanding, and so every other concept must fall under them. That puts all treatment of any object of pure reason on a systematic basis, and provides an absolutely reliable pointer or clue to how and through what points of enquiry every metaphysical endeavour must proceed if it is to be complete; for it exhausts all the workings of the understanding, under which every other concept must be brought. Similarly with the table of principles: we can know that it is complete only through relation to the system of the categories. And even in the classification of the concepts, if it is to get beyond ·the sort of classification that might be based on findings in· the empirical psychology of the understanding, it is always the very same guiding thread, which, as it must always be settled a priori by the same fixed points of the human understanding, forms a closed circle every time, leaving no doubt that if we want a complete philosophical and a priori knowledge of the object of a pure conception either of the understanding or of reason, this is the way to get it. So I couldn’t neglect this clue with regard to one of the most abstract ontological divisions, namely all the differences that fall under the concepts of something and of nothing, and to construct accordingly a rule-governed and necessary table.

And this system, like any true one based on a universal principle, shows its inestimable value in this, that it •keeps out all foreign concepts that might otherwise slink in among the pure concepts of the understanding, and •assigns to

43

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is pure natural science possible?

every item of knowledge its proper place. ·Here’s an example·. The concepts that I arranged in a table according to the clue of the categories, under the name ‘concepts of reflection’, turn up among the pure concepts of the understanding in ontology, without having any permission or right to be there. The pure concepts of the understanding are concepts of connection, and thereby of the objects themselves, whereas the concepts of reflection have to do only with the mere comparison of concepts already given; so the nature and uses of the two kinds of concept are quite different; and my systematic classification of the concepts of reflection keeps them out of company where they don’t belong. But the value of putting the categories in a special table of their own will be still more obvious when we do—as I shortly shall—distinguish those concepts of the understanding from the transcendental concepts of reason. The latter are quite different in nature and in origin from the former, so they must have quite another form. This separation, necessary as it is, has never yet been made in any system of metaphysics, which is why the concepts of reason have been jumbled together with the concepts of the understanding, as though they were siblings. This mix-up was inevitable in the absence of a separate system of categories.

44

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is metaphysics possible?

Main transcendental problem 3:

How is metaphysics possible in general?

40
I have now provided an explanatory justification for •pure mathematics and for •pure natural science. Neither of them needed this for the sake of its own security and certainty; for pure mathematics is supported by the self-evident truth of its propositions; and pure natural science, although its ultimate sources lie in the understanding, is thoroughly supported and confirmed by experience. (Certain as pure natural science is, it can never equal mathematics in that regard, which is why it can’t entirely do without the testimony of experience.) Both these sciences therefore needed my enquiry not for themselves but for another science, namely •metaphysics.

Metaphysics is concerned not only with concepts of nature (which always find their application in experience) but also with pure concepts of reason, which never find application in any possible experience. No experience can tell us what’s true and what’s false involving concepts of reason, or even whether these concepts are objectively real or mere fictions. Yet the part of metaphysics that involves them is what the rest of metaphysics is for—and that’s why this science ·unlike the other two· needs an explanatory justification for its own sake. The third question now before us concerns the heart of metaphysics, its special feature, namely reason’s preoccupation with itself, and its assumption that by brooding over its own •concepts it can come to know about •objects that it supposes to arise immediately out of those •concepts without help of any kind from experience.^6

Reason will never be satisfied until it has solved this problem—·i.e. answered the question ‘How is metaphysics possible·?’. Reason won’t let pure understanding be used outside the domain of experience; but reason itself is destined to go beyond those confines. Every particular experience is only a part of the whole domain of experience; but the absolute whole of all possible experience is not itself an experience, yet it is something that reason has to think about, as a problem. For reason to present this problem to itself, it needs concepts quite different from those of the understanding. The latter are applied only to items given in experience; but the concepts of reason have a use that is transcendent: it transcends all actual and possible experience, because it involves thinking about the completeness of all possible experience, i.e. thinking about

the-totality-of-possible-experience

considered as a single unified item. Such an item couldn’t itself be given in experience.

Just as •the understanding supplies categories, which are needed for experience, so •reason supplies Ideas, by which I mean concepts that one must have though their objects can’t be given in any possible experience. •Ideas are as inherent in the nature of •reason as •categories are in the nature of the •understanding. Ideas carry with them an illusion that could easily mislead; this illusion is unavoidable, although it can be prevented from actually leading us astray.

^6 If we can say that a science is actual, at least in the thinking of all men (·subjectively actual·), as soon as we have established that the problems leading to it are ones that are set before everybody by the nature of human reason,.... then we are bound to say that metaphysics is subjectively actual (and necessarily so), which leads us to the legitimate question: How is it (objectively) possible?

45

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is metaphysics possible?

All illusion consists in taking the subjective ground of judgment to be objective, as though reason in its use of the Ideas were acquiring a special kind of knowledge. Reason falls victim to this, and is guilty of error, when it takes something that merely concerns •reason’s own nature and mode of operation and tries to make it refer to •some object in itself. The only safeguard against this temptation is for reason to know itself—to understand what’s going on when it uses Ideas in a transcendent, extravagant manner that goes beyond all possible experience.

41
We must distinguish Ideas, which are pure concepts of reason, from the categories or pure concepts of the understanding; the two correspond to two sorts of knowledge that are quite different from one another •in their natures, •in where they come from, and •in how they are used. In the fundamentals of a science that purports to cover all a priori knowledge, the distinction between Ideas and categories is crucial. If we don’t respect it, metaphysics will be absolutely impossible—or at best a random, bungling attempt to build a house of cards in ignorance of the materials one is using and of what they are good for. If my Critique of Pure Reason had done nothing but make this distinction plain for the first time, it would have contributed more to our grasp of metaphysics—what it is, and how it should be conducted—than all the fruitless efforts to do justice to the transcendent problems of pure reason that had ever before been undertaken. Before the Critique, no-one had even suspected that reason was quite different from understanding; so everybody ran the two together, mentioning concepts of the understanding and concepts of reason in the same breath, as though they were of the same kind.

42

All instances of pure knowledge by the understanding have this in common: ·although they aren’t derived from experience·, they involve concepts that can have application in experience, and principles that can be confirmed by experience. Transcendent knowledge by reason contrasts with this. The Ideas that it involves can’t be applied in experience, nor can its propositions ever be confirmed or refuted by experience. If any errors creep into the employment of reason, they will have to be discovered by pure reason itself ·because neither sensibility nor understanding can have anything to do with them·. For reason thus to stand guard over itself is very difficult, because the reason that is standing guard is the very faculty that is necessarily prone to intellectual illusions, and we have no firm objectively grounded procedure for avoiding them—only a subjective enquiry into reason itself as a source of Ideas.

43

My chief aim in the Critique was not only to distinguish carefully the various sorts of knowledge but also to derive from their common source the concepts belonging to each of them. I did this so that by knowing the origins of these concepts I could settle how they might safely be used; and it also gave me the priceless though unexpected advantage of knowing, a priori and in a principled way, that •my list of concepts, and •my classification and •descriptions of them, are complete. Without this, everything in metaphysics is a mere jumble, in which you never know whether you have enough ·for your purpose·, or whether and where something is still lacking. This advantage is the very essence of pure philosophy, and isn’t to be had anywhere else.

I have derived the twelve categories—the four trios of pure concepts of the understanding - from a classification of

46

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is metaphysics possible?

kinds of judgment that can be made. The concepts of reason are three in number, and they derive from a classification not of judgments but of logical arguments—specifically, the three kinds of inferences of reason. For these pure concepts of reason (the transcendental Ideas) are given—we simply do have them—and if one doesn’t want to regard them as something like innate, the only source that can be found for them is the activity of reason. That activity in its concern with logical form constitutes the logical element of the inferences of reason; but it also involves recognizing judgments of the understanding as involving this or that a priori form of judgment, and in this role it yields transcendental concepts of pure reason.

The basic sorts of argument are: categorical, conditional, and disjunctive. [A categorical argument has a first premise of the form ‘(Subject) is (Predicate)’; a conditional one has a premise of the form ‘If P, then Q’; a disjunctive one has one of the form ‘Either P or Q’.] ·Each Idea involves the thought of a kind of completeness·. So the Ideas—the concepts of pure reason—are as follows.

•Categorical: the Idea of a complete subject (the Idea of what is substantial); ·this is the Idea of an ultimate ‘thing which...’, like Locke’s idea of substance in general·; this Idea is psychological ·because the natural home ground of this thought is in application to oneself: I am a thing which·...’.

•Conditional: the Idea of a complete series of conditions—·e.g. the thought of all the causes of the present state of the world·; this Idea is cosmological.

•Disjunctive: the Idea of a complete reality that somehow encompasses the entire range of what’s possible; this Idea is theological.^7 [For an explanation of how theology comes into this, see section 55 on page 59. It’s not very helpful, but it’s all Kant gives us in this work.]

All three give rise to dialectics—·i.e. to characteristic dangers of intellectual illusion, insoluble problems, lurking contradictions, and the like·. But their ways of doing so are different, and so we have—·corresponding to the trio

•categorical, •conditional, and •disjunctive

—a· three-part division of the dialectics into

its •Paralogism, its •Antinomy, and its •Ideal.

Through this way of coming at things we can feel assured that all the claims of pure reason are completely represented, nothing missed, because we have completely surveyed the faculty of reason itself, from which they all take their origin.

44

It should be borne in mind that the Ideas of reason, unlike the categories, don’t help us to bring the understanding to bear on experience. In the knowledge of nature by the understanding, the Ideas of reason are entirely dispensable; indeed they are a positive obstacle to what is going on. (They have, however, their own good use, which we’ll come to later.) •The psychological Idea of reason brings up the question ‘Is the soul a simple substance or not?’ The answer to that is of no interest when we are doing empirical psychology. No possible experience could be evidence for either answer to the question. So far as the description and explanation of our mental histories is concerned, the concept of simple substance is quite empty. •As for the questions raised by the cosmological Idea—Did the world begin? Will it end?—answers to these can have no role whatever in explaining

^7 In disjunctive judgments we consider the whole range of what is possible as divided in respect to some particular concept. The ontological principle that every object falls under one or the other out of each contradictory pair of predicates, which is also the principle of all disjunctive judgments, essentially relies on this thought of the sum of all possibility—which goes with the thought that every possible object is completely determinate, ·because it falls under just one out of each contradictory pair of predicates·....

47

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is metaphysics possible?

any event in the world. •And as for the theological Idea: there’s a correct maxim of natural science that says that we shouldn’t try to explain how nature is by appealing to the will of a highest being, because such an explanation would no longer be natural science, but rather an admission that we have reached the end of it. So the proper use of •Ideas of reason must be quite different from the use of the •categories, i.e. the •pure concepts of the understanding through which experience becomes possible.

Now, reason and understanding are related with one another in a certain manner, which brings in some parts of my laborious analytic of the understanding [i.e. the part of the Critique of Pure Reason labelled ‘Transcendental Analytic’]. How? Well, it can’t have to do with the business of getting knowledge of nature through experience: the part reason plays in that—in mathematics and natural science—can be perfectly well played without all this subtle examination of the nature and functions of the understanding. So my analytic of the understanding must link with the Ideas of pure reason for a purpose that lies beyond the empirical use of the understanding. ·So now we have a dilemma. On the one hand·, I have said that we can’t use the understanding outside the realm of experience, as that would be a meaningless activity, with no subject-matter. On the other hand, the nature of reason must conform with the activities of the understanding, contributing to their perfection and not disturbing them.

Here’s the solution—the truth about what reason has to do with understanding. What pure reason does is to demand that understanding, when it is brought to bear on the complex of experience, shall achieve completeness in its operations. This, however, is only a completeness of principles, not of intuitions and objects. ·To put the point in simpler terms: The demand for completeness says ‘As long as there’s something you don’t yet understand, keep working on it’; it doesn’t say ‘Aim to grasp the whole story all at once: •survey the mind in such a way that you have all its properties on one side and the ultimate subject that bears those properties on the other; •arrive at results about the world’s entire past and entire future; •think in a concrete way about God as the explanation of the entire world’·. The illusion—which brings the risk of error—comes from the fact that reason, wanting to make its demand for completeness as sharp and graspable as possible, slips into treating it as though it were a demand for knowledge of something—·the ultimate subject of mental states, the world’s whole past, etc·.

45: Prefatory remark to the dialectic of pure reason
I have shown in sections 33 and 34 that the freedom of the categories from any input from the senses may mislead reason into extending their use, quite beyond all experience, to things ·as they are· in themselves ·as distinct from things as they appear to us·; though ·no such use is legitimate, for the following reason·. Because the categories lack any sensory element that can give them meaning or sense in particular cases, they can represent anything in their role as mere logical functions; but there’s nothing about which they can, unaided, give specific information. The fancy objects ·that reason wrongly tries to bring under the categories· are known as ‘noumena’, or pure beings of the understanding (or better, beings of thought). Examples include

substance—but conceived without permanence in time,

cause—but not conceived as acting in time,

and so on. ·In thinking or talking like this· one attaches to these ·supposed· objects predicates whose only ·legitimate· use is to enable experience to conform to laws; and yet ·by leaving time out of it· one deprives them of all the conditions

48

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is metaphysics possible?

of intuition that have to be satisfied for experience to be possible, and so these concepts lose all meaning again.

There’s no risk that the understanding, when left to itself and not given orders from the outside, will so wantonly roam out of its own proper territory into that of mere creatures of thought. But the empirical use of the rules of the understanding is conditioned, and reason can’t be fully satisfied with that; so it demands a completion of this chain of conditions. [Until this point in the Preliminaries the concept of condition has been used almost entirely in saying things about (a) the conditions that our understanding must satisfy, the conditions that our sensibility must satisfy—e.g. in saying that spatiality and temporality are formal conditions of our sensibility. We now, for almost the first time, encounter a different use of the concept: the topic now is not

(a) the general conditions that have to be satisfied if we are to have certain kinds of engagement with the world,

but rather

(b) the conditions that various items within the world have to satisfy if they are to exist.

Examples of (b): Any event in the experienced world occurs only because something causes it to do so; any region of space exists only because there is a larger region in which it is embedded; any period of time exists only because there was an earlier period of time leading up to it; any state exists only if there is something that it is the state of; and so on. Kant holds that (b) these in-the-experienced-world conditioning relationships can be depended on because they are put there by (a) the general conditions that our sensibility and understanding have to satisfy. So all this is part of a single unified body of doctrine. Still, it is as well to notice how, after so much talk about ‘conditions’, we are rather suddenly on the presence of the notion of chains of conditions. It is just the shift from (a) to (b).]
This forces the understanding to leave its proper domain, so that it can do two things: •represent objects of experience in a series that stretches too far for any experience to capture it, and •look completely outside itself for noumena to which it can attach that chain, thus completing the series, escaping from the conditions of experience, and making its hold complete. So there they are—the transcendental Ideas. ·•They are in themselves virtuous, though •they can make trouble; but •the trouble can be averted·. •They don’t try to produce concepts that are in themselves excessive or extravagant; all they aim for—in conformity with the true but hidden goal to which our reason is naturally drawn—is a limitless extension of the empirical use of the categories. •But through an unavoidable ·intellectual· illusion they may seduce the understanding into using the categories in a transcendent manner, ·i.e. in a manner that isn’t related to experience·. Deceitful as this misuse is, ·it is hard to avoid·. To keep yourself from it and confine the categories within the bounds of experience, it won’t do merely to resolve in advance to be on your guard against doing so. •What you need is scientific instruction ·on how to avoid the trouble·, and even then it takes hard work.

I. The psychological Ideas

46
People have long since remarked that in all substances the proper subject—

namely, the substantial as such, i.e. what remains after all the qualities (as predicates) are set aside

—is unknown, and this limit on our knowledge has been the topic of various complaints. But if our understanding is at fault in this matter, it is not for its inability to know—to determine by itself—the substance of things, but rather for its wanting to know the substance of things, thereby treating a mere Idea as though it were a given object ·into whose nature one might enquire·. Pure reason demands that for every predicate of a thing we seek its proper subject; but •this subject can’t be anything but a ·further· predicate, so

49

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is metaphysics possible?

reason tells us to find a subject for •it in its turn, and so on, indefinitely (or until we give up). So we are never to regard anything that we arrive at as an ultimate subject: and our understanding can never have the thought of the substantial itself, however deeply it penetrates and even if all of nature is unveiled to us. That’s because the special characteristic of our understanding is that when it thinks something it does so by representing it through concepts, and thus through mere predicates; so it can never reach the absolute subject—·the sheer thing, not understood as thing-that-is-F for any predicate F·. Hence all the real properties through which we know bodies are mere qualities of them; and that includes impenetrability, which we can only represent to ourselves as the effect of a power whose subject is unknown to us.

Now, it appears as if we do confront this ·absolute· subject in our consciousness of ourselves (of the thinking subject), and indeed that we have this in an immediate intuition; for all the predicates of inner sense refer to the I as a subject, and I can’t conceive myself as the predicate of some other subject. So it seems that we are given in experience something that completes the process of relating given concepts predicatively to a subject—given it not merely as an idea but as an object, i.e. the absolute subject itself. But this turns out to be a false hope. For the I isn’t a concept,^8 but only a designation of the object of inner sense insofar as we know it by no further predicate. So it can’t itself be a predicate of any other thing, any more than it can be a determinate concept of an absolute subject; it’s only a relating of inner phenomena to their unknown subject. Yet this Idea (which does excellent service as a regulative principle, totally destroying all materialistic explanations of the inner phenomena of the soul) leads through a wholly natural misunderstanding to a highly plausible argument: from •this supposed knowledge of the substantial status of our thinking being, the argument infers •conclusions about the nature of the soul—the nature of it that lies right outside the compass of experience. [See the explanation of ’regulative’ at the end of section 56 on page 60.]

47

We may call this thinking self (the soul) substance, as being the ultimate subject of thinking that can’t be further represented as the predicate of something else; but the concept ·of substance, in this use of it·, remains quite empty, with nothing following from it, if it can’t be shown to involve permanence—which is what makes fruitful the concept of substances that we encounter in experience.

But permanence can never be proved on the basis of the concept of a substance considered as a thing in itself, but only in relation to experience. This is adequately shown by the first Analogy of Experience ·in the Critique of Pure Reason·. If that proof doesn’t convince you, try for yourself whether you can derive from the concept of a subject that doesn’t exist as the predicate of another thing that its existence is thoroughly permanent and that it cannot—unaided or through any natural cause—either come into existence or be annihilated. Synthetic a priori propositions such as that can never be proved ·of things· in themselves, but only in application to things as objects of possible experience.

^8 If the representation of self-awareness, the I, were a concept through which something could be thought, it could be used as a predicate of other things or would contain such predicates in itself. But it is nothing more than the feeling of something existing, without the slightest concept of it; it is only the representation of that to which all thinking relates.

50

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is metaphysics possible?

48
So if we want to use the concept of •the soul as substance as a basis on which to conclude that •the soul is permanent, we can do this only in relation to possible experience; if we take the soul to be a thing in itself, and look for a conclusion that holds good beyond the bounds of all possible experience, permanence can’t be shown. But all our possible experience requires us to be alive; so the only permanence-of-the-soul result we can establish is that the soul is permanent throughout one’s life; for the death of man is the end of all experience that the soul could have of itself as an object—unless the contrary is proved, but that ‘contrary’ is supposed to be the conclusion of the argument for the soul’s permanence, so it can’t appear among the premises. The most we can show, therefore, is that the soul is permanent throughout one’s life—a result that nobody will disagree with! What we want is to show that the soul lasts after death, and this we cannot do, for the reason I have given: the necessary tie between the concept of substance and the concept of permanence is created by the principles of possible experience, and so it holds good only within the domain of possible experience.^9

49
Here’s something else that can be proved ·as a requirement for the intellectual management· of experience, but can’t be shown to hold of things in themselves: Our outer experience not only does but must correspond to something real outside of ourselves. That tells us this much: there is something empirical—thus, some phenomenon in space outside us—·the existence of· which can be satisfactorily proved. ·That’s all it tells us·, for we have no dealings with objects other than those belonging to possible experience; because objects that can’t be presented to us in any experience are nothing to us. What is empirically outside me is what appears in space. Now space, together with all the phenomena it contains, belongs to the representations whose objective truth is proved by how they are inter-connected according to laws of experience, just as the actuality of my soul (as an object of inner sense) is proved by how the phenomena of inner sense are inter-connected. Accordingly, •it is by outer experience that I am conscious of the actuality of bodies, as external phenomena in space, just as •by inner experience I am conscious of the existence of my soul in time; but I know this soul only as an object of inner sense—knowing it only through appearances that constitute my inner state;

^9 It is indeed very remarkable that metaphysicians have always glided comfortably over the principle that substances are permanent without trying to prove it. No doubt this is because as soon as they started on the concept of substance they found that every possible basis for a proof had deserted them. Common sense, which strongly felt that perceptions couldn’t be unified in experience without this presupposition ·of the permanence of substance· filled the gap by a postulate. (·It had to postulate permanence instead of proving it· because it could never derive the necessary permanence of substance from experience itself, for two complementary reasons. (1) We have no way of tracking substances through all their alterations and dissolutions and finding ·empirically· that their matter, their stuff, is never lessened. (2) The principle in question involves necessity, which is a sure sign of its being an a priori principle ·and thus not knowable through or provable from experience·.) People then optimistically applied this postulate ·about all substances· to the concept of soul as a substance, and inferred from this that a man’s soul must continue in existence after his death (especially because this substance’s having no parts—which they inferred from the indivisibility of consciousness—guaranteed that it couldn’t be destroyed by falling to pieces). If they had found the genuine source of this principle of the permanence of substance—a discovery requiring deeper researches than they were ever inclined to make—they would have seen that the law of the permanence of substances holds good only for the purposes of ·intellectually managing· experience; so it applies to things only so far as they are to be known and conjoined with others in experience. It never applies independently of all possible experience, and consequently it cannot hold good of the soul after death.

51

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is metaphysics possible?

the nature of the soul in itself—the thing that has these phenomena—is unknown to me. So all that Cartesian idealism achieves is to distinguish •outer experience from •dreaming; and to distinguish the •conformity to law that is a criterion of the truth of the former from the •irregularity and false illusion of the latter. In ·dealing with· both ·outer experience and dreaming· Cartesian idealism presupposes space and time as required for the existence of objects; its only question is this:

•Are the objects of the outer senses, which when awake we put in space, actually to be found in space (as the object of inner sense, the soul, is actually to be found in time)?

That amounts to this:

•Does experience carry with it sure criteria to distinguish it from imagination?

Doubts about this are easy to dispose of. We dispose of them in ordinary life every time we investigate how appearances in both space and time are connected according to universal laws of experience: when the representation of outer things agrees thoroughly with those laws, we can’t doubt that they constitute truthful experience. So it is very easy to refute material idealism, which ·questions the existence of bodies, although it doesn’t think of them as things in themselves, but· considers appearances as appearances and takes account only of how they are connected in experience: it is just as sure an experience that bodies exist outside us (in space) as that I myself exist according to the representation of inner sense (in time); ·I put it like that because· the concept of outside us means existing in space. Compare these two:

•taking ‘body’ to refer not merely to outer intuition (in space) but to the thing-in-itself that is the basis of this appearance—·the thing that the appearance is an appearance of·,

and

•taking the ‘I’ in the proposition ‘I am’ to refer not merely the object of inner intuition (in time) but to the subject of consciousness—·the thing that has the consciousness·.

The ‘body’ thought generates •the question of whether bodies (which are really phenomena of outer sense) exist as bodies in nature apart from my thoughts—a question that can be briskly answered in the negative. The ‘I’ thought generates •the question of whether I myself (an appearance of inner sense, the soul that empirical psychology studies) exist apart from my faculty of representation in time; and this question is on exactly the same footing as the other, and must likewise be answered in the negative.

Everything is decided and certain in this way, once it has been given its true meaning, Formal idealism (which I have also called ‘transcendental idealism’) actually abolishes material (or Cartesian) idealism. For if space is nothing but a form of my sensibility, then it is—as a representation in me—just as actual as I myself am; and the only remaining question concerns the empirical truth of the representations in space. And if on the other hand space and the phenomena in it are something existing outside us, then the actuality of these ·alleged· objects outside us can never be proved ·in the way it would have to be proved, namely· by applying the criteria of experience beyond the domain of our perception.

II. The cosmological Idea

50
The cosmological Idea is the most remarkable product of pure reason in its transcendent use. It has more power than anything else to rouse philosophy from its dogmatic slumber

52

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is metaphysics possible?

and to stimulate it to a hard task, namely making a critique of reason itself.

I term this Idea ‘cosmological’ because it never takes its object from anywhere but the world of the senses, having no use for anything that isn’t given to the senses. So in that way it stays at home, does not become transcendent, and is to that extent not a mere Idea. (Whereas ·the psychological Ideas don’t in that sense ‘stay at home’, because· merely conceiving the soul as a simple substance involves conceiving something—the simple—that can’t be presented to the senses.) Despite that, the cosmological Idea ·does in its own way go outside the domain of the senses, because it· extends the connection of the conditioned with its condition so far that experience never can keep up with it. In this way, then, it is always an Idea, whose object can never be adequately given in any experience.

51
Note first that in this territory ·of the cosmological Ideas· the usefulness of a system of categories is so obvious and unmistakable that this alone would show that it is indispensable in the system of pure reason, even if there weren’t several other proofs of that. There are exactly four such transcendent Ideas, and exactly four classes of categories; but ·the Ideas differ from the categories in that· they are concerned only with the absolute completeness of the series of the conditions for a given conditioned item. Matching these cosmological Ideas there are exactly four kinds of dialectical assertions of pure reason. Their being dialectical shows in this:

Against each of these assertions we can bring its contradictory, on the strength of principles of pure reason that are as plausible as those supporting the original assertion.

No exercise of metaphysical art can fend off this conflict ·between the assertion and its contradictory· except the one that compels the philosopher to look into the first sources of pure reason itself. This Antinomy—·i.e. this conflict between dialectical assertions and their contradictories·—isn’t something I thought up to amuse myself: it comes from the nature of human reason; so it can’t be avoided or brought to an end. The Antinomy contains the following four theses together with their antitheses:

(1) Thesis: The world has a beginning in time and space (a limit).
Antithesis: The world is spatially and temporally infinite.

(2) Thesis: Everything in the world consists of ·elements that are· simple.
Antithesis: There is nothing simple; everything is composite.

(3) Thesis: There are in the world causes through freedom.
Antithesis: There is no liberty; all is nature.

(4) Thesis: In the series of the world’s causes there is some necessary being.
Antithesis: There is nothing necessary in the world; in that series everything is contingent.

52a
We have here the strangest phenomenon of human reason; no other use of reason produces anything like it. If we •think of the appearances of the world of the senses as things in themselves (as we often do), and if we •take them to be combined through principles that hold universally for things in themselves rather than merely through principles of experience (which we also often do—indeed without my critique we can’t help it!), there arises a conflict that can’t be removed dogmatically ·by proving one side and refuting

53

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is metaphysics possible?

the other·. That’s because thesis and antithesis can both be shown by equally clear, evident, and compelling proofs (I guarantee that all the proofs are correct), so reason is divided against itself—which gladdens the heart of the sceptic but must make the critical philosopher feel ill at ease.

52b
We can blunder in various ways in metaphysics without any fear of being detected in falsehood. For as long as we avoid self-contradiction, which we can always do when we assert synthetic propositions (even if they are wholly fictitious), ·our only way of being detected in falsehood is through experience. And· experience can’t refute us when we assert propositions ·of the sort involved in metaphysics, namely ones· in which the concepts that are involved are mere Ideas, instances of which can’t be presented to us in experience. For how can we tell from experience whether the world has lasted from eternity or had a beginning, whether matter is infinitely divisible or consists of simple parts? Such concepts can’t be instantiated in any experience, however extensive, and consequently neither the positive nor the negative proposition ·in the antinomy· can be empirically discovered to be false. The only way in which reason could unintentionally reveal its secret dialectic, which it falsely offers as positive doctrine, would be for this to happen:

Reason bases an assertion on a universally admitted principle, and infers the exactly opposite assertion, with the greatest correctness of argument, from another principle that is equally accepted.

That’s what actually does happen in our present case of the four natural Ideas of reason, from which arise four assertions and four counter-assertions, each validly derived from universally accepted principles, revealing the dialectical illusion of pure reason in the use of these principles—an illusion that would otherwise have stayed hidden for ever.

So this is a decisive experiment, which must necessarily reveal to us any error lying hidden in the presuppositions of reason.^10 Contradictory propositions can’t both be false unless they both involve some self-contradictory concept. ·And then they can both be false·. For example A square circle is round is false (it is false that the circle is round, because it is square), and A square circle is not round is likewise false (it is false that the circle isn’t round, i.e. that it has corners, because it is a circle.) The logical mark of the impossibility of a concept consists precisely in this, that two contradictory propositions involving it are both false, and as no third proposition can be thought between them, nothing at all is thought through that concept.

52c
The first two antinomies, which I call ‘mathematical’ because they are concerned with the addition or division of the homogeneous, are based on such a self-contradictory concept; and that’s how it comes about that in each of them both the thesis and antithesis are false. [Re ‘homogeneous’: see the start of the next section’s second paragraph.]

When I speak of objects in time and in space, I am speaking not about •things in themselves (of which I know nothing), but about •things in appearance, i.e. about experience as a particular way of knowing objects—the only way of knowing

^10 I should therefore like the critical reader ·of the Critique of Pure Reason· to attend especially to this antinomy of pure reason, because nature itself seems to have arranged it to pull reason up short in its bold claims, and to force it to look into itself. I take responsibility for every proof I have given for the thesis as well as for the antithesis, and thereby promise to show the certainty of the inevitable antinomy of reason. If this curious phenomenon ·of the ‘proofs’ of both P and not-P· leads you to go back to examine the presupposition on which it is based, you will feel yourself obliged to join me in inquiring more deeply into the ultimate basis of all knowledge of pure reason.

54

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is metaphysics possible?

them that has been granted to mankind. When I think of something as being in time or in space, I must not say ·or think·:

In itself it exists in space and in time, independently of these thoughts of mine;

for if I did I would be contradicting myself. That’s because space and time, together with appearances in them, are nothing existing in themselves and outside my representations, but are themselves only modes of representation [= ‘ways of being represented-to’], and it is plainly contradictory to say that a mere mode of representation exists outside our representation. So objects of the senses exist only in experience; and to attribute to them a self-subsisting existence •apart from experience or •in advance of it amounts to telling ourselves that experience is real apart from experience or in advance of it!

Now if I ask about the extent of the world in space and in time, my complete stock of concepts doesn’t enable me to call it infinite or to call it finite. For neither state of affairs can be contained in experience: there can’t be experience of an infinite space, or of an infinite time elapsed; or of the world’s being bounded by empty space or by empty time before the world began—all these are mere Ideas. This finite or infinite size of the world, ·not being cashable out in terms of experience·, would therefore have to belong to the world itself apart from all experience. But this contradicts the notion of •a world of the senses, which is merely a totality of appearances that exist and are interconnected only in our representation, that is, in experience, since •this world is not an object in itself but a mere mode of representation. From this it follows that the answer ‘Yes’ to the question ‘Is the world finite in space or in time?’ is false, and so is the answer ‘No’; because the concept of a world of the senses existing for itself and in itself is self-contradictory.

The same holds good for the second antinomy, concerning the division of appearances. For these appearances are mere representations, and their parts exist only in the representation, and consequently exist only in the dividing, i.e. in a possible experience that presents them; and the dividing can go only as far as this experience goes. If you assume that an appearance, such as that of a body, contains—in itself, in advance of all experience—all the parts that any possible experience can ever reach, what you are doing amounts to this:

Attributing to a mere appearance, which can exist only in experience, an existence preceding experience; or saying that mere representations are there before we encounter them through our faculty of representation.

This is self-contradictory, and consequently so is each answer to the misconceived question ·about divisibility·, whether we answer that bodies in themselves consist of infinitely many parts, or that they have a finite number of simple parts.

53

In the first (the mathematical) class of antinomies the falsehood of the assumed proposition consisted in •taking contradictory items (appearance, thing in itself) to be harmoniously compatible within a single concept. In the second (dynamic) group, on the other hand, the falsehood of the assumed proposition consists in •taking a consistent pair of propositions to be mutually contradictory. Thus, in the first class of antinomies the opposed assertions •were both false, while in the second class the two propositions—which are treated as opposed to one another through mere misunderstanding—•may both be true.

Connecting items mathematically through the concept of ·spatial or temporal· size requires that the connected

55

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is metaphysics possible?

items be of the same kind; but dynamic connections by no means require that kind of homogeneity. When it comes to extended magnitudes—·i.e. stretches of space or of time·—all the parts must be homogeneous with one another and with the whole; but in the connection of cause and effect, although •homogeneity may be found there too, it isn’t necessary. Or at any rate the concept of causality doesn’t require it, because cause-effect has to do with positing something through something else •quite different from it.

If the objects of the world of the senses were taken for things in themselves, and the laws of nature discussed above were taken to be laws of things in themselves, contradiction would be unavoidable. Similarly, if the subject of freedom were taken to be a mere appearance, like other objects, contradiction would be equally unavoidable, for the same predicate taken in the same sense would be at once affirmed and denied of one and the same object. But if natural necessity is tied only to appearances, and freedom only to things in themselves, there’s no contradiction in assuming or allowing both kinds of causality at once, however hard or impossible it may be to make the latter kind (freedom) comprehensible.

In ·the realm of· appearance every effect is an event, something that happens in time; so according to the universal law of nature it must be preceded by a cause, some state of which leads to the event according to a constant law. But the cause’s entering into this state that gives it its causal power must likewise take place or happen; the cause must have begun to act, for without that the effect’s following from it cannot conceived. ·Without such a beginning·, the effect, as well as the effectiveness of the cause, would have to have existed always. This yields the result:

•The state of the cause that makes it effective must also have started among appearances, being an event (just as the effect is), and so have been caused in its turn, and so on ·backwards for ever·.

Which in turn yields the further result:

•The condition that governs the coming-into-effectiveness of causes must be natural necessity.

If on the other hand, certain causes of appearances have the property of being free, then freedom must be a capacity for starting these appearances—these events—spontaneously; there’s no such event as the cause’s starting to be effective, and thus no need for anything outside the cause to prod it into starting to be effective. But in that case the cause must have its effectiveness in a manner that doesn’t place it in time; so it can’t be an appearance, and must be regarded as a thing in itself, with only its effects being appearances.^11 If we can without contradiction think of beings of the understanding—·choices, decisions, etc.·—as

^11 The only acceptable use of the Idea of freedom is in ·thinking about· the relation of the intellectual (as cause) to appearance (as effect)—·the relation between what a person chooses and how his body moves·. So the incessant action through which ·any portion of· matter fills its space—·acting so as to keep other matter out of that place·—though it takes place from an internal principle [here = ‘source’ or ‘driver’], can’t be an exercise of freedom. Nor can we find a concept of freedom that is suitable for purely rational beings such as God. For his action, though independent of external determining causes (because it is only his immanent or caused-from-within action that I am talking about), is determined in his eternal reason, that is, in the divine nature ·which never changes·. It is only if something is to start by an action, so that the effect occurs in the time-series or in the world of our senses (e.g. the beginning of the world), that the question arises of whether •the effectiveness of the cause must in its turn have been started, or whether instead •the cause can initiate an effect without its own effectiveness beginning. In the former case the concept of this causality is a concept of natural necessity, in the latter, that of freedom. From this you will see that in explaining freedom as the faculty of starting an event spontaneously I have exactly hit the notion which is the problem of metaphysics.

56

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is metaphysics possible?

exercising such an influence on appearances, then ·that enables us to have the second part of the following two-part story·:

•Natural necessity is what links all causes to all effects ·when both cause and effect belong· in the world of the senses.

•Freedom is possessed by any cause that isn’t itself an appearance though it underlies an appearance.

So nature and freedom can without contradiction be attributed to the very same thing, but in different relations—on one side as an appearance, on the other as a thing in itself. We have in us a faculty that is not merely

•connected with its subjective determining grounds that are the natural causes of its actions, and is in that way the faculty of a being that belongs to appearances,

but is also

•connected to objective grounds (that are only Ideas), being connected to them in that they can determine [here = ‘influence’] this faculty—a connection expressed by the word ought.

·To spell that out a little in more familiar terms: When a person decides how to act on some occasion, the question ‘Why did he make that decision?’—a request to know what determined him to make it—can have answers of two entirely different kinds. •One kind explains the decision in terms of his prior state of mind, and the psychological laws that led from that to his decision. •The other kind explains the decision in terms of his reasons for it, his beliefs about what he ought to do. The former kind of answer invokes natural necessity; the second doesn’t, because it doesn’t explain the decision as an event arising from prior events; it is the second that takes us out of the realm of appearance, and makes room for freedom·. This faculty—·the one involved in the second kind of answer·—is called reason. To the extent that we consider a man exclusively in the light of his reason, viewed as responding to objective judgments about what he ought to do, to that extent we aren’t viewing him as a being of sense—·an inhabitant of the world of our senses·—because this freedom ·or responsiveness to the ‘ought’ thought· is a property of a thing in itself. We can’t at all grasp how it is possible—i.e. how the ought, which is not ·an event, not· something that has happened, can determine the man’s activity, becoming the cause of actions ·which are things that happen, and· whose effect is an appearance in the world of the senses. Still, ·although we don’t grasp how this can be·, if reason did relate in this ‘influencing’ way to a person’s decisions, that would bring freedom into what happens in the world of the senses to the extent that we can see those happenings as influenced by objective grounds (which are themselves Ideas). For reason’s effectiveness as a cause wouldn’t depend on subjective conditions—·i.e. on facts about the person’s prior state of mind·—and therefore wouldn’t depend on events in time or on the law of nature that controls such events. That’s because the grounds of reason—·the basic ‘ought’ thoughts·—govern actions in a universal way, according to ·universal· principles, without influence from the circumstances of either time or place.

What I am presenting here is meant merely as an example to make things intelligible. It doesn’t necessarily belong to our problem—·i.e. the question How is metaphysics in general possible?·—which must be decided from mere concepts, independently of the properties that we meet in the actual world.

Now I can say without contradiction that •all the actions of rational beings, so far as they are appearances, fall under •the necessity of nature; but •those same actions, considered purely in terms of the rational subject and its ability to act

57

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is metaphysics possible?

according to mere reason, are •free. For what is required for the necessity of nature? Only that every event in the world of the senses come about in accordance with constant laws, thus being related to causes in the domain of appearance; and in this process the underlying thing in itself remains out of sight, as does its causality. But I maintain this:

The law of nature still holds, whether or not the rational being causes effects in the world of the senses through reason and thus through freedom. If it does, the action is performed according to maxims whose effects in the realm of appearance are always consistent with constant laws; if on the other hand it doesn’t, the action is ·not merely consistent with but· subject to the empirical laws of the sensibility, and in this case as in the other the effects hang together according to constant laws.

This conformity to laws is all we demand for natural necessity; indeed, it exhausts all that we know about natural necessity. But in •the former case ·where the action is caused by reason·, reason is the cause of these laws of nature ·rather than being subject to them·, and therefore it is itself free; in •the latter case, where the effects follow according to mere natural laws of sensibility with reason having no input, it doesn’t follow that reason is in this case determined by the sensibility, which indeed it couldn’t be, so reason is free in this case too. Freedom, therefore, doesn’t get in the way of natural law in the domain of appearance, any more than natural law brings about a breakdown in the freedom of the practical use of reason, which relates to things in themselves as determining grounds.

Thus practical freedom—the freedom in which reason has causal force according to objectively determining grounds—is rescued, without doing the slightest harm to natural necessity in relation to the very same effects, as appearances. These remarks explain what I said earlier about transcendental freedom and its compatibility with natural necessity (with a single subject taken in two different ways). For

whenever a being acts from objective causes regarded as determining grounds ·of reason·, the start of its action is a first beginning,

although

the same action is in the series of appearances only a subordinate beginning, which must be preceded and determined by a state of the cause, which in turn is determined by another immediately preceding it ·and so on backwards·.

In this way we can have the thought, for •rational beings and quite generally for •any beings whose causality is determined in them as things in themselves, of a being’s ability to begin a series of states from within itself, without falling into conflict with the laws of nature. For the relation the action has to objective grounds of reason isn’t a temporal one; in this case what determines the causality does not precede the action in time, because determining grounds such as reason provides don’t involve •objects of sense such as causes in the domain of appearance, but rather •determining causes as things in themselves, which don’t exist in time. And so the action can without inconsistency be seen •(with regard to the causality of reason) as a first beginning and as free, and •(with regard to the series of appearances) as a merely subordinate beginning and as subject to natural necessity.

The fourth Antinomy is solved in the same way as is reason’s conflict with itself in the third. The propositions at issue in the fourth—·that there is a necessary being, and that there is not·—are perfectly reconcilable provided we distinguish the cause IN the domain of appearance from the cause OF the domain of appearance (with the latter thought of as a thing in itself). Then one proposition says:

58

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is metaphysics possible?

Nowhere in the world of the senses is there a cause (according to similar laws of causality) whose existence is absolutely necessary;

the other says:

This world is nevertheless connected with a necessary being as its cause (but of another kind and according to another law).

The ‘incompatibility’ of these propositions entirely rests on the mistake of extending what is valid merely of appearances to things in themselves, and in general running the two together in one concept.

54
This then is how I present and how I solve the entire antinomy in which reason finds itself caught when it applies its principles to the world of the senses. The mere presentation would contribute a lot to the knowledge of human reason, even if the solution hadn’t yet fully satisfied you—which it well might not, because you have to combat a natural illusion that has only recently been exposed to you and that you have previously always regarded as genuine. For there’s no escaping from this: so long as you take the objects of the world of the senses to be things in themselves, and not the mere appearances which is what they really are, you haven’t any chance of avoiding this conflict of reason with itself; so you must re-examine my deduction of all our a priori knowledge and the tests that I put it through, in order to come to a decision on the question. This is all I require at present; for if in carrying this out you take your thoughts deeply enough into the nature of pure reason, you will familiarize yourself with the concepts through which alone the solution of the conflict of reason is possible. Unless that happens, I can’t expect complete assent even from the most attentive reader.

III. The theological Idea

55
·I have discussed the •psychological Idea(s) and the •cosmological Idea(s). Now·:
The •third transcendental Idea is the ideal of pure reason. The use of reason for which it provides material is the most important of all; though if it is pursued in a merely ·theory-building or· speculative manner, that makes it transcendent—·theorizing outside the domain of possible experience·—which in turn makes it dialectical. With the psychological and cosmological Ideas, reason starts with experience, and goes wrong by taking a grandiose view of its grounds and trying to achieve, where it can, the absolutely complete series of grounds. Not so with the third, theological Idea. Here reason totally breaks with experience; and—starting from mere concepts of what would constitute the absolute completeness of a thing in general, and thus bringing in the Idea of •a most perfect primal being—it works down from there to secure the possibility and therefore the actuality of •all other beings. And so the mere presupposition of a being that is conceived not in the series of experience but for the purposes of experience—for the sake of comprehending its connection, order, and unity—that is, the Idea, is distinguished from the concept of the understanding more easily in this case than in the others. Hence we can easily expose the dialectical illusion that arises from our taking the subjective conditions of our thinking to be objective conditions of objects themselves, and taking an hypothesis necessary for the satisfaction of our reason to be an objectively established truth. I have nothing more to say here about the pretensions of transcendental theology, because my remarks about them in the Critique are easily grasped, clear, and decisive.

59

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How is metaphysics possible?

56: General remark on the transcendental Ideas
The objects given to us by experience are in many respects incomprehensible, and the law of nature leads us to many questions ·about them· which, when carried beyond a certain point (though still in conformity with those laws), cannot be answered. For example: why do material things attract one another? But if we •go right outside nature, or •·stay within it but· in thinking about how it is interconnected go beyond all possible experience and so enter the realm of mere Ideas, then we can’t say that our subject-matter is incomprehensible and that the nature of things confronts us with insoluble problems. For in this case we aren’t dealing with nature—or, to put it more generally, we aren’t dealing with •given objects—but with •concepts that have their origin solely in our reason, and with mere creations of thought; and all the problems that arise from our concepts of them must be soluble, because of course reason can and must give a full account of its own process.^12 As the psychological, cosmological, and theological Ideas are nothing but pure concepts of reason that can’t be applied to anything found in any experience, the questions that reason confronts us with regarding them don’t come from objects but from mere maxims that our reason lays down for its own satisfaction. It must be possible for them all, as a group, to be satisfactorily answered, which is done by showing that they are principles for bringing our use of the understanding into thorough harmony, completeness, and synthetic unity, so that they do in that way hold good for experience—but for experience as a whole. But although an absolute whole of experience is impossible, the Idea of a totality of knowledge according to principles is needed if our knowledge is to have a special kind of unity, the unity of a system. Without that, our knowledge is nothing but piece-work, and can’t be used for the highest end (which is always the establishment of a general system of all ends). I am talking here not only about practical ·or moral· ends, but also about the highest end of the speculative use of reason.

The transcendental Ideas thus express reason’s special role, namely as setting a standard for systematic unity in the use of the understanding. But if the following happens:

We see this unity in our way of knowing as attached to the object of knowledge; we take something that is merely regulative to be constitutive; and we persuade ourselves that by means of these Ideas we can extend our knowledge far beyond all possible experience (and thus in a transcendent manner),

this is •a mere misunderstanding in our estimate of the proper role of our reason and of its principles, and it is •a dialectic that confuses the empirical use of reason and also sets reason against itself. What makes it a misunderstanding is the fact that really reason serves merely to bring experience as near as possible to completeness within itself, i.e. to stop its progress from being limited by anything that can’t belong to experience. [A regulative principle is one that guides, advises, or even commands—such as ‘Never accept that you have found an event that didn’t have a cause’. A constitutive principle is one that gives information, has factual content, purports to tell truths about reality. Kant holds, for example, that ‘Every event has a cause’ is acceptable as regulative, but not as constitutive.]

^12 Herr Platner in his Aphorisms acutely says: ‘If reason is a criterion, there can’t be a concept that human reason cannot comprehend. Incomprehensibility comes up only with what is actual....’ So it only sounds paradoxical and is not really strange to say that although much in nature is beyond our comprehension (e.g. biological reproduction), if we rise still higher and go right out beyond nature everything will be comprehensible again. For then we leave behind the objects which can be given us, and occupy ourselves merely with Ideas; and here we can easily grasp the law that reason, through them, prescribes to the understanding for its use in experience, because that law is reason’s own product.

60

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Conclusion

Conclusion

Determining the boundaries of pure reason

57
After the clearest arguments, which I have provided, it would be absurd for us to hope to know more of any object than belongs to the possible experience of it, or lay claim to the slightest knowledge of anything not taken to be an object of possible experience—knowledge that would tell us what the thing is like in itself. For how could we learn such facts, given that time, space, and the categories—and even more all the concepts drawn from empirical intuition or perception in the world of the senses—don’t and can’t have any use other than to make experience possible, and that even the pure categories are meaningless if they are removed from this relation to perception?

But on the other hand it would be even more absurd if we rejected things in themselves, or declared that •our experience is the only possible way of knowing things, •our intuition of them in space and in time the only possible intuition, •our concept-using understanding the pattern for every possible understanding—all of which would amount to taking the principles of the possibility of experience to be universal conditions of things in themselves.

My principles, which limit the use of reason to possible experience, could in that way become transcendent, and the limits of our reason might pass themselves off as limits of the possibility of things in themselves (Hume’s Dialogues ·Concerning Natural Religion· illustrate this process), if a careful critique didn’t both watch over the bounds of our reason....and set a limit to its pretensions. Scepticism originally arose from metaphysics and its lawless dialectic. Wanting to favour the experiential use of reason, it started out by declaring that whatever transcends this use is worthless and deceitful; but little by little, as the awareness sank in that the a priori principles used in experience lead (surreptitiously, and seemingly just as legitimately) further than experience extends, there came to be doubts even about experience. There’s no danger in this ·error·, for healthy common sense will doubtless always assert its rights ·regarding experience·. But a certain confusion arose in science, which can’t work out how far reason is to be trusted—and why just this far and no further?—and the only way to clear up this confusion and forestall any future relapses is through a formal, principled fixing of the boundary of the use of our reason.

It is true: we can’t rise above all possible experience and form a definite concept of what things in themselves may be. Nevertheless, we aren’t free to stop enquiring into them; for experience never satisfies reason fully; rather, in answering ·our· questions it points further and further back, leaving us still hungering for their complete solution. You can see this in the dialectic of pure reason, the solid subjective ground for which consists in just this hunger for completeness. As regards the nature of our soul: having a clear awareness of oneself as a subject, and having become convinced that psychological phenomena can’t be explained materialistically, •who can refrain from asking what the soul really is? And if no concept of experience suffices for the purpose, •who can refrain from accounting for it by a concept of reason (the concept of simple immaterial being), even though we are totally unable to show its objective reality? As regards

61

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Conclusion

all the cosmological questions about the duration and size of the world, and about freedom versus natural necessity, •who can be satisfied with mere empirical answers to these, when every answer given on empirical principles gives rise to a fresh question, which then requires an answer in its turn, and in this way clearly shows that reason can’t be satisfied by explanations relying on facts about how things go in the empirical world? Finally, •who doesn’t see, from the utter contingency and dependence of everything he thinks and assumes using mere principles of experience, the impossibility of stopping with those principles? And •who doesn’t feel himself compelled, despite all the prohibitions against losing himself in transcendent Ideas, to seek peace and contentment (beyond all the concepts that he can vindicate by experience) in the concept of a being the Idea of which can’t be seen to be possible, but which can’t be refuted either because it relates to a mere being of the understanding, without which ·Idea· reason would remain forever dissatisfied?

Where extended things are concerned, boundaries always presuppose a space existing outside a certain definite place, and enclosing it; limits don’t require anything like that, but are mere negations, indicating of some quantity that it isn’t absolutely complete. But our reason sees around itself a space for knowledge of things in themselves, so to speak, though it can never have definite concepts of them and is limited to appearances only.

As long as the knowledge of reason is all of one kind—·for example, reasoning within number-theory, within geometry, within natural science, or the like·—definite boundaries to it are inconceivable. In mathematics and in natural science human reason recognizes limits, that is, recognizes that its inner progress will never be complete; but it doesn’t recognize boundaries, i.e. doesn’t recognize that outside it there’s something it can’t ever reach. In mathematics there’s no end to the enlargement of our insight or to the new discoveries that may be made; similarly in natural science, there’s no end to the discovery of new properties of nature, of new forces and laws, through continued experience and unification of it by reason. ·So these sciences are never complete, which means that at any time they have limits·. But these limits should not be misunderstood—·i.e. should not be thought of as boundaries·—for mathematics bears only on appearances, and so it has no dealings with anything that can’t be an object of sensible intuition, such as the concepts of metaphysics and of morals, ·which means that it has no dealings with anything that could be a boundary for it·. Mathematics can never lead to such things, and has no need for them. So there is a continual progress and approach towards ·completion in· these sciences, towards the point or line, so to speak, of contact ·with completeness·. The inwardness of things doesn’t show up in the domain of appearance, though ·the Idea of· it can serve as the ultimate ground of explanation of appearances; and natural science will never reveal it to us. But it isn’t needed for scientific explanations. Indeed, even if such ·ultimate grounds of explanation· were to be offered from other sources (for instance, if angels told us about them), natural science still ought to reject them and not use them to advance •its explanations. For •those must be based only on what can belong to experience as an object of sense and be connected with our actual perceptions in accordance with empirical laws.

But metaphysics, in the dialectical attempts of pure reason (which we don’t undertake arbitrarily or wantonly, being driven to them by the nature of reason itself), leads us to boundaries. And the transcendental Ideas, just because we can’t evade them and can never realize them ·in the sense

62

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Conclusion

of encountering an instance of one of them·, serve not only to •tell us that the pure use of reason has boundaries, but also to •show us where they are. That’s the purpose and function of this disposition of our reason, which has given birth to metaphysics as its favourite child; and this child, like every other in the world, is a product not of blind chance but of an original seed that is wisely organized for great purposes. For metaphysics, perhaps more than any other science, has in its main outlines been placed in us by nature itself, and can’t be viewed as the outcome of an arbitrary choice or of an accidental enlargement ·of our thoughts· in the progress of experience—from which indeed it is wholly separate.

Concepts and laws of the understanding suffice for the empirical use of reason, that is, for the use of it within the world of the senses; but they don’t satisfy reason itself, because it faces an infinite sequence of questions with no hope of ever completely answering them. The transcendental Ideas, which have that completion as their aim, are such problems of reason. Now reason sees clearly that the world of the senses can’t contain this completion, neither (therefore) can all the concepts that serve only for understanding the world of the senses—space and time, and the ones I have presented under the label ‘pure concepts of the understanding’. The world of the senses is nothing but a chain of appearances connected according to universal laws; so it •has no existence for itself, •isn’t really the thing in itself, and consequently must stand in a relation to ·something other than itself, namely· to what contains the grounds of this experience—to beings that can be known not merely as phenomena but as things in themselves. It is only in the knowledge of these that reason can hope to satisfy its demand for completeness in the advance from the conditioned to its conditions.

In sections 33-4 above I indicated the limits of reason with regard to all knowledge of mere creations of thought. [The word ‘limits’—Schranken—doesn’t occur in those two sections.] Now, since the transcendental Ideas have made it necessary for us to approach them, and thus have led us to the spot where •occupied space meets •the void, so to speak—i.e. where •experience touches •that of which we can know nothing, namely noumena—we can settle what the boundaries are of pure reason. For in all boundaries there’s something positive:

for example, a surface is the boundary of corporeal space, and is itself a space; a line is a space that is the boundary of a surface; a point is the boundary of a line but yet is always a place in space,

whereas limits contain mere negations. The limits pointed out in sections 33 and 34 are still not enough [meaning ‘not enough to satisfy us’?] once we have discovered that there is still something beyond them (though we can never know what it is in itself). For the question now arises: How does our reason conduct itself in this connection of what we know with what we don’t know and never shall? There is here an actual connection of the known with something completely unknown (which will always remain so); and even if the unknown isn’t going to become the least bit known (and there’s no hope that it will), the concept of this connection must still be capable of being identified and brought into clarity.

So we ought to have the thought of an immaterial being, a world of understanding, and a supreme being (all mere noumena), because •it is only in these items—as things in themselves—that reason finds completion and satisfaction, which it can never hope for in deriving appearances from grounds that are homogeneous with them ·and therefore demand to be grounded in their turn·. Another reason why we ought to ought to have those thoughts is that •·appearances· really do bring in something distinct from

63

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Conclusion

themselves (and totally unlike them), in that appearances always presuppose an object in itself ·of which the appearance is an appearance·, and thus they suggest its existence whether or not we can know more of it.

Now, we can never know these beings of understanding as they are in themselves, i.e. determinately, but still we have to assume them in •relation to the world of the senses and connect them with that world by means of reason; so we shall at least be able to think •this connection by means of such concepts as express their relation to the world of the senses. ·This relational approach to noumena is the best we can do·. For if we think a being of the understanding •through nothing but pure concepts of the understanding, we really think nothing definite, and consequently our concept has no significance; and if we think it •through properties borrowed from the world of the senses, it is no longer a being of understanding but is thought as one of the phenomena and belongs to the world of the senses. I shall illustrate this with the notion of the supreme being.

The •deistic concept—·i.e. the •thin concept of a (not necessarily personal) supreme being·—is a wholly pure concept of reason; but all it represents is a thing containing all realities. It can’t pick out any one reality—·thereby saying something in detail about the supreme being·—because to do so it would have to use an example taken from the world of the senses, and in that case I (·as a user of the concept in question·) would after all be dealing only with an object of the senses, not something of a radically different sort that can never be an object of the senses. Here’s an example:

Suppose that I attribute understanding to the supreme being. My only concept of understanding is one that fits understandings like mine—one that has to get its intuitions ·passively· from the senses, and that occupies itself ·actively· in bringing those intuitions under rules of the unity of consciousness. If I applied that concept to the supreme being, I would be saying that the raw materials of the supreme being’s thought come from the realm of appearance; but it was the inadequacy of appearances ·to meet the demands of reason· that forced me to beyond them to the concept of a being that doesn’t •depend on appearances and isn’t •identified or characterized through them. ·To credit the supreme being with understanding, therefore, I need a concept of understanding from which the notion of getting-data-from-the-senses has been purged·. But if I separate understanding from sensibility to obtain a pure understanding ·that the supreme being might have·, then nothing remains but the mere form of thinking without intuitions; and form alone doesn’t enable me to know anything definite, and so it doesn’t enable me to point my thought at the supreme being as an object. ·On the one hand, then, I mustn’t suppose that the supreme being •thinks about sensible intuitions; on the other, I mustn’t suppose that the supreme being •thinks without having intuitions to think about. So·: for my purpose ·of attributing understanding to the supreme being· I would have to conceive another kind of understanding, such as would ·actively· intuit its objects ·itself, instead of passively having intuitions of them brought to it by sensibility·. But I haven’t the least notion of such an understanding, because human understanding is conceptual, its only way of knowing is through general concepts, ·and it has no ability to present itself with intuitive data·.

I shall run into exactly the same trouble if I attribute a will to the supreme being; for I have this concept only by drawing it from my internal experience; I experience will in myself as

64

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Conclusion

based on facts of the form I shall not be satisfied unless I get object x, which means that my will is grounded in sensibility, ·through which desired objects are presented to me·; and that ·dependence on sensibility· is absolutely incompatible with the pure concept of the supreme being.

Hume’s objections to deism are weak, and affect only the arguments and not the thesis of deism itself. But as regards theism, which is supposed to come from adding certain content to deism’s merely transcendent ·and thus empty· concept of the supreme being, his objections are very strong; indeed they are irrefutable as arguments against certain forms of theism, including all the usual ones. Hume always insists that •by the mere concept of an original being, to which we apply only ontological predicates (‘eternal, ‘omnipresent’, ‘omnipotent’), we don’t think anything definite, and that •other properties must be added if we are to have a concept of a definite, concrete thing. ·This isn’t a trivial requirement, Hume holds. For example, he says that· it isn’t enough to say It is a cause; but we must explain what kind of causality it has—for example, whether it is exercised through understanding and will—and that is the point at which his attack begins on his real topic, theism; up to there he had been attacking only the arguments for deism, which isn’t a notably dangerous thing to do. All his dangerous arguments refer to anthropomorphism [from Greek meaning ‘man-shaped-ism’; in theology anthropomorphism is the view that God is like man]. Hume holds this to be inseparable from theism, and to make it internally self-contradictory; and if anthropomorphism were left out ·of the theological story·, theism would drop out with it, and nothing would remain but deism. We can’t make anything out of deism: it is worthless, and can’t serve as a foundation for religion or morals. If this anthropomorphism were really unavoidable, no proofs whatever of the existence of a supreme being, even if they were all granted, could give us a detailed concept of this being without involving us in contradictions.

When we connect the command to avoid all transcendent judgments of pure reason with the apparently conflicting command to proceed to concepts that lie beyond the domain of immanent (empirical) use, we become aware that the two commands can subsist together, but only right on the boundary of all permitted use of reason—for this boundary belongs equally to the domain of experience and to that of the creations of thought [= Ideas]. And through that awareness we also learn how these Ideas, remarkable as they are, serve merely for marking the boundaries of human reason. On the one hand they give warning •not to go on extending our empirical knowledge with no thought of boundaries, as though nothing but sheer world remained for us to know, and yet on the other hand •not to overstep the bounds of experience and want to make judgments about things beyond them, as things in themselves.

But we stop at this boundary if we limit our judgment merely to how •the world may relate to •a being whose very concept lies beyond the reach of any knowledge we are capable of within the world. For we don’t then attribute to the supreme being in itself any of the properties through which we represent objects of experience, and so we avoid dogmatic anthropomorphism; but we attribute those properties to the supreme being’s relation to the world, thus allowing ourselves a symbolic anthropomorphism, which in fact concerns only language and not the object itself.

When I say that we are compelled to view the world as if it were the work of a supreme understanding and will, I actually say nothing more than that a watch, a ship, a regiment, are related to the watchmaker, the shipbuilder, the commanding officer in the same way that the sensible world (or everything that underlies this complex of appearances) is

65

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Conclusion

related to the unknown; and in saying this I don’t claim to know the unknown as it is •in itself, but only as it is •for me or •in relation to the world of which I am a part.

58
Such knowledge is knowledge by analogy. This doesn’t involve (as the word ‘analogy’ is commonly thought to do)

•an imperfect similarity of two things, but rather

•a perfect similarity of relations between the members of two quite dissimilar pairs of things.^13

By means of this analogy we are left with a concept of the supreme being that is detailed enough for us, though we have omitted from it everything that could characterize it absolutely or in itself; for we characterize only its relation to the world and thus to ourselves, and that is all we need. Hume’s attacks on those who want to determine this concept absolutely, taking the materials for doing so from themselves and the world, don’t affect my position; he can’t object against me that if we give up the objective anthropomorphism of the concept of the supreme being we have nothing left.

Hume in the person of Philo in his Dialogues grants to Cleanthes as a necessary hypothesis the deistic concept of the original being, in which this being is thought through nothing but the ontological predicates of ‘substance’, of ‘cause’, etc. ·Two comments on this·:

(1) We must think the original being in this way; because ·there’s no other way to think it, and if we don’t have any thought of the original being· reason can’t have any satisfaction in the world of the senses, where it is driven by mere conditions that are in their turn conditioned, ·thus driving us back along a never-starting sequence of causes·. If the use of reason in relation to all possible experience is to be pushed to the highest point while remaining in complete harmony with itself, the only possible way to do this is to assume a highest reason as a cause of all the connections in the world. Such a principle must be thoroughly advantageous to reason, and can’t hurt it anywhere in its natural use.

^13 Thus, there is an analogy between the legal relation of human acts and the mechanical relation of motive powers. I can never do something to someone else without giving him a right to do the same to me in the same circumstances; just as no body can act on another through its motive power without thereby causing the other to react equally against it. Right and motive power are quite dissimilar things, yet in their relation there is complete similarity. By means of such an analogy I can give a relational concept of things that are absolutely unknown to me. For example, as

a = the promotion of the happiness of children

is related to

b = parental love,

so

c = the happiness of the human species

is related to

x = the unknown in God, which we call love.

Not because (x) God’s love has the least similarity to (b) any human inclination; but because we can suppose its relation to the world to be similar to a relation that some things in the world have to some others. But the relational concept in this case is a mere category, namely the concept of cause, having nothing to do with sensibility.

66

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Conclusion

(2) We can properly think the original being in this way, because those predicates—·‘substance’, ‘cause’ etc.·—are mere categories, which yield a concept of the original being that isn’t determinate and for just that reason isn’t limited to any conditions of sensibility. In thinking of the original being in this way we don’t fall into anthropomorphism, which transfers predicates from the world of the senses to a being quite distinct from that world. We aren’t transferring reason as a property to the original being in itself, but only to its relation to the world of the senses; and so anthropomorphism is entirely avoided. For all we are considering here is the cause of •something that is perceived everywhere in the world, namely •the world’s rational form; and insofar as the supreme being contains the ground of this rational form of the world, reason is to be attributed to it. But in saying that the supreme being has reason, we are speaking analogically, expressing only the relation that the unknown supreme cause has to the world, and we do this so as to see everything in the world as being in the highest degree reasonable. This procedure doesn’t involve us in treating reason as an attribute through which we can conceive God; what we do, rather, is to conceive the world in the way that’s needed if we are to tackle it with the greatest possible principled use of reason. In this way we admit that the supreme being in itself is quite inscrutable and isn’t even conceivable in any determinate way, and that keeps us from ·two errors that we might otherwise make. Roughly and briefly, they are the errors of trying to •explain God in terms of the world, and trying to •explain the world in terms of God. A little more fully, •one of the errors is that of·

making a transcendent use of our concept of reason as an efficient cause (by means of the will), trying to describe the nature of God in terms of properties that are only borrowings from human nature—thereby losing ourselves in gross and extravagant notions;

and ·the other error consists in·

allowing our contemplation of the world to be flooded with supernatural patterns of explanation, led by the transfer to God of our notions of human reason—thereby deflecting this contemplation from its proper role, which is to study mere nature through ·human· reason, not rashly to derive nature’s appearances from a supreme reason.

The best way to put it, given our weak concepts, is this: we should conceive the world AS IF its existence and its inner nature came from a supreme reason.

In thinking of it in this way, we achieve two things. •We recognize what the world itself is like, without wanting to determine what its cause is like in itself. And •we see the ground of what the world is like (the ground of the world’s rational form) in the relation of the supreme cause to the world, not finding the world sufficient by itself for that purpose.^14

Returning now to what Philo granted to Cleanthes: We are perfectly free to predicate of this original being a causality through reason in respect of the world, thus moving on to theism; and this doesn’t oblige us to attribute this kind of ·causally powerful· reason to the original being itself, as a property attached to it.

Thus the difficulties that seem to stand in the way of

^14 I shall say: •the causality of the highest cause relates to •the world in the same way that •human reason relates to its artifacts. That leaves the nature of the supreme cause itself still unknown to me: I only compare •its effect (the order of the world) which I know, and the conformity of this to reason, with •the effects of human reason, which I also know; and hence I call the supreme cause ‘reason’, without thereby attributing to it what I understand by ‘reason’ as applied to man, or assigning to it any property of anything else that I know.

67

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Conclusion

theism disappear. We achieve this by joining to Hume’s principle:

Don’t push the use of reason dogmatically beyond the domain of all possible experience

this other principle, which he quite overlooked:

Don’t consider the domain of experience as something which in the eyes of our reason sets its own boundaries.

The critique of reason here indicates the true middle way between •the dogmatism against which Hume fought and •the scepticism that he wanted to introduce to oppose it. It isn’t the usual kind of ‘middle way’, which one is advised to pick out for oneself as it were mechanically (a little of the one, a little of the other), making nobody any the wiser. Rather, it is a middle way that can be delineated exactly, according to principles.

59
At the beginning of this note I used the metaphor of a boundary in order to fix the limits on the proper use of reason. [This ‘note’ is this Conclusion. Its title includes the term ‘boundaries’, but the concept isn’t discussed until pages 62–3.] The world of the senses contains mere appearances, which aren’t things in themselves; but the understanding must assume things in themselves (noumena), because it recognizes the objects of experience as appearances ·and understands that they must be appearances of something·. Our reason covers both •appearances and •things in themselves, and the question arises: How does reason go about setting boundaries to the understanding with respect to both these domains? Experience, which contains all that belongs to the world of the senses, doesn’t set bounds for itself; it proceeds in every case from some conditioned item to some other ·item that is its condition, and is also a· conditioned object; ·and nothing in this procedure requires it ever to come to a halt·. The boundary of experience must lie •wholly outside it, and that is •the domain of pure beings of the understanding. But when it comes to finding out what these beings are like, this domain is for us an empty space; and when we are dealing with concepts whose instances we can identify and study, we can’t move out of the domain of possible experience. But a boundary is itself something positive, which belongs as much to •what lies inside it as to •the space lying outside the given totality; so reason partakes in real positive knowledge when it stretches out to this boundary. Reason doesn’t try to go beyond the boundary, because out there it is confronted by an empty space in which it can conceive •forms of things but can’t conceive •things themselves. Still, even when it adopts this stance towards the boundary, just in setting the boundary reason has knowledge. In this knowledge it isn’t confined within the world of the senses, but it doesn’t stray outside it either; rather, as befits the knowledge of a boundary, it focuses on the relation between what lies outside the boundary and what’s contained inside it.

Natural theology is such a concept at the boundary of human reason, ·because at that boundary· reason finds itself compelled to look out further towards the Idea of a •supreme being (and, for moral purposes towards the Idea of a world that can be thought but not experienced). It doesn’t do this so as to find out anything about this •mere creation of the understanding lying outside the world of the senses; its purpose is rather to employ principles of the greatest possible (theoretical as well as practical) unity to guide its conduct within the world of the senses—a purpose that is served by relating these principles to an independent reason, as the cause of all the connections ·found in the world of the senses·. The aim isn’t to merely invent a being ·of reason. Invention isn’t in question here·, because beyond the world of

68

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Conclusion

the senses there must be something that can be thought only by the pure understanding. Reason’s aim is to characterize this being, though of course only by analogy.

And so we are left with our original proposition, which is the upshot of the whole critique:

Reason, through all its a priori principles, never teaches us about anything except objects of possible experience, and about these it teaches us nothing more than can be known in experience.

But this limitation on what reason can do doesn’t prevent it from leading us to the objective boundary of experience, i.e. to the relation to something that is the ultimate ground of all objects of experience without itself being one of them. Still, reason doesn’t teach us anything about what this ‘something’ is like in itself—only about how it relates to reason’s own complete and utterly high-minded use in the domain of possible experience. But this is all the usefulness we can reasonably want ·reason to have·, and we have cause to be satisfied with it.

60
So I have fully exhibited metaphysics as something we can do, showing it as an automatic upshot of the natural tendency of human reason, and showing what our essential goal is when we do metaphysics. But we have found that ·things can go wrong in this pursuit·: this wholly natural use of such a tendency of our reason, if it isn’t reined in and given limits (which can come only from a scientific critique), entangles us in transcendent dialectical inferences ·leading to conclusions· of which some are illusory and others are even in conflict with one another; and this fallacious metaphysics is not a help but an obstacle to the advancement of our knowledge of nature. So it is worth our while to investigate the natural goals towards which we can steer this liking that our reason has for transcendent concepts, ·and this will counteract the mishaps mentioned above·, because everything that is natural must be originally aimed at some useful purpose.

Such an enquiry is risky, and I admit that what I can say about it is only conjecture, like every speculation about nature’s original purposes. But this is permissible, just this once, because I am enquiring not into •the objective validity of metaphysical judgments but into •our natural tendency to make such judgments, so that the enquiry belongs not to the system of metaphysics but rather to the study of mankind.

The transcendental Ideas, taken all together, form the real problem of natural pure reason, a problem that compels reason to quit the mere observation of nature, to go beyond all possible experience, and in so doing to bring into existence this thing (whether it is knowledge or sophistry!) called metaphysics. When I consider all of these Ideas, I think I see that

the aim of this natural tendency—this metaphysics—is to free our thinking from the fetters of experience and from the limits of the mere observation of nature, taking this freedom at least far enough to open up to us a domain containing only objects for the pure understanding, which no sensibility can reach.

This is not so that we can speculatively occupy ourselves with this domain (for we can find no ground to stand on while we do that), but so that we can think of moral principles as at least possible. ·The connection between their being possible and the domain opened up by metaphysics is as follows·. Reason absolutely requires that moral principles be universal; and they can’t achieve universality unless they can fix their expectations and hopes on the domain of transcendental Ideas ·because in the domain of experience strict universality is never to be found·.

69

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Conclusion

Now I find that the •psychological Idea, little as it shows me of the nature of the human soul ·thought of as something· elevated above all concepts of experience, does plainly enough show the inadequacy of these concepts, and in that way steers me away from a materialist theory of mind—a theory that’s unfit to explain anything in nature, as well as cramping the use of reason in moral thinking. The •cosmological Ideas serve similarly to keep us from naturalism, which asserts that nature is sufficient unto itself; they do this through ·bringing home to us· the obvious fact that even if we had all possible knowledge of nature, reason’s legitimate demands wouldn’t be satisfied. Finally there is the •theological Idea, ·whose service to us is as follows·. All natural necessity in the sensible world is conditioned, because it always involves something’s being necessitated by something else that is also conditioned; and thus unconditional necessity is to be looked for only in a cause that is different from the world of the senses. And the causality of this cause can’t be yet another example of natural necessity, for if it were it could never make comprehensible the existence of the contingent (as its consequent). So the theological Idea, ·which is the Idea of a non-natural cause of everything contingent·, is something that reason uses to free itself from fatalism, and to arrive at the concept of a cause possessing freedom, or of a highest intelligence. (This frees us from both versions of fatalism: (1) blind natural necessity in the system of nature itself, without a first principle, and (2) blind causality of a first principle of nature.) Thus the transcendental Ideas serve, if not to instruct us positively, at least to put a stop to the impudent assertions of materialism, of naturalism, and of fatalism—assertions that restrict the domain of reason—thereby making room for the moral Ideas to operate outside the domain of speculation. This, I should think, goes some way towards explaining reason’s natural tendency ·to engage with Ideas·, which I mentioned earlier.

The facts about the •practical or moral usefulness that a purely •speculative science can have don’t lie within the province of the science itself; so they can be seen simply as a scholium [= ‘explanatory note, marginal comment’] which, like all scholia, is not a part of the science itself. Still, this material surely lies within the boundaries of philosophy, especially of philosophy drawn from the well of pure reason—a part of philosophy in which reason’s •speculative use in metaphysics must necessarily be all of a piece with its •practical use in morals. Hence the unavoidable dialectic of pure reason, considered as something occurring in metaphysics as a natural tendency, deserves to be explained not only as •an illusion that needs to be cleared away but also, if possible, as •·an upshot of· something put in place by nature for a purpose—though this task lies outside the job-description of metaphysics proper, and so can’t rightly be assigned to it.

The solutions of the questions put forward in the Critique at A647–68 = B675–96 should be regarded as a second scholium—this time one that’s more closely related to the content of metaphysics.^15 For that part of the Critique presents certain principles of reason that characterize a priori •the order of nature or rather •the understanding which is to seek nature’s laws through experience. They seem to have

^15 Throughout the Critique I stuck to my resolve not to neglect anything, however deeply hidden, that could enable the inquiry into the nature of pure reason to be completed. Afterwards it is up to each person to decide how far to take his researches, once he has been shown what remains to be done. This ·attitude to further research· can reasonably be expected from someone who has made it his business to survey the whole field, so as to leave it to others for future cultivation and for whatever subdividing of it they think fit. The scholia belong to this ·part of the total project·; because of their dryness they can hardly be recommended to amateurs, and hence they are presented only for experts.

70

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Conclusion

propositional content and not merely to be rules for how the understanding should be employed, and to be law-giving with regard to experience, although they spring from mere reason, which cannot like the understanding be considered as a principle of possible experience. This agreement ·between principles issued by reason and what is found in experience· may rest on this:

Nature isn’t attached to appearances (or to the sensibility through which appearances come) in themselves, but is to be found only in the relation of sensibility to the understanding. ·And just as nature takes us upwards from sensibility to understanding, so the theoretical use of the understanding takes us further upwards to reason·. A thoroughgoing unity in the use of the understanding for the sake of a systematically unified possible experience can be had only if •the understanding is related to reason. And so, ·putting the two together·, experience is indirectly subject to the legislation of reason.

The question of whether this is where the agreement comes from may be pondered by those who want to trace the nature of reason even beyond its use in metaphysics, into the general principles for making general natural history systematic. In the Critique I represented this task as important, but I didn’t try there to carry it out.

And thus I conclude the analytic solution of my own chief question: How is metaphysics in general possible? by starting with the actual doing of metaphysics (or at least with the consequences of that) and climbing from there to the grounds of its possibility. [See the explanation of ‘analytic’, in this sense of the word, on page 6.]

71

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How metaphysics is possible as a science

Solution of the general question of the

Prolegomena:

How is metaphysics possible as a science?

Metaphysics as a natural tendency of reason is real, but by itself it is dialectical and deceitful (as the analytic solution of the third principal question showed). If we set ourselves to take principles from it, and in using them to follow the natural (but nonetheless false) illusion, we can never produce science, but only a pointless dialectical art in which one school may outdo another but none can ever get, and be entitled to, lasting approval.

For metaphysics as a science to be entitled to claim not mere fallacious plausibility but insight and conviction, a critique of reason itself must exhibit

•the whole stock of a priori concepts,

•the classification of them according to their different sources (sensibility, understanding, and reason),

•a complete list of these concepts, and

•the analysis of each of them together with all the consequences of that analysis;

but above all the critique must show

•the possibility of synthetic a priori knowledge (doing this through a deduction of these concepts),

•the principles governing the use of the a priori concepts, and finally

•the boundaries of that use;

and all of this is to be presented in a complete system! Thus criticism, and that alone, contains in itself the whole well-tested and verified plan for achieving metaphysics as a science—the plan and indeed all the means for carrying it out. By any other ways or means the task is impossible. [Here and below, ‘criticism’ translates Kritik, which is usually rendered as ‘critique’.] So the question here isn’t so much •how the task is possible as •how to get it under way, inducing good minds to quit their mistaken and fruitless cultivation in favour of one that won’t deceive, and •how such an alliance for the common end may best be directed.

This much is certain, that someone who has sampled criticism will for ever after be disgusted with all the dogmatic twaddle that he used to endure—he had to endure it because his reason was in need of something and couldn’t find anything better ·than the twaddle· for its nourishment.

Criticism relates to ordinary academic metaphysics exactly as chemistry does to alchemy, or as astronomy does to the astrology of the fortune-teller. I guarantee that when you have thought through and grasped the principles of criticism, even if only in these preliminaries, you will never return to that old and sophistical pseudo-science ·of dogmatic academic metaphysics·; rather, you will look forward with a certain delight to a metaphysics that is now surely in your power, that requires no more preparatory discoveries, and, above all, that can provide reason with permanent satisfaction. For here is an excellence that metaphysics can confidently count on and that no other possible science can: it can be completed and put into a permanent state where there are no more changes to be made, and no additions through new discoveries. That’s because in metaphysics reason has the sources of its knowledge in itself, not in objects and the intuition of them (reason has nothing to learn from intuition); and when it has presented the fundamental laws of its own capacities completely, and so definitely as to prevent any misunderstanding, there’s nothing left for pure reason to know a priori—indeed, there isn’t even any basis

72

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How metaphysics is possible as a science

left for it to ask any further questions. There’s something especially attractive about the sure prospect of knowledge that is so definite and so completed—even apart from all its advantages (of which more later).

All false art, all empty ‘wisdom’, lasts its time out but eventually destroys itself, and its cultural high-point comes at the moment of ·the onrush of· its decay. That this time has come for metaphysics is shown by the condition into which it has fallen in all the learned nations, in contrast with all the zeal with which other sciences of every kind are pursued. The old organization of university studies still preserves its shadow; and now and then a solitary academy of science, by offering prizes, tempts someone or other to have a shot at it; but it is no longer counted among the solid sciences. You can judge for yourself how a gifted man would take it if he were called ‘a fine metaphysician’! It might be meant as a compliment, but hardly anyone would want to be so labelled.

Yet, though •the time of the collapse of all dogmatic metaphysics has undoubtedly arrived, we are still far from being able to say that •the time has come for its rebirth through a solid and complete critique of reason. When someone’s inclinations shift from running one way to running in the opposite direction, he passes through an intermediate stage of indifference ·in which he isn’t inclined in any direction. And this fact about human desires and tendencies has its analogue in shifts of intellectual direction among the sciences·. This moment ·of ‘indifference’, with an old science on the wane and no new one to take its place·, is •the most dangerous for an author, but in my opinion it’s •the most favourable for the science. For when the total breaking of former ties has extinguished the partisan spirit, minds are in the best state to take in, gradually, proposals for a new scheme of alliances. If I say:

I hope that these preliminaries may excite investigation in the domain of criticism, and provide something new and promising to nourish the universal spirit of philosophy that seems ·except for moral philosophy· to be under-nourished,

I can already imagine that everyone who is tired and cross from walking the thorny paths of my critique will ask me: What’s your basis for hoping that? I answer: The basis of the irresistible law of necessity.

Will the human mind ever give up metaphysical researches altogether? There’s no more chance of that than there is of our choosing to give up breathing altogether so as to avoid inhaling impure air! So there will always be metaphysics in the world; what’s more every person—especially every thinking person—will have metaphysical views, and in the absence of a public standard he will tailor them to suit himself. What has been called ‘metaphysics’ up to now can’t satisfy any demanding mind, but it’s quite impossible to give up metaphysics completely; so a critique of pure reason itself must now be attempted; or if one exists it must be investigated and comprehensively tested. There’s no other way to meet this pressing need, which is something more than mere thirst for knowledge.

Ever since I have come to know criticism, when I finish reading a book with metaphysical content—one that has entertained and enriched me by its precision of thought, variety, orderliness, and easy style—I can’t help asking: Has this author really advanced metaphysics a single step? I hope they will forgive me—those learned men whose writings have been useful to me in other respects and have always helped me to develop my mental powers—for saying that I have never been able to find that the science of metaphysics has been advanced in the least by their works or by my own

73

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How metaphysics is possible as a science

lesser ones (even when my egotism speaks in their favour!).

The reason for this is very obvious: it is that metaphysics didn’t then exist as a science; and ·those other writers and I couldn’t make small steps towards bringing it into existence, because· it can’t be assembled bit by bit, but must have its seed fully preformed in the critique. However, in order to prevent any misunderstanding we should bear in mind something I have already said: the understanding gains a great deal from the analytic treatment of our concepts, but the science (of metaphysics) isn’t in the least advanced by it, because these analyses of concepts are merely materials out of which the science is to be assembled in the first place. Let the concepts of substance and of accident be ever so well analysed and fixed; that’s an excellent preparation for some future use. But if I can’t prove that in everything that exists the substance endures and only the properties change, our science isn’t the least advanced by all this analysis. Metaphysics has so far not been able to prove a priori either •the above proposition, or •the principle of sufficient reason, still less •any compound principle such as belongs to psychology or cosmology, or indeed •any synthetic proposition whatsoever. So all this analysis has achieved nothing, created and advanced nothing; and despite all this bustle and clatter the science is right back where it was in Aristotle’s time; though the preparations for it would have been better advanced ·now· than they were ·back then·, if only the guiding thread to synthetic knowledge had been found.

If anyone thinks himself wronged in this, he can easily refute my charge by producing a single synthetic proposition belonging to metaphysics that he offers to prove a priori in the dogmatic manner. Until he has done this I shan’t grant that he has really advanced the science; even if the proposition ·that he claims to be able to prove· is sufficiently confirmed by common experience. No demand can be more moderate or fairer than this, and if it isn’t fulfilled (as it quite certainly won’t be), the fairest verdict we can give is this: Up to now, metaphysics has never existed as a science.

In case my challenge is accepted, I must rule out just two things.

(1) One is: playing around with probability and conjecture, which are as little suited to metaphysics as they are to geometry. Nothing can be more absurd than to think of grounding our judgments on probability and conjecture in metaphysics, which is a philosophy based on pure reason. Everything that is to be known a priori is for that very reason announced as absolutely certain, and must therefore be proved as such. We might as well think of basing geometry or arithmetic on conjectures! The calculus of probability, which is part of arithmetic, contains no •merely probable judgments. Rather, it consists of •completely certain judgments about the degree of possibility of certain upshots in given homogeneous conditions. What happens across the totality of all possible cases must be in accordance with such rules ·or judgments·, though these aren’t determinate enough to say what will happen in any particular case. Only in empirical natural science can conjectures be tolerated (they come in there through induction and analogy), and even there it must at least be quite certain that what one is assuming could be true.

(2) The second thing I rule out is decision by means of the divining rod of so-called sound common sense, which doesn’t dip ·in the same place· for everyone and is guided by ·the· personal qualities ·of the person holding it·. When we are dealing with concepts and principles not considered as valid with regard to experience but considered as valid even beyond the conditions of experience, appealing to •common sense is even more absurd ·than relying on probability·, if

74

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant How metaphysics is possible as a science

that’s possible. For what is common sense? It is ordinary understanding insofar as it judges correctly. But what is •ordinary understanding? It is the capacity for knowledge and for using rules in application to particular cases, as distinguished from •speculative understanding, which is the capacity for knowledge of rules in the abstract. So common sense can hardly understand the rule that every event is determined by its cause, and can never take it in as a general proposition. It therefore demands an example from experience; and when it ·is given one, and· hears that this rule means nothing but what it (·common sense·) always thought when a window-pane was broken or an article of furniture went missing, then it understands the principle and agrees to it. •Ordinary understanding is thus of use only to the extent that it can see its rules confirmed by experience (though actually the rules are in it a priori); consequently the job of having insight into these rules a priori and independently of experience is assigned to •speculative understanding, and lies quite outside the domain of vision of common sense. But metaphysics has to do only with speculative understanding; and someone who appeals to common sense for support in metaphysics shows that he doesn’t have much of it! For in this context common sense has no judgment at all; and ·when it is invoked, there is a kind of bad faith in that, because· it is looked down on with contempt except when people are in difficulties and don’t know where else to turn for advice or help.

These false friends of common sense (who occasionally prize it highly, but usually despise it) customarily offer this excuse ·for sometimes appealing to it·:

There must in the end be some propositions that are immediately certain, and for which there’s no need to give any proof, or even any account at all; because if there were not, there would be no end to the grounds for our judgments. ·And these immediately certain propositions are the ones we know to be true through our common sense·.

But these people can never prove their right to say this by pointing to anything indubitable that they can immediately ascribe to common sense—with two exceptions ·that are irrelevant to our present concerns·. •One is the principle of contradiction, which ·we can set aside because it· is inadequate for showing the truth of synthetic judgments. •The other is comprised of mathematical propositions, such as that twice two make four, and that between two points there is only one straight line, etc. But these judgments are vastly different from those of metaphysics. For in mathematics when I conceptually represent something to myself as possible I can also make it, construct it, in my thought: to one two I add the other two, one by one, and so myself make the number four; or from one point to another I draw in thought all kinds of lines, and can draw only one in which every part is like every other part ·which means that the line is straight·. But ·no such construction has a place in metaphysics, as I shall explain through the example of the concept of causation·: with all my power of thinking I can’t extract from the concept of one thing the concept of something else whose existence is necessarily connected with the first thing; rather, ·if I want a basis for connecting something with something else· I must call in experience. Now, my understanding provides me a priori (yet always only in reference to possible experience) with the concept of such a connection ·between different things·, namely causation. But I can’t exhibit this concept a priori in intuition, thus showing its possibility a priori, as I can the concepts of mathematics. In metaphysics the concept of causation (together with the principles of its application) has to be valid a priori, and for that there must be a justification and deduction of its

75

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Making metaphysics actual as a science

possibility—for otherwise we can’t know what its range of validity is, ·e.g.· whether it can be used only in experience or also outside it. Such a •justification and deduction are nothing remotely like the •intuitive construction through which we can show possibility in mathematics. [See the long note on page ??.]

In metaphysics as a speculative science of pure reason, therefore, we can never appeal to common sense. We can make such an appeal when

we are forced to •abandon pure reason and to renounce all purely speculative knowledge (which must always be knowledge ·strictly so-called·, which involves renouncing metaphysics itself and its teaching on certain matters,

·this ‘forcing’ coming about because·

we find that all we can achieve is •reasonable belief—which suffices for our needs and may indeed be more wholesome for us than knowledge ·strictly so-called·.

When we make that switch, the shape of the situation is completely altered. Metaphysics must be science, over-all and in each part; otherwise it is nothing. That is because metaphysics, as speculation of pure reason, has nothing to hold it steady except universal insights. Beyond its domain, however, probability and common sense can be used legitimately and to good effect, but following principles of their own, the importance of which always depends on their reference to practical life.

That’s what I consider myself entitled to require for the possibility of metaphysics as a science.

Appendix:

On what can be done to make metaphysics actual as a science

As none of the paths that have so far been followed have reached the goal ·of metaphysics as a science·, and since it never will be reached except through a preceding critique of pure reason, it seems reasonable to ask that this present attempt ·at such a critique· be examined carefully and accurately—unless you think it better to give up all pretensions to metaphysics, which is all right as long as you stick to it.

If we take the course of things as it is, not as it ought to be, there are two sorts of judgments: (1) a judgment that precedes the investigation, (2) a judgment that comes after the investigation. In our case (1) is what happens when the reader pronounces judgment on the Critique of Pure Reason on the basis of his own metaphysics, though the possibility of that is what the Critique aimed to investigate. In (2) ·in our case· the reader is able to •set aside for a while the consequences of the critical enquiries, which may clash violently with the metaphysics that he used to accept, and •first examines the grounds from which those consequences can be derived. If what ordinary metaphysics offers were

76

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Making metaphysics actual as a science

demonstrably certain (like the theorems of geometry, for instance), judgments of kind (1) would be legitimate; for if the consequences of certain principles conflict with established truths, the principles are false and can be rejected without further enquiry. But if •metaphysics doesn’t have a stock of indisputably certain (synthetic) propositions, and if •it is even the case that a number of the propositions of metaphysics—though as plausible as the best of them—have consequences that conflict with one another, and if •metaphysics contains absolutely no criterion for the truth of specifically metaphysical (synthetic) propositions, then the (1) kind of judging isn’t admissible, and ·the (2) method should be followed, that is· the investigation of the principles of the Critique must precede all judgments as to its worth or unworth. ·In the remainder of this Appendix I shall present an actual example of (1), followed by a proposal for an example of (2)·.

On a sample of a judgment of the Critique prior to its examination

This judgment occurs in an ·anonymous review· in the Göttingen Scholarly News for January 1782.... When an author who knows the subject-matter of his work and has worked hard to present his own thoughts in it falls into the hands of a reviewer who for his part •is sharp enough to see the points on which depend the value (if any) of the book, who •doesn’t hang on the words but goes for the content, and •confines himself to sifting and testing the principles from which the author started, the author may dislike the severity of his judgment but the public doesn’t mind it because here the public is the winner. And the author can be glad that an opportunity to correct or explain his work has come through the examination of a competent judge. If he thinks he is mainly right, he can in this way remove any obstacles that might eventually hurt the success of his work.

It’s not like that with my reviewer. He seems to have missed entirely the real point of my enquiry. Perhaps he was impatient with thinking his way through a lengthy work; or angry at the threatened reform of a science in which he thought he had settled everything long ago; or—what I reluctantly believe is the case—narrowness of grasp stopped him from carrying his thoughts beyond his school metaphysics. Anyway, he •impetuously whips through a long series of propositions which no-one cd grasp without knowing their premises, and •scatters around his condemnations without giving understandable reasons. So his review is no use to the reader, and doesn’t do the slightest harm to me in the judgment of experts. So I would have passed over this review completely if it hadn’t given me an opportunity to provide some clarifications that may save some readers of these Preliminaries from misinterpretations.

Wanting to position himself so as to set the whole work in a light that is most unflattering to its author, doing this easily without putting any work into it, Reviewer begins and ends by saying: ‘This work is a system of transcendental (or, as he translates it, of higher) idealism.’^16

^16 ‘Higher’—no way! High towers, and metaphysically-great men that resemble them, are not for me—there is usually too much wind around them! My place is the fertile bottom-land of experience; and the word ‘transcendental’—whose meaning was so often explained by me but not once grasped by Reviewer (so carelessly has he looked at everything)—doesn’t signify something that •goes beyond all experience, but something that •does indeed precede experience a priori, but whose role is simply •to make knowledge through experience possible. If these concepts step beyond experience, their employment is termed transcendent, as distinct from their immanent use, that is, their use limited to experience. ·Don’t confuse ‘transcendent’ with ‘transcendental’·. All misunderstandings of this kind have been adequately guarded against in the work itself, but it suited the reviewer’s turn to misunderstand me. [The use here of ‘Reviewer’, as though it were a proper name, is Kant’s. He will do this once more.]

77

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Making metaphysics actual as a science

A glance at this line showed me what sort of review was in store for me. It was like someone who has never seen or heard of geometry, finds a copy of Euclid and on flipping through its pages sees various figures, is asked his opinion of it, and replies: ‘The work is a text-book of drawing; the author uses a special language in which to give dark, incomprehensible directions that in the upshot teach nothing more than what everyone can accomplish with a good natural eye, etc.’

Meanwhile, let us see what sort of idealism it is that runs through my whole work, although it is far from constituting the soul of the system.

The thesis of all genuine idealists from the Eleatic school to Bishop Berkeley is contained in this formula:

All knowledge through the senses and experience is nothing but sheer illusion, and only in the ideas of the understanding and reason is there truth.

The principle that governs and determines my idealism throughout is on the contrary:

All knowledge of things through unaided pure understanding or pure reason is nothing but sheer illusion, and only in experience is there truth.

This is precisely the opposite of the former, genuine idealism. So how did I come to use this expression for a completely opposite purpose, and how did my reviewer come to see genuine idealism everywhere?

The solution of this difficulty rests on something that could have been very easily understood—by anyone who wanted to!—from the over-all structure of the work. Space and time, together with everything they contain, are not things or qualities in themselves, but belong merely to the appearances of such things and qualities; up to this point I am doctrinally at one with the ·genuine· idealists. But they, and especially Berkeley, regarded space ·itself· as a mere empirical representation, and held that it together with all its properties is known to us only by means of experience or perception—just like the appearances in space. As against this, I show in the first place, that

space (and also time, which Berkeley ignored) and all its properties can be known by us a priori, because space (as well as time) •is present in us before all perception or experience as a pure form of our sensibility and •makes possible all sensible intuition and thus all appearances.

It follows from this ·contrast between Berkeley and me· that •because truth rests on universal and necessary laws as its criteria, experience for Berkeley can have no criteria of truth, because its appearances (according to him) have nothing underlying them a priori, from which it follows in turn that they are nothing but sheer illusion; whereas for me space and time (in combination with the pure concepts of the understanding) prescribe their law a priori to all possible experience, and this at the same time yields the sure criterion for distinguishing truth from illusion in experience.^17

My so-called idealism (properly: critical idealism) is thus of a quite special kind, in that

it overthrows ordinary idealism; and through it all a priori knowledge, even that of geometry, first re-

^17 Genuine idealism always has a visionary purpose; it is bound to. But my idealism is designed solely for grasping the possibility of our a priori knowledge of objects of experience—a problem that has never been solved before, and never even been posed. In this way all visionary idealism collapses. As was already to be seen in Plato, visionary idealism inferred from our ·having· a priori knowledge (even that of geometry) ·that there is· another intuition different from that of the senses, namely an intellectual intuition. It never occurred to any of them that the senses themselves might intuit a priori ·as I say they do, for example in geometry·.

78

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Making metaphysics actual as a science

ceives objective reality; and even the most zealous ·ordinary· realists couldn’t have claimed that, because they lacked my demonstrated ideality of space and time—·that is, my proof that space and time are forms of our sensibility·.

In these circumstances I would have liked, so as avoid all misunderstanding, to name this concept of mine differently; but I can’t very well alter the name totally. So I may be permitted in future to call it ‘formal idealism’ (·as I did on page 52·) or, better, ‘critical idealism’, to distinguish it from the dogmatic idealism of Berkeley and the sceptical idealism of Descartes.

I find nothing else worthy of comment in this review of my book. All the way through the reviewer presents blanket judgments—a smart procedure for a reviewer to use, because it doesn’t reveal the state of his knowledge or ignorance; ·whereas· a single criticism that was thorough and detailed, if it concerned the main issue (as it ought to), might have exposed error in my work, and might also have revealed the reviewer’s level of skill in this sort of enquiry. Another well-conceived device for removing early on the readers’ desire to read the book itself—readers who usually form their conceptions of books merely from newspaper articles—is •to pour out all in one breath a number of propositions, torn out of the context of their grounds of proof and explanations, which are bound to strike the reader as nonsensical (especially considering that they are poles apart from all ·ordinary· school-metaphysics), •to make the reader disgusted with the demands on his patience ad nauseam, and then, after presenting ·and attributing to me· the brilliant proposition that constant illusion is truth (which was news to me!), •to conclude with the firm, fatherly rebuke: ‘What’s the point, then, of this quarrel with accepted language, what’s the point—and what’s the source—of the idealistic distinction?’ After a first judgment that all that is special in my book is metaphysically heretical, now at the end it is said to be a mere change of language; which clearly proves that my would-be judge hasn’t the slightest grasp of it, and hasn’t even understood himself.^18

Reviewer speaks like a man who must be aware of having important and excellent insights—but ones that he keeps hidden, for I don’t know of anything recent relating to metaphysics that would justify his tone. It is wrong for him to withhold his discoveries from the world, for there are doubtless many others like me who haven’t been able to find, in all the fine things that have been written in this branch of philosophy, anything that has advanced the science ·of metaphysics· by so much as a finger-breadth. What we do find are •definitions sharpened, •lame proofs fitted out with new crutches, •the crazy-quilt of metaphysics supplied with new patches or with a change of pattern; but none of this is what the world requires! The world has had enough of metaphysical assertions; what is wanted is ·to establish· •the possibility of this science, •the sources from which certainty could be derived in it, and •sure criteria by which to distinguish the dialectical illusion of pure reason from truth. The reviewer must have the key to all this; otherwise he would never have spoken in such a high tone.

But ·joking aside· I am inclined to suspect that no such requirement for the science ·of metaphysics· has ever entered his head. If it had,

he would have focussed on this matter in his review, and ·if he thought I had been wrong about it· even a failed attempt in such an important affair would

^18 [Kant has a footnote here, protesting at two of the reviewer’s misunderstandings.]

79

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Making metaphysics actual as a science

have won his respect. If that is how things stand, we are good friends again. He can think his way as deeply as he likes into his metaphysics; no-one will stop him; but he can’t make judgments about the source of metaphysics in reason, for that lies outside metaphysics.

·That’s if the requirements for a science of metaphysics had entered his head·. But my suspicion ·that they didn’t· is not unfounded, as is shown by the fact that he doesn’t say a word about •the possibility of synthetic knowledge a priori, though this was •the real problem on the solution of which the fate of metaphysics wholly rests, and to which my Critique (along with the present Preliminaries) was entirely directed. The idealism that he stumbled on ·in the Critique·, and was pinned down by, was incorporated in the system only because it was the sole means for solving •the above problem (though it was later confirmed on other grounds); so ·if he had understood what was going on· he would have to have shown either that the problem isn’t as important as I make it out to be in the Critique (and again now in these Preliminaries), or that my appearance concept doesn’t solve it at all or provides a solution that is inferior to some other. But I don’t find a word of this in the review. So the reviewer understood nothing of what I wrote, and perhaps also nothing of the spirit and nature of metaphysics itself; unless (and I would rather think this) a reviewer’s haste, and annoyance at the difficulty of working through so many obstacles, threw an unfavourable shadow over the work lying before him, hiding from him its fundamental features.

In the domain of metaphysics as elsewhere, there is a good deal to be done before a learned journal—however carefully recruited and well-chosen its contributors are—can maintain its otherwise well-deserved reputation. Other sciences and branches of knowledge have their standards. Mathematics has its standard within itself; history and theology have it in secular or sacred books; natural science and medicine have it in mathematics and experience; jurisprudence has it in law books; and even matters of taste have standards in the examples of the ancients. But for judging the thing called metaphysics the standard has yet to be found (I have made an attempt to settle what it is and how it should be used). Until it is worked out, what is to be done when works of this kind are to be judged? If the works are of the dogmatic kind, do what you like with them; when someone plays the master over others ·in this game·, it won’t be long before he runs into someone else who pays him back in kind. But if the writings are of the critical sort—offering a critique not of other writings but of reason itself—then the standard of judgment can’t be •taken for granted but must first be •sought for. When such writings are in question, it may still be all right to offer objections and blame; but underlying them should be an attitude of co-operation, because the need ·for standards, and for metaphysics to become a science· is common to us all, and the lack of the needed insight makes it inappropriate for anyone to come across as a judge handing down verdicts.

But so as to connect this defence ·of my work· with the interests of the philosophizing public, I propose a test that will settle the question of how metaphysical enquiries should be directed towards their common end. It is just what mathematicians have done to show by competition which methods are best:

I challenge my reviewer critic to prove in his way any one really metaphysical principle that he accepts. Being metaphysical it must be synthetic and known a priori from concepts. It •could be one of the most indispensable principles, as for instance the principle of the persistence of substance, or of the necessary

80

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Making metaphysics actual as a science

determination of events in the world by their causes; but it •must (this is a fair demand) be proved on a priori grounds.

If he can’t do this (and silence is a confession), he must admit that

as metaphysics is nothing at all without the absolute certainty of propositions of this kind, ·and as he can’t prove any of them in his dogmatic manner·, the first thing that’s needed—before anything else is done—is to establish the possibility or impossibility of metaphysics, in a critique of pure reason.

So he is obliged either to admit that my principles of criticism are correct, or to prove that they are not. I can already foresee that, although he has been carefree in his reliance on the certainty of his principles, when it comes to a strict test he won’t find a single one in the whole range of metaphysics that he can boldly bring forward. So I shall grant him the most favourable terms that can ever be expected in such a competition, namely: I shall take the onus of proof from him and lay it on myself.

He finds in these Preliminaries [section 51] and in my Critique (B 454–89, the Antinomies chapter) eight propositions, in pairs whose members contradict each other, but each of which necessarily belongs to metaphysics, which must either accept or disprove it (although each has in its day been accepted by some philosopher). Now the reviewer is at liberty to select •any one he likes out of these eight propositions, and to accept it without any proof (that’s a gift from me), but •only one (for wasting time won’t do either of us any good); and then to attack my proof of the contrary proposition. If I can rescue the latter, thereby showing that the opposite of the proposition he chose can be just as clearly proved in accordance with principles that every dogmatic metaphysics must necessarily recognize, then this will settle that metaphysics has a hereditary fault that can’t be explained—let alone removed—until we ascend to the birth-place of metaphysics, pure reason itself. So my critique—·which makes that ascent·—must either be accepted or replaced by a better one; it must at least be studied, which is all I am demanding now. If on the other hand I can’t save my proof, then •a synthetic proposition a priori from dogmatic principles is firmly entrenched on my opponent’s side, •my impeachment of ordinary metaphysics is ·revealed as· unfair, and •I pledge myself to recognize his censure of my critique as justified (though none of this will happen!). But for this it would be necessary, it seems to me, that he should drop his anonymity. Otherwise I don’t see how I could avoid, instead of having just one problem to deal with, being honoured or assailed by many problems from anonymous and indeed uninvited opponents.

Proposal for an investigation of the Critique, on which a judgment can follow

I am obliged to the learned public for the silence with which it has for a long time honoured my Critique; for this shows •a postponement of judgment, and thus •some supposition that a work that leaves all the beaten paths and strikes out on a new and initially difficult one may contain something through which an important but currently withered branch of human knowledge might derive new life and fruitfulness; and thus it also shows •a concern not to break off and destroy the still delicate graft through a hasty judgment. A specimen of a judgment that was delayed for the above reasons is now before my eyes in the Gotha Scholarly News. Setting aside my own (suspect) praise for this review, any reader can see for himself that it is a solid piece of work; this can be seen from its graspable and accurate presentation of a portion of the basic principles of my work.

81

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Making metaphysics actual as a science

Because an extensive structure can’t be judged as a whole from a hurried glance, I propose that it [the system of Critique of Pure Reason] be tested piece by piece from its foundations, and that the present Preliminaries be used as a general outline with which the work itself could then sometimes be compared. If this suggestion were based only on the imagined importance that vanity usually attributes to one’s own output, it would be immodest and would deserve to be indignantly rejected. But ·that isn’t how things stand; something very serious is at stake·; the affairs of speculative philosophy are now on the brink of total extinction, although human reason hangs onto them with undying affection, an affection that is now trying (and failing) to change into indifference because it has been constantly disappointed.

In our thinking age one might expect that many deserving men would use any good opportunity to work together for the common interest of an ever more enlightened reason, if only there were some hope that in this way they would reach their goal. Mathematics, natural science, law, arts, even morals etc., don’t completely fill the soul; there’s always a space staked out for pure, speculative reason. The emptiness of this space prompts us to resort to grotesque masks and worthless glitter, or to mysticism, ostensibly in search of employment and entertainment though really we are just distracting ourselves so as to drown out the burdensome voice of reason, which, true to its own nature, demands something that can satisfy it, and not merely something that started up so as to serve other ends or to satisfy our inclinations. So a study that is concentrated on •this territory of reason existing for itself must (or so I have reason to hope) have a great attraction for anyone who has tried in this way to stretch his thought, because it is just precisely •here that all other kinds of knowledge—all other goals, even—must come together and unite into a whole. I would venture to say that the attraction is greater than any other theoretical knowledge has; one wouldn’t lightly trade this one for any of them—e.g. forgoing metaphysics in order to take up chemistry.

However, for this investigation I am not offering the work itself, but rather these Preliminaries as plan and guide. Although

I am even now well satisfied with the Critique as far as its content, order, and manner of presentation are concerned, and with how carefully I weighed and tested every sentence before writing it down (for it has taken me years to be completely satisfied not only over-all but ·also in detail·, sometimes labouring to become satisfied with the sources of one particular proposition),

I am nevertheless not completely satisfied with my exposition in some chapters of the Doctrine of Elements—for example on the Deduction of the Concepts of the Understanding, or on the Paralogisms of Pure Reason—because a certain long-windedness takes away from their clarity; and your examination ·of the work as a whole· could be based on what these Preliminaries say about those chapters rather than on the chapters themselves.

The Germans are praised for taking things further than people of other nations in matters where steady and continuous work is needed. If this opinion is well founded, then an opportunity to confirm it presents itself here: a project in which all thinking men have an equal interest, and whose successful outcome is hardly in doubt, though it has never succeeded before. The prospects for completing the project are good especially because the science in question is of such a peculiar sort that it can be brought to completion all at once, reaching a permanent state in which it can never be •taken the least bit further, •amplified by later discoveries, or even •altered in any way (apart from improvements in

82

Prolegomena Immanuel Kant Making metaphysics actual as a science

clarity in some places, or improvements in how the science is used for all sorts of purposes). This advantage ·of being made finally complete in a single operation· is one that no other science can have, because none of the others concerns a cognitive faculty that is as completely isolated and as independent of other faculties ·as is the faculty of pure reason·. The present moment seems to be favourable to my expectations, because just now in Germany no-one seems to know how to occupy himself outside the so-called useful sciences, doing something that isn’t mere play, but a project in which success will be permanent.

I must leave to others to work out how the efforts of scholars might be united in the pursuit of this goal. I’m not looking for a mere acceptance of my theses by anyone; I’m not even flattering myself with the hope of that. But as long as the matter is investigated from the ground up, perhaps with ·my system’s being subjected to· attacks, repetitions, qualifications, or confirmation, completion, and extension, the outcome is certain to be a system—maybe not mine—which can become a possession for which future generations will have reason to be grateful.

It would take too long for me to show here •what kind of metaphysics may be expected to ensue if we first get right about the principles of criticism, and to show •how the resultant metaphysics would appear richly and respectably outfitted, not cutting a poor, paltry, plucked figure just because its old false feathers had been pulled out! But other great benefits that such a reform would bring with it are immediately obvious. The ordinary metaphysics had good uses, in that it sought out the elementary concepts of pure understanding in order to clarify them through analysis and make them definite through explanation. In this way it was a training for reason, in whatever direction it might go. But that’s all the good the ordinary metaphysics did; ·and really it did less than that·. For it negated this service ·that it had performed for reason· by encouraging conceit through reckless assertions, sophistry through subtle escapes and excuses, and shallowness through the ease with which it settled the most difficult problems by means of a little school-philosophy. This school-philosophy is all the more seductive the more it has the option of taking something from the language of science (on the one hand) and something from ordinary speech and thought (on the other), thus being all things to all men—but in reality nothing at all! In contrast, criticism gives to our judgment a standard by which knowledge can with certainty be distinguished from pseudo-knowledge; and, by being brought into full operation in metaphysics, criticism lays the basis for a way of thinking that goes on to extend its healthy influence over every other use of reason, for the first time inspiring the true philosophical spirit. But the service that criticism does for theology also, by making it independent of the judgment of dogmatic speculation and thus securing it completely against the attacks of all dogmatic opponents, is certainly not to be valued lightly. For ordinary metaphysics, although it promised to give great help to theology, couldn’t keep this promise; ·indeed it was worse than useless to theology·. By calling speculative dogmatics to its assistance, ·which it did under the influence of common metaphysics·, theology succeeded only in arming enemies against itself. Mysticism, which can prosper in a rationalistic age only when it hides behind a system of school-metaphysics, under the protection of which it may venture to rave rationally, so to speak, will be driven by critical philosophy from this, its last hiding-place. And concerning all of this nothing else can be as important for a teacher of metaphysics as to be able to say—once and for all, with universal agreement—that what he is expounding is at last science, and that it will bring real benefit to the public.

83

Groundwork for the Metaphysic of Morals

Immanuel Kant

Copyright ©2010–2015 All rights reserved. Jonathan Bennett
[Brackets] enclose editorial explanations. Small ·dots· enclose material that has been added, but can be read as though it were part of the original text. Occasional •bullets, and also indenting of passages that are not quotations, are meant as aids to grasping the structure of a sentence or a thought. Every four-point ellipsis .... indicates the omission of a brief passage that seems to present more difficulty than it is worth. Longer omissions are rerported between square brackets in normal-sized type.] In the title, ‘Groundwork’ refers not to the foundation that is laid but to the work of laying it.
First launched: July 2005 Last amended: September 2008
[This single-column (but otherwise unrevised) version by Philosophy Ink derives from the original two-column PDF version at http://www.earlymoderntexts.com. Even Bennett's pagination has been retained since he sometimes makes in-text references to his own page numbers.]

Contents

Preface 1
Chapter 1: Moving from common-sense knowledge to philosophical knowledge about morality 5
Chapter 2: Moving from popular moral philosophy to the metaphysic of morals 14
Chapter 3: Moving from the metaphysic of morals to the critique of pure practical reason 41

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Preface

Preface

Ancient Greek philosophy was divided into three branches of knowledge: •natural science, •ethics, and •logic. This classification perfectly fits what it is meant to fit; the only improvement it needs is the supplying of the principle on which it is based; that will let us be sure that the classification does cover all the ground, and will enable us to define the necessary subdivisions ·of the three broad kinds of knowledge·. [Kant, following the Greek, calls the trio Physik, Ethik and Logik. Our word ‘physics’ is much too narrow for Physik, which is why ‘natural science’ is preferred here. What is lost is the surface neatness of the Greek and German trio, and of the contrast between natural science and metaphysics, Physik and Metaphysik]

There are two kinds of rational knowledge:

•material knowledge, which concerns some object, and

•formal knowledge, which pays no attention to differences between objects, and is concerned only with the form of understanding and of reason, and with the universal rules of thinking.

Formal philosophy is called •‘logic’. Material philosophy—having to do with definite objects and the laws that govern them—is divided into two parts, depending on whether the laws in question are laws of •nature or laws of •freedom. Knowledge of laws of the former kind is called •‘natural science’, knowledge of laws of the latter kind is called •‘ethics’. The two are also called ‘theory of nature’ and ‘theory of morals’ respectively.

•Logic can’t have anything empirical about it—it can’t have a part in which universal and necessary laws of thinking are derived from experience. If it did, it wouldn’t be logic—i.e. a set of rules for the understanding or for reason, rules that are valid for all thinking and that must be rigorously proved. The •natural and •moral branches of knowledge, on the other hand, can each have an empirical part; indeed, they must do so because each must discover the laws ·for its domain·. For •the former, these are the laws of nature considered as something known through experience; and for •the latter, they are the laws of the human will so far as it is affected by nature. ·The two sets of laws are nevertheless very different from one another·. The laws of nature are laws according to which everything does happen; the laws of morality are laws according to which everything ought to happen; they allow for conditions under which what ought to happen doesn’t happen.

•Empirical philosophy is philosophy that is based on experience. •Pure philosophy is philosophy that presents its doctrines solely on the basis of a priori principles. Pure philosophy ·can in turn be divided into two·: when it is entirely formal it is •logic; when it is confined to definite objects of the understanding, it is •metaphysics.

In this way there arises the idea of a two-fold metaphysic—a metaphysic of nature and a metaphysic of morals. Physics, therefore, will have an empirical part and also a rational part, and ethics likewise, though here the empirical part may be called more specifically ‘practical anthropology’ and the rational part ‘morals’ in the strict sense.

All crafts, trades and arts have profited from the division of labour; for when •each worker sticks to one particular kind of work that needs to be handled differently from all the others, he can do it better and more easily than when •one person does everything. Where work is not thus differentiated and divided, where everyone is a jack-of-all-trades, the crafts remain at an utterly primitive level. Now, here is a question worth asking: Doesn’t pure philosophy in each of its parts require a man who is particularly devoted to that part? Some people regularly mix up the empirical with the rational, suiting their mixture to the taste of the public

1

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Preface

without actually knowing what its proportions are; they call themselves independent thinkers and write off those who apply themselves exclusively to the rational part of philosophy as mere ponderers. Wouldn’t things be improved for the learned profession as a whole if those ‘independent thinkers’ were warned that they shouldn’t carry on two employments at once—employments that need to be handled quite differently, perhaps requiring different special talents for each—because all you get when one person does several of them is bungling? But all I am asking is this: Doesn’t the nature of the science ·of philosophy· require that we carefully separate its empirical from its rational part? That would involve putting

•a metaphysic of nature before real (empirical) natural science, and

•a metaphysic of morals before practical anthropology.

Each of these two branches of metaphysics must be carefully cleansed of everything empirical, so that we can know how much pure reason can achieve in each branch, and from what sources it creates its a priori teaching. ·The metaphysic of morals must be cleansed in this way, no matter who the metaphysicians of morals are going to be·—whether they will include all the moralists (there are plenty of them!) or only a few who feel a calling to this task.

Since my purpose here is directed to moral philosophy, I narrow the question I am asking down to this:

•Isn’t it utterly necessary to construct a pure moral philosophy that is completely freed from everything that may be only empirical and thus belong to anthropology?

That there must be such a philosophy is self-evident from the common idea of duty and moral laws. Everyone must admit •that if a law is to hold morally (i.e. as a basis for someone’s being obliged to do something), it must imply absolute necessity; •that the command: You are not to lie doesn’t apply only to human beings, as though it had no force for other rational beings (and similarly with all other moral laws properly so called); •that the basis for obligation here mustn’t be looked for in people’s natures or their circumstances, but ·must be found· a priori solely in the concepts of pure reason; and •that any precept resting on principles of mere experience may be called a practical rule but never a moral law. This last point holds even if there is something universal about the precept in question, and even if its empirical content is very small (perhaps bringing in only the motive involved).

Thus not only are moral laws together with their principles essentially different from all practical knowledge involving anything empirical, but all moral philosophy rests solely on its pure ·or non-empirical· part. Its application to human beings doesn’t depend on knowledge of any facts about them (anthropology); it gives them, as rational beings, a priori laws—·ones that are valid whatever the empirical circumstances may be·. (Admittedly ·experience comes into the story in a certain way, because· these laws require a power of judgment that has been sharpened by experience—•partly in order to pick out the cases where the laws apply and •partly to let the laws get into the person’s will and to stress that they are to be acted on. For a human being has so many preferences working on him that, though he is quite capable of having the idea of a practical pure reason, he can’t so easily bring it to bear on the details of how he lives his life.)

A metaphysic of morals is therefore indispensable, ·for two reasons, one •theoretical and one •practical·. One reason comes from •our wish, as theoreticians, to explore the source of the a priori practical principles that lie in our reason. The other reason is that •until we have the guide and supreme

2

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Preface

norm for making correct moral judgments, morality itself will be subject to all kinds of corruption. ·Here is the reason for that·. For something to be morally good, it isn’t enough that it conforms to the ·moral· law; it must be done because it conforms to the law. An action that isn’t performed with that motive may happen to fit the moral law, but its conformity to the law will be chancy and unstable, and more often than not the action won’t be lawful at all. So we need to find the moral law in its purity and genuineness, this being what matters most in questions about conduct; and the only place to find it is in a philosophy that is pure ·in the sense I have introduced—see page 1·. So metaphysics must lead the way; without it there can’t be any moral philosophy. Philosophy ·that isn’t pure, i.e.· that mixes pure principles with empirical ones, doesn’t deserve the name of ‘philosophy’ (for what distinguishes •philosophy from •intelligent common sense is precisely that •the former treats as separate kinds of knowledge what •the latter jumbles up together). Much less can it count as ‘moral philosophy’, since by this mixing ·of pure with empirical· it deprives morality of its purity and works against morality’s own purposes.

I am pointing to the need for an entirely new field of investigation to be opened up. You might think that ·there is nothing new about it because· it is already present in the famous Wolff’s ‘introduction’ to his moral philosophy (i.e. in what he called ‘universal practical philosophy’); but it isn’t. Precisely because his work aimed to be universal practical philosophy, it didn’t deal with any particular kind of will, and attended only to will in general and with such actions and conditions as that brings in; and so it had no room for the notion of •a will that is determined by a priori principles with no empirical motives, which means that it had no place for anything that could be called •a pure will. Thus Wolff’s ‘introduction’....concerns the actions and conditions of the human will as such, which for the most part are drawn from ·empirical· psychology, whereas the metaphysic of morals aims ·at a non-empirical investigation, namely· investigating the idea and principles of a possible pure will. Without having the least right to do so, Wolff’s ‘universal practical philosophy’ does have things to say about laws and duty; but this doesn’t conflict with what I have been saying. For the authors of this intellectual project remain true to their idea of it ·in this part of its territory also: they· don’t distinguish

•motives that are presented completely a priori by reason alone and are thus moral in the proper sense of the word,

from

•motives that involve empirical concepts—ones that the understanding turns into universal concepts by comparing experiences.

In the absence of that distinction, they consider motives without regard to how their sources differ; they treat them as all being of the same kind, and merely count them; and on that basis they formulate their concept of obligation, ·so-called·. This is as far from moral obligation as it could be; but in a philosophy that doesn’t decide whether the origin of all possible practical concepts is a priori or a posteriori, what more could you expect?

Intending some day to publish a •metaphysic of morals, I now present this •groundwork, ·this exercise of foundation-laying·, for it. There is, to be sure, no other basis for such a metaphysic than a critical examination of pure practical reason, just as there is no other basis for metaphysic than the critical examination of pure speculative reason that I have already published. [The unavoidable word ‘speculative’ (like its cognate‘speculation’) is half of the dichotomy between practical and speculative. A speculative endeavour is one aimed at establishing truths about what is the case, implying nothing about what ought to be the

3

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Preface

case; with no suggestion that it involves guesswork or anything like that. Two of Kant’s most famous titles— Critique of Pure Reason and Critique of Practical Reason —are really short-hand for Critique of Pure Speculative Reason and Critique of Pure Practical Reason. respectively. That involves the speculative/practical contrast; there is no pure/practical contrast. The second of those two works, incidentally, still lay in the future when Kant wrote the present work.] However, ·I have three reasons for not plunging straight into a critical examination of pure practical reason·. (1) It is nowhere near as important to have a critical examination of pure •practical reason as it is to have one of ·pure· •speculative reason. That is because even in the commonest mind, human reason can easily be brought to a high level of correctness and completeness in moral matters, whereas reason in its theoretical but pure use is wholly dialectical [= ‘runs into unavoidable self-contradictions’]. (2) When we are conducting a critical examination of pure practical reason, I insist that the job is not finished until •practical reason and •speculative reason are brought together and unified under a common concept of reason, because ultimately they have to be merely different applications of one and the same reason. But I couldn’t achieve this kind of completeness ·here· without confusing the reader by bringing in considerations of an altogether different kind ·from the matter in hand·. That is why I have used the title Groundwork for the Metaphysic of Morals rather than Critique of Pure Practical Reason. (3) A metaphysic of morals, in spite of its forbidding title, can be done in a popular way so that people of ordinary intelligence can easily take it in; so I find it useful to separate this preliminary work on the foundation, dealing with certain subtleties here so that I can keep them out of the more comprehensible work that will come later. [Here and throughout, ‘popular’ means ‘pertaining to or suitable for ordinary not very educated people’. The notion of being widely liked is not prominent in its meaning.]

In laying a foundation, however, all I am doing is seeking and establishing the supreme principle of morality—a self-contained and entirely completable task that should be kept separate from every other moral inquiry. Until now there hasn’t been nearly enough attention to this important question ·of the nature of and basis for the supreme principle of morality·. My conclusions about it could be •clarified by bringing the ·supreme· principle to bear on the whole system of morality, and •confirmed by how well it would serve all through. But I must forgo this advantage: basically it would gratify me rather than helping anyone else, because a principle’s being easy to use and its seeming to serve well don’t prove for sure that it is right. They are more likely merely to create a bias in its favour, which will get in the way of its being ruthlessly probed and evaluated in its own right and without regard to consequences.

[Kant has, and uses in the present work, a well-known distinction between •‘analytic’ propositions (known to be true just by analysing their constituent concepts) and •‘synthetic’ propositions (can’t be known without bringing in something that the concepts don’t contain). In this next sentence he uses those terms in a different way—one that goes back to Descartes—in which they mark off not two •kinds of proposition but two •ways of proceeding. In the analytic procedure, you start with what’s familiar and on that basis work out what the relevant general principles are; synthetic procedure goes the other way—you start with general principles and derive familiar facts from them.]

In the present work I have adopted the method that is, I think, the most suitable if one wants to proceed •analytically from common knowledge to settling what its supreme principle is, and then •synthetically from examining this principle and its sources back to common knowledge to which it applies. So the work is divided up thus:

4

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 1

Chapter 1 Moving from common-sense knowledge to philosophical knowledge about morality.

Chapter 2 Moving from popular moral philosophy to the metaphysic of morals.

Chapter 3 Final step from the metaphysic of morals to the critical examination of pure practical reason.

Chapter 1:

Moving from common-sense knowledge to philosophical knowledge about morality

Nothing in the world—or out of it!—can possibly be conceived that could be called ‘good’ without qualification except a GOOD WILL. Mental talents such as intelligence, wit, and judgment, and temperaments such as courage, resoluteness, and perseverance are doubtless in many ways good and desirable; but they can become extremely bad and harmful if the person’s character isn’t good—i.e. if the will that is to make use of these •gifts of nature isn’t good. Similarly with •gifts of fortune. Power, riches, honour, even health, and the over-all well-being and contentment with one’s condition that we call ‘happiness’, create pride, often leading to arrogance, if there isn’t a good will to correct their influence on the mind.... Not to mention the fact that the sight of someone who shows no sign of a pure and good will and yet enjoys uninterrupted prosperity will never give pleasure to an impartial rational observer. So it seems that without a good will one can’t even be worthy of being happy.

Even qualities that are conducive to this good will and can make its work easier have no intrinsic unconditional worth. We rightly hold them in high esteem, but only because we assume them to be accompanied by a good will; so we can’t take them to be absolutely ·or unconditionally· good. •Moderation in emotions and passions, self-control, and calm deliberation not only are good in many ways but seem even to constitute part of the person’s inner worth, and they were indeed unconditionally valued by the ancients. Yet they are very far from being good without qualification—·good in themselves, good in any circumstances·—for without the principles of a good will they can become extremely bad: ·for example·, a villain’s •coolness makes him far more dangerous and more straightforwardly abominable to us than he would otherwise have seemed.

What makes a good will good? It isn’t what it brings about, its usefulness in achieving some intended end. Rather, good will is good because of how it wills—i.e. it is good in itself. Taken just in itself it is to be valued incomparably more highly than anything that could be brought about by it in the satisfaction of some preference—or, if you like, the sum total of all preferences! Consider this case:

Through bad luck or a miserly endowment from step-motherly nature, this person’s will has no power at all to accomplish its purpose; not even the greatest effort on his part would enable it to achieve anything it aims at. But he does still have a good will—not as a

5

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 1

mere wish but as the summoning of all the means in his power.

The good will of this person would sparkle like a jewel all by itself, as something that had its full worth in itself. Its value wouldn’t go up or down depending on how useful or fruitless it was. If it was useful, that would only be the setting ·of the jewel·, so to speak, enabling us to handle it more conveniently in commerce (·a diamond ring is easier to manage than a diamond·) or to get those who don’t know much ·about jewels· to look at it. But the setting doesn’t affect the value ·of the jewel· and doesn’t recommend it the experts.

But there is something extremely strange in this •idea of the absolute worth of the will—the mere will—with no account taken of any use to which it is put. It is indeed so strange that, despite the agreement even of common sense (·an agreement I have exhibited in the preceding three paragraphs·), you’re bound to suspect that there may be nothing to it but high-flown fancy, and that I have misunderstood what nature was up to in appointing reason as the ruler of our will. So let us critically examine the •idea from the point of view of this suspicion.

We take it as an axiom that in the natural constitution of an organized being (i.e. one suitably adapted to life) no organ will be found that isn’t perfectly adapted to its purpose, whatever that is. Now suppose that nature’s real purpose for you, a being with reason and will, were that you should survive, thrive, and be happy—in that case nature would have hit upon a very poor arrangement in appointing your reason to carry out this purpose! For all the actions that you need to perform in order to carry out this intention of nature—and indeed the entire regulation of your conduct—would be marked out for you much more exactly and reliably by instinct than it ever could be by reason. And if nature had favoured you by giving you reason as well as instinct, the role of reason would have been to let you •contemplate the happy constitution of your nature, to admire it, to rejoice in it, and to be grateful for it to its beneficent cause; not to let you •subject your faculty of desire to that weak and delusive guidance and to interfere with nature’s purpose. In short, nature would have taken care that reason didn’t intrude into practical morality and have the presumption, with its weak insight, to think out for itself the plan of happiness and how to get it. Nature would have taken over the choice not only of ends but also of the means to them, and with wise foresight she would have entrusted both to instinct alone. [Kant presents this paragraph in terms not of ‘you’ but of ‘a being’.]

What we find in fact is that the more a cultivated reason devotes itself to the enjoyment of life and happiness, the more the person falls short of true contentment; which is why many people—especially those who have made the greatest use of reason—have a certain hostility towards reason, though they may not be candid enough to admit it. They have drawn many advantages from reason; never mind about its role in the inventions that lead to •ordinary luxuries; my interest is in the advantages of intellectual pursuits, which eventually seem to these people to be also a •luxury of the understanding. But after looking over all this they find that they have actually brought more trouble on themselves than they have gained in happiness; and eventually they come not to despise but to envy the common run of people who stay closer to merely natural instinct and don’t give reason much influence on their doings. ·So much for the drawbacks of well-being and happiness as one’s dominant aim in life·. As for those who play down or outright deny the boastful eulogies that are given of the happiness and contentment that reason can supposedly bring us: the judgment they are making doesn’t involve gloom, or

6

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 1

ingratitude for how well the world is governed. Rather, it’s based on the idea of another and far nobler purpose for their existence. It is for achieving this purpose, not happiness, that reason is properly intended; and this purpose is the supreme condition, so that the private purposes of men must for the most part take second place to it. ·Its being the supreme or highest condition means that it isn’t itself conditional on anything else; it is to be aimed at no matter what else is the case; which is why our private plans must stand out of its way·.

So reason isn’t competent to act as a guide that will lead the will reliably to its objectives and will satisfy all our needs (indeed it adds to our needs!); an implanted instinct would do this job much more reliably. Nevertheless, reason is given to us as a practical faculty, that is, one that is meant to have an influence on the will. Its proper function must be to produce a will that is good in itself and not good as a means. Why? Because

•nature has everywhere distributed capacities suitable to the functions they are to perform,

•the means ·to good· are, as I have pointed out, better provided for by instinct, and

•reason and it alone can produce a will that is good in itself.

This ·good· will needn’t be the sole and complete good, but it must be the condition of all others, even of the desire for happiness. So we have to consider two purposes: (1) the unconditional purpose of producing a good will, and (2) the conditional purpose of being happy. Of these, (1) requires the cultivation of reason, which—at least in this life—in many ways limits and can indeed almost eliminate (2) the goal of happiness. This state of affairs is entirely compatible with the wisdom of nature; it doesn’t have nature pursuing its goal clumsily; because reason, recognizing that its highest practical calling is to establish a good will, can by achieving that goal get a contentment of its own kind (the kind that comes from attaining a goal set by reason), even though this gets in the way of things that the person merely prefers.

So we have to develop •the concept of a will that is to be esteemed as good in itself without regard to anything else, •the concept that always takes first place in judging the total worth of our actions, with everything else depending on it, •a concept that is already lodged in any natural and sound understanding, and doesn’t need to be taught so much as to be brought to light. In order to develop and unfold it, I’ll dig into the concept of duty, which contains it. The concept of a good will is present in the concept of duty, ·not shining out in all its objective and unconditional glory, but rather· in a manner that brings it under certain subjective •restrictions and •hindrances; but •these are far from concealing it or disguising it, for they rather bring it out by contrast and make it shine forth all the more brightly. ·I shall now look at that contrast·.

·My topic is the difference between doing something from duty and doing it for other reasons. In tackling this, I shall set aside without discussion two kinds of case—one for which my question doesn’t arise, and a second for which the question arises but is too easy to answer for the case to be interesting or instructive. Following those two, I shall introduce two further kinds of case·. (1) I shan’t discuss actions which—even if they are useful in some way or other—are clearly opposed to duty, because with them the question of doing them from duty doesn’t even arise. (2) I shall also ignore cases where someone does A, which really is in accord with duty, but where what he directly wants isn’t to perform A but to perform B which somehow leads to or involves A. ·For example: he (B) unbolts the door so as to escape from the fire, and in so doing he (A) enables

7

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 1

others to escape also. There is no need to spend time on such cases·, because in them it is easy to tell whether an action that is in accord with duty is done •from duty or rather •for some selfish purpose. (3) It is far harder to detect that difference when the action the person performs—one that is in accord with duty—is what he directly wanted to do, ·rather than being something he did only because it was involved in something else that he directly wanted to do·. Take the example of a shop-keeper who charges the same prices for selling his goods to inexperienced customers as for selling them to anyone else. This is in accord with duty. But there is also a prudential and not-duty-based motive that the shop-keeper might have for this course of conduct: when there is a buyers’ market, he may sell as cheaply to children as to others so as not to lose customers. Thus the customer is honestly served, but we can’t infer from this that the shop-keeper has behaved in this way from duty and principles of honesty. His own advantage requires this behaviour, and we can’t assume that in addition he directly wants something for his customers and out of love for them he charges them all the same price. His conduct of his policy on pricing comes neither from duty nor from directly wanting it, but from a selfish purpose. [Kant’s German really does say first that the shop-keeper isn’t led by a direct want and then that he is. His point seems to be this: The shop-keeper does want to treat all his customers equitably; his intention is aimed at precisely that fact about his conduct (unlike the case in (2) where the agent enables other people to escape but isn’t aiming at that at all). But the shop-keeper’s intention doesn’t stop there, so to speak; he wants to treat his customers equitably not because of what he wants for them, but because of how he wants them to behave later in his interests. This involves a kind of indirectness, which doesn’t assimilate this case to (2) but does distinguish it from a fourth kind of conduct that still isn’t morally worthy but not because it involves the ‘indirectness’ of (2) or that of (3).]

(4) It is a duty to preserve one’s life, and moreover everyone directly wants to do so. But because of ·the power of· that want, the often anxious care that most men have for their survival has no intrinsic worth, and the maxim Preserve yourself has no moral content. Men preserve their lives according to duty, but not from duty. But now consider this case:

Adversities and hopeless sorrow have completely taken away this unfortunate man’s relish for life. But his fate has not made him ·passively· •despondent or dejected. He is strong in soul, and is •exasperated at how things have gone for him, ·and would like actively to do something about it. Specifically·, he wishes for death. But he preserves his life without loving it, not led by any want or fear, but acting from duty.

For this person the maxim Preserve yourself has moral content.

We have a duty to be charitably helpful where we can, and many people are so sympathetically constituted that without any motive of vanity or selfishness they •find an inner satisfaction in spreading joy and •take delight in the contentment of others if they have made it possible. But I maintain that such behaviour, done in that spirit, has no true moral worth, however amiable it may be and however much it accords with duty. It should be classed with ·actions done from· other wants, such as the desire for honour. With luck, someone’s desire for honour may lead to conduct that in fact accords with duty and does good to many people; in that case it deserves •praise and •encouragement; but it doesn’t deserve •high esteem, because the maxim ·on which the person is acting· doesn’t have the moral content of an action done not because the person likes acting in that way but from duty. [In this context, ‘want’ and ‘liking’ and ‘desire’ are used

8

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 1

to translate Neigung, elsewhere in this version translated as ‘preference’; other translations mostly use ‘inclination’.]

Now consider a special case:

This person has been a friend to mankind, but his mind has become clouded by a sorrow of his own that has extinguished all feeling for how others are faring. He still has the power to benefit others in distress, but their need leaves him untouched because he is too preoccupied with his own. But now he tears himself out of his dead insensibility and acts charitably purely from duty, without feeling any want or liking so to behave.

Now, for the first time, his conduct has genuine moral worth. Having been deprived by nature of a warm-hearted temperament, this man could find in himself a source from which to give himself a far higher worth than he could have got through such a temperament. It is just here that the worth of character is brought out, which is morally the incomparably highest of all: he is beneficent not from preference but from duty.

To secure one’s own happiness is a duty (at least indirectly), because discontent with one’s condition—bundled along by many cares and unmet needs—could easily become a great temptation to transgress against duties. But quite apart from duty, all men have the strongest and deepest desire [Neigung] for happiness, because in the idea of happiness all our desires are brought together in a single sum-total. But the injunction ‘Be happy!’ often takes a form in which it thwarts some desires, so that a person can’t get a clear and secure concept of •the sum-total of satisfactions that goes under the name ‘happiness’. So it isn’t surprising that the prospect of •a single satisfaction, definite as to what it is and when it can be had, can outweigh a fluctuating idea ·such as that of happiness·. For example, a man with the gout [a painful ailment made worse by alcohol and rich food] can choose to enjoy what he likes and put up with the consequences, because according to his calculations (this time, anyway) he hasn’t sacrificed present pleasure to a possibly groundless expectation of the ‘happiness’ that health is supposed to bring. But even for this man, whose will is not settled by the general desire for happiness and for whom health plays no part in his calculations, there still remains—as there does for everyone—the law that he ought to promote his happiness, not from wanting or liking but from duty. Only by following this could his conduct have true moral worth.

No doubt this is how we should understand the scriptural passages that command us to love our neighbour and even our enemy. We can’t be commanded to feel love for someone, or to simply prefer that he thrive. There are two sorts of love: •practical love that lies in the will and in principles of action, and •pathological love that lies in the direction the person’s feelings and tender sympathies take. [Kant uses ‘pathological’ simply to mean that this is a state that the person is in; from Greek pathos = ‘that which happens to a person’; no suggestion of abnormality. His point is that being a loving person is no more morally significant than being a stupid person or a right-handed person.] The latter of these cannot be commanded, but the former can be—and that is a command to do good to others from duty, even when you don’t want to do it or like doing it, and indeed even when you naturally and unconquerably hate doing it.

·So much for the first proposition of morality:

•For an action to have genuine moral worth it must be done from duty.·

The second proposition is:

•An action that is done from duty doesn’t get its moral value from the purpose that’s to be achieved through it but from the maxim that it involves, ·giving the reason why the person acts thus·.

9

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 1

So the action’s moral value doesn’t depend on whether what is aimed at in it is actually achieved, but solely on the principle of the will from which the action is done, irrespective of anything the faculty of desire may be aiming at. From what I have said it is clear that the purposes we may have in acting, and their effects as drivers of the will towards desired ends, can’t give our actions any unconditional value, any moral value. Well, then, if the action’s moral value isn’t to be found in

•the will in its relation to its hoped-for effect,

where can it be found? The only possible source for it is

•the principle on which the will acts—and never mind the ends that may be achieved by the action.

For the will stands at the crossroads, so to speak, at the intersection between •its a priori principle, which is formal, and •its a posteriori driver—·the contingent desire that acts on it·—which is material. In that position it must be determined by something; and if it is done from duty it must be determined by the formal principle of the will, since every material principle—·every contingent driver of the will·—has been withdrawn from it.

The third proposition—a consequence of the first two—I would express as follows:

•To have a duty is to be required to act in a certain way out of respect for law.

(1) As for what will result from my action, I can certainly prefer or be drawn to it, but I can’t have respect for it; to earn my respect it would have to be something the will does, not merely something that its doings lead to. (2) Similarly, I can’t •respect any want or preference: if the preference is mine, the most I can do is to •endorse it; if it is someone else’s I can even •love it—i.e. see it as favourable to my interests. What can get respect and can thus serve as a command is •something that isn’t (1) a consequence of my volition but only a source for it, and isn’t (2) in the service of my preferences but rather overpowers them or at least prevents them from being considered in the choice I make; •this something is, in a word, law itself. Suppose now that someone acts from duty: the influence of his preferences can’t have anything to do with this, and so facts about what he might achieve by his action don’t come into it either; so what is there left that can lead him to act as he does? If the question means ‘What is there objectively, i.e. distinct from himself, that determines his will in this case?’ the only possible answer is law. And if the question concerns what there is in the person that influences his will—i.e. what subjectively influences it—the answer has to be his respect for this practical law, and thus his acceptance of the maxim I am to follow this law even if it thwarts all my desires. (A maxim is a subjective principle of volition. The objective principle is the practical law itself; it would also be the subjective principle for all rational beings if reason fully controlled the formation of preferences.)

So an action’s moral value doesn’t lie in •the effect that is expected from it, or in •any principle of action that motivates it because of this expected effect. All the expected effects—something agreeable for me, or even happiness for others—could be brought about through other causes and don’t need •the will of a rational being, whereas the highest good—what is unconditionally good—can be found only in •such a will. So this wonderful good, which we call moral goodness, can’t consist in anything but the thought of law in itself that only a rational being can have—with the will being moved to act by this thought and not by the hoped-for effect of the action. When the person acts according to this conception, this moral goodness is already present •in him; we don’t have to look for it •in the upshot of

10

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 1

his action.^1 [In passages like this, ‘thought’ translates Vorstellung = ‘mental representation’.]

So we have a law the thought of which can settle the will without reference to any expected result, and must do so if the will is to be called absolutely good without qualification; what kind of law can this be? Since I have robbed the will of any impulses that could come to it from obeying any law, nothing remains to serve as a ·guiding· principle of the will except conduct’s universally conforming to law as such. That is, I ought never to act in such a way that I couldn’t also will that the maxim on which I act should be a universal law. In this context the ·guiding· principle of the will is conformity to law as such, not bringing in any particular law governing some class of actions; and it must serve as the will’s principle if duty is not to be a vain delusion and chimerical concept. Common sense in its practical judgments is in perfect agreement with this, and constantly has this principle in view.

Consider the question: May I when in difficulties make a promise that I intend not to keep? The question obviously has two meanings: is it •prudent to make a false promise? does it conform to •duty to make a false promise? No doubt it often is •prudent, ·but not as often as you might think·. Obviously the false promise isn’t made prudent by its merely extricating me from my present difficulties; I have to think about whether it will in the long run cause more trouble than it saves in the present. Even with all my supposed cunning, the consequences can’t be so easily foreseen. People’s loss of trust in me might be far more disadvantageous than the trouble I am now trying to avoid, and it is hard to tell whether it mightn’t be more prudent to act according to a universal maxim not ever to make a promise that I don’t intend to keep. But I quickly come to see that such a maxim is based only on fear of consequences. Being truthful from •duty is an entirely different thing from being truthful out of •fear of bad consequences; for in •the former case a law is included in the concept of the action itself (·so that the right answer to ‘What are you doing?’ will include a mention of that law·); whereas in •the latter I must first look outward to see what results my action may have. [In the preceding sentence, Kant speaks of a ‘law for me’ and of results ‘for me’.] To deviate from the principle of duty is certainly bad; whereas to be unfaithful to my maxim

^1 It might be objected that I tried to take refuge in an obscure feeling behind the word ‘respect’, instead of clearing things up through a concept of reason. Although respect is indeed a feeling, it doesn’t come from outer influence; rather, it is a •feeling that a rational concept creates unaided; so it is different in kind from all the •feelings caused from outside, the ones that can come from desire or fear. When I directly recognize something as a law for myself I recognize it with respect, which merely means that I am conscious of submitting my will to a law without interference from any other influences on my mind. The will’s being directly settled by law, and the consciousness of this happening, is called ‘respect’; so respect should be seen as an effect of the law’s operation on the person’s will, not as a cause of it. Really, respect is the thought of a value that breaks down my self-love. Thus it is not something to be either desired or feared, though it has something analogous to both ·desire and fear·. The only thing that can be respected is law, and it has to be the law that we •impose on ourselves yet •recognize as necessary in itself.

•As a law it makes us subject to it, without consulting our self-love; which gives it some analogy to fear.

•As imposed on us by ourselves, it is a consequence of our will; which gives it some analogy to preference.

·This is really the only basic sense of the term ‘respect’·. Any •respect for a person is only •respect for the law (of righteousness, etc.) of which the person provides an example. Our respect for a person’s talents, for instance, is our recognition that we ought to practice until we are as talented as he is; we see him as a kind of example of a •law, because we regard it as our •duty to improve our talents. ·So respect for persons is a disguised form of respect for law·. All moral concern (as it is called) consists solely in respect for the law.

11

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 1

of prudence may be very advantageous to me, though it is certainly safer to abide by it. How can I know whether a deceitful promise is consistent with duty? The shortest way to go about finding out is also the surest. It is to ask myself:

•Would I be content for my maxim (of getting out of a difficulty through a false promise) to hold as a universal law, for myself as well as for others?

·That is tantamount to asking·:

•Could I say to myself that anyone may make a false promise when he is in a difficulty that he can’t get out of in any other way?

Immediately I realize that I could will •the lie but not •a universal law to lie; for such a law would result in there being no promises at all, because it would be futile to offer stories about my future conduct to people who wouldn’t believe me; or if they carelessly did believe me and were taken in ·by my promise·, would pay me back in my own coin. Thus my maxim would necessarily destroy itself as soon as it was made a universal law.

So I don’t need to be a very penetrating thinker to bring it about that my will is morally good. Inexperienced in how the world goes, unable to prepare for all its contingencies, I need only to ask myself: Can you will that your maxim become a universal law? If not, it must be rejected, not because of any harm it might bring to anyone, but because there couldn’t be a system of •universal legislation that included it as one of its principles, and •that is the kind of legislation that reason forces me to respect. I don’t yet see what it is based on (a question that a philosopher may investigate), but I at least understand these two:

•It is something whose value far outweighs all the value of everything aimed at by desire,

•My duty consists in my having to act from pure respect for the practical law.

Every other motive must yield to duty, because it is the condition of a •will that is good in itself, and the value of •that surpasses everything.

And so in the common-sense understanding of morality we have worked our way through to its principle. Admittedly, common sense doesn’t have the abstract thought of this principle as something universal, but it always has the principle in view and uses it as the standard for its judgments.

It would be easy to show how common sense, with this compass in its hand, knows very well how to distinguish •good from •bad, •consistent with duty from •inconsistent with duty. To do this it doesn’t have to be taught anything new; it merely needs (Socrates-fashion) to have its attention drawn to the principle that it already has; and thus ·we can see· that neither science nor philosophy is needed in order to know what one must do to be honest and good, and even to be wise and virtuous. That’s something we might well have assumed in advance: that the knowledge of what every person is obliged to do (and thus also what everyone is obliged to know) is everyone’s business, even the most common person’s. We can’t help admiring the way common sense’s ability to make •practical judgment outstrips its ability to make •theoretical ones. In •theoretical judgments, if common sense ventures to go beyond the laws of experience and perceptions of the senses, it falls into sheer inconceivabilities and self-contradictions, or at least into a chaos of uncertainty, obscurity, and instability. On the other hand, it is just when common sense excludes ·everything empirical—that is·, all action-drivers that bring in the senses—that its ability to make •practical judgments first shows itself to advantage. It may then start splitting hairs, quibbling with its own conscience or with other claims concerning what should be called right, or wanting to satisfy itself about the exact worth of certain actions; and the great

12

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 1

thing about these activities of common sense is that in them it has as good a chance of getting it right as any philosopher has—perhaps even a better chance, because the philosopher doesn’t have any principle that common sense lacks and his judgment is easily confused by a mass of irrelevant considerations so that it easily goes astray. ·Here are two ways in which we could inter-relate common-sense morality and philosophy·: (1) We could go along with common-sense moral judgments, and bring in philosophy—if at all—only so as to make the system of morals more complete and comprehensible and its rules more convenient for use, especially in disputation. (2) We could steer common sense away from its fortunate simplicity in practical matters, and lead it through philosophy into a new path of inquiry and instruction. From what I have said, isn’t it clear that (1) is the wiser option to take?

Innocence is indeed a glorious thing, but it is very sad that it doesn’t take care of itself, and is easily led astray. For this reason, even wisdom—which consists in •doing and allowing more than in •knowing—needs science [Wissenschaft], not as something to learn from but as something that will ensure that wisdom’s precepts get into the mind and stay there. [‘Knowing’ translates Wissen, which is half the word translated as ‘science’, an overlap that Kant surely intended. The ‘science’ in question here is presumably metaphysics.] ·Without that help, they are not likely to ‘stay there’, and here is why·. Against all commands of duty that a man’s reason presents to him as deserving of so much respect, he feels in himself a powerful •counter-weight—namely, his needs and preferences, the complete satisfaction of which he lumps together as ‘happiness’. Reason issues inexorable commands without promising the preferences anything ·by way of recompense·. It ignores and has no respect for the claims ·that desire makes·—claims that are so impetuous and yet so plausible, and which refuse to give way to any command. This gives rise to a natural dialectic—·an intellectual conflict or contradiction·—in the form of a propensity to argue against the stern laws of duty and their validity, or at least to cast doubt on their purity and strictness, and, where possible, to make them more accordant with our wishes and desires. This undermines the very foundations of duty’s laws and destroys their dignity—which is something that even ordinary practical reason can’t, when it gets right down to it, call good.

In this way common sense is driven to go outside its own territory and to take a step into the field of practical philosophy. It doesn’t do this because of any speculative (= ‘theory-building’) need, which is something that never occurs to it so long as it is satisfied to remain merely healthy reason. [Kant’s phrase translated here as ‘common sense’ is gemeine Menschvernunft, which contains Vernunft = ‘reason’. Putting its bits together it could be taken to mean ‘general human reason’, but ‘common sense’ is about right.] Rather, it is driven to philosophy in order to become •informed and clearly •directed regarding the source of its principle and how exactly it differs from the maxims based on needs and preferences. It does this so as to escape from the embarrassment of opposing claims, and to avoid risking the loss of all genuine moral principles through the ambiguity in which common sense is easily involved—·the ambiguity between the moral and prudential readings of questions about what one ought to do·. Thus when common-sense moral thought develops itself, a dialectic surreptitiously occurs that forces it to look to philosophy for help, and the very same thing happens in common-sense theoretical thinking. It is true of each kind of ordinary or common-sense thought: each can come to rest only in a complete critical examination of our reason.

13

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 2

Chapter 2:

Moving from popular moral philosophy to the metaphysic of morals

Although I have derived our existing concept of duty from the ordinary ·commonsensical· use of our practical reason, that doesn’t at all imply that I have treated it as an empirical concept. On the contrary, if we attend to our experience of men’s doings, we meet frequent and—I admit—justified complaints that we can’t cite a single sure example of someone’s being disposed to act from pure duty—not one!—so that although much is done that accords with what duty commands, it always remains doubtful whether it is done from duty and thus whether it has moral worth. That is why there have always been philosophers who absolutely denied the reality of this ·dutiful· disposition in human actions, attributing everything ·that people do· to more or less refined self-interest. This hasn’t led them to question the credentials of the concept of morality. Rather, they ·have left that standing, and· have spoken with sincere regret of the frailty and corruption of human nature, which •is high-minded enough to accept the idea ·of duty·—an idea so worthy of respect—as a source of commands, •is too weak to follow this idea ·by obeying the commands·, and •employs reason, which ought to be its source of laws, only to cater to the interests that its preferences create—either singly or, at best, in their greatest possible harmony with one another.

It is indeed absolutely impossible by means of experience to identify with complete certainty a single case in which the maxim of an action—however much it might conform to duty—rested solely on moral grounds and on the person’s thought of his duty. It sometimes happens that we make a considerable sacrifice in performing some good action, and can’t find within ourselves, search as we may, anything that could have the power to motivate this except the moral ground of duty. But this shouldn’t make us confident that the true determining cause of the will was actually our •sense of duty rather than a secret impulse of •self-love masquerading as the idea of duty. For we like to give ourselves credit for having a more high-minded motive than we actually have; and even the strictest examination can never lead us entirely behind the secret action-drivers—·or, rather, behind the •pretended action-driver to where the •real one secretly lurks·—because when moral worth is in question it is not a matter of visible actions but of their invisible inner sources.

·The claim that the concept of duty is an empirical one is not only false but dangerous·. Consider the people who ridicule all morality as a mere phantom of human imagination overreaching itself through self-conceit: one couldn’t give them anything they would like better than the concession that the concepts of duty have to come wholly from experience (for their laziness makes them apt to believe that the same is true of all other concepts too). This concession would give them a sure triumph. I am willing to admit—out of sheer generosity!—that most of our actions are in accord with duty; but if we look more closely at our thoughts and aspirations we keep encountering •the beloved self as what our plans rely on, rather than •the stern command of duty with its frequent calls for self -denial. One needn’t be an enemy of virtue, merely a cool observer who can distinguish •even the most intense wish for the good from •actual good, to wonder sometimes whether true virtue is to be met with anywhere in the world; especially as one gets older and one’s

14

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 2

power of judgment is made wiser by experience and more acute in observation. [Kant was 60 years old when he wrote this work.] What, then, can stop us from completely abandoning our ideas of duty, and preserve in us a well-founded respect for its law? Only the conviction that

•Even if there never were any actions springing from such pure sources, that’s not the topic. Our concern is not •with whether this or that was done, but •with reason’s commanding—on its own initiative and independently of all appearances—what ought to be done.

So our concern is •with ·a kind of· actions of which perhaps the world has never had an example; if you go purely by experience you might well wonder whether there could be such actions; and yet they are sternly commanded by reason. Take the example of pure sincerity in friendship: this can be demanded of every man as a duty; the demand comes independently of all experience from the idea of reason that acts on the will on a priori grounds; so it isn’t weakened in the slightest by the fact—if it is a fact—that there has never actually been a sincere friend.

When this is added:

•If we don’t want to deny all truth to the concept of morality and to give up applying it to any possible object, we have to admit that morality’s law applies so widely that it holds •not merely for men but for all rational beings as such, •not merely under certain contingent conditions and with exceptions but with absolute necessity ·and therefore unconditionally and without exceptions·,

—when this becomes clear to us, we see that no experience can point us towards even the possibility of such apodictic laws. [This word, like the German apodiktisch, comes from Greek meaning, roughly, ‘clearly demonstrated’. Kant uses it to mean something like ‘utterly unbreakable, unconditional, permitting no excuses or exceptions’.] For what could entitle us to accord unlimited respect to something that perhaps is valid only under contingent human conditions? And how could laws for •our will be held to be laws for •the will of any rational being (and valid for us only because we are such beings), if they were merely empirical and didn’t arise a priori from pure though practical reason?

One couldn’t do worse by morality than drawing it from examples. We can’t get our concept of morality initially from examples, for we can’t judge whether something is fit to be an example or model of morality unless it has already been judged according principles of morality. ·This applies even to •the model that is most frequently appealed to·. Even •Jesus Christ must be compared with our ideal of moral perfection before he is recognized as being perfect; indeed, he says of himself ‘Why callest thou me (whom you see) good? There is none good (the archetype ·or model· of good) but one, i.e. God (whom you don’t see)’ [Matthew 19:17; the bits added in parentheses are Kant’s]. But ·don’t think that with God the father we have at last found the example or model from which we can derive our concept of morality·. Where do we get the concept of God as the highest good from? Solely from the idea of moral perfection that reason lays out for us a priori and which it ties, unbreakably, to the concept of a free will. ·Some have said that the moral life consists in ‘imitating Christ’, but· imitation has no place in moral matters; and the only use of examples there is •for encouragement—i.e. showing beyond question that what the law commands can be done—and •for making visible ·in particular cases· what the practical rule expresses more generally. But they can never entitle us to steer purely by examples, setting aside their true model which lies in reason.

15

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 2

Well, then, there are moral concepts that are established a priori, along with the principles of morality. Would it be a good idea to set these out in abstract form? Given that

•there is no genuine supreme principle of morality that doesn’t rest on pure reason alone independently of all possible experience,

·and thus given that

•the a priori concepts and principles I have mentioned are the whole foundation for morality·,

I don’t think there should be any question about whether they should be presented abstractly. At any rate, there should be no question about that if we want our knowledge of them to be distinguished from ordinary knowledge and to merit the label ‘philosophical’. But these days the question may arise after all. For if we conducted a poll on the question:

Which would you prefer—•pure rational knowledge of morality, separated from all experience and bringing with it a metaphysic of morals, or •popular practical philosophy?

it is easy to guess on which side the majority would stand!

Catering to the notions of the man in the street is all very well after we have made a fully satisfactory job of ascending to the principles of pure reason—first providing a metaphysical basis for the doctrine of morals and then getting it listened to by popularizing it. But it’s utterly absurd to aim at popularity [here = ‘being accessible by the common man’] at the outset, where everything depends on the correctness of the fundamental principles. There is a real virtue—a rare one!—in genuine popularization of philosophy; but the procedure I have been describing, ·in which popularity is sought at the outset·, involves no such virtue. It is not hard to be generally comprehensible if one does it by dropping all basic insight and replacing it with a disgusting jumble of patched-up observations and half-reasoned principles. Shallow-minded people lap this up, for it is very useful in coffee-house chatter, while people with better sense feel confused and dissatisfied, and helplessly turn away. Philosophers who see right through this hocus-pocus call people away from sham ‘popularity’ and towards the genuine popularity that can be achieved on the basis of hard-won insights; but they don’t get much of a hearing.

When we look at essays on morality written in this beloved style, what do we find? Sometimes •human nature in particular is mentioned (occasionally with the idea of a rational nature in general); now •perfection shows up, and now •happiness; •moral feeling here, •fear of God there; a •little of this and a •little of that—all in a marvellous mixture. It never occurs to the authors to ask: Can the principles of morality be found in knowledge of human nature (knowledge that we can get only from experience)? If they can’t—if the principles are a priori, free from everything empirical, and to be found in pure rational concepts with not a trace of them anywhere else—shouldn’t we tackle the investigation of them as a separate inquiry, as pure practical philosophy or (to use the dread word) as a metaphysic of morals,^2 dealing with it on its own so as to bring it to completion and make the popularity-demanding public wait until we have finished?

·The answer to that last question is ‘Yes, we should’, because· a completely self-contained metaphysic of morals, with no admixture of anthropology or theology or physics or....occult qualities...., is not only an essential basis for all theoretically sound and definite •knowledge of duties,

^2 We can if we wish divide the philosophy of morals into ‘pure’ (metaphysics) and ‘applied’ (meaning ‘applied to human nature’), like the divisions of mathematics and logic into pure and applied. This terminology immediately reminds us that moral principles are not based on what is special in human nature but must stand on their own feet a priori, and that they must yield practical rules for every rational nature, and accordingly for man.

16

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 2

but also a tremendously important help towards actually •carrying out its precepts. For the pure thought of duty and of the moral law generally, unmixed with empirical inducements, has a •stronger influence on the human heart purely through reason—this being what first shows reason that it can be practical—than all other action-drivers that may be derived from the empirical field; so much •stronger that reason, aware of its dignity, despises the empirical inputs and comes to dominate them. In contrast with this, a mixed theory of morals—assembled from action-drivers involving feelings and preferences and from rational concepts—is bound to make the mind vacillate between motives that •can’t be brought together under any principle and that •can lead to the good only by great good luck and will frequently lead to the bad.^3

What I have said makes ·five things· clear: that •all moral concepts have their origin entirely a priori in reason, and this holds as much for the most ordinary common-sense moral concepts as for ·the ones used in· high-level theorizing; that •moral concepts can’t be formed by abstraction from any empirical knowledge or, therefore, from anything contingent; that •this purity ·or non-empiricalness· of origin is what gives them the dignity of serving as supreme practical principles; that •any addition of something empirical takes away just that much of their influence and of the unqualified worth of actions ·performed in accordance with them·; and that •not only is it necessary in developing a moral theory but also important in our practical lives that we derive the concepts and laws of morals from pure reason and present them pure and unmixed, determining the scope of this entire practical but pure rational knowledge (the entire faculty of pure practical reason). [What follows is meant to flow on from that fifth point; Kant wrote this paragraph as one sentence.] This ·determination of scope· is to be done not on the basis of principles of human reason that non-moral philosophy might allow or require, but rather (because moral laws are to hold for every rational being just because it is rational) by being derived from the universal concept of rational being. To apply morals to men one needs anthropology; but first morals must be completely developed as pure philosophy, i.e. metaphysics, independently of anthropology; this is easy to do, given how separate the two are from one another. For we know—·and here I repeat the fifth of the points with which I opened this paragraph·—that if we don’t have such a metaphysic, it is not merely •pointless to ·try to· settle accurately, as a matter of theory, what moral content there is in this or that action that is in accord with duty, but •impossible to base morals on legitimate principles even for ordinary practical use, especially in moral instruction; and that’s what is needed for pure moral dispositions to be produced and worked into men’s characters for the purpose of the highest good in the world.

^3 I have been asked....why teachings about virtue containing so much that is convincing to reason nevertheless achieve so little.... The answer is just this: the teachers themselves haven’t brought their concepts right out into the clear; and when they wish to make up for this by hunting all over the place for motives for being morally good so as to make their medicine have the right strength, they spoil it. Entertain the thought of

an act of honesty performed with a steadfast soul, with no view towards any advantage in this world or the next, under the greatest temptations of need or allurement.

You don’t have to look very hard to see that conduct like this far surpasses and eclipses any similar action that was affected—even if only slightly—by any external action-driver. It elevates the soul and makes one want to be able to act in this way. Even youngish children feel this, and one should never represent duties to them in any other way.

17

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 2

In this study I have already moved

•from common moral judgment to philosophical moral judgment,

and am now advancing by natural stages ·within the realm of philosophical moral judgment, specifically·:

•from popular philosophy to metaphysics.

Popular philosophy goes only as far as it can grope its way by means of examples; metaphysics is not held back by anything empirical, and, because it has to stake out the whole essence of rational knowledge of this kind, it will if necessary stretch out as far as ideas ·of reason·, of which there can’t be any examples. In making this advance we must track and clearly present the practical faculty of reason, right from •the universal rules that set it up through to •the point where the concept of duty arises from it.

Everything in nature works according to laws. Only a rational being has a will—which is the ability to act according to the thought of laws, i.e. to act on principle. To derive actions from laws you need reason, so that’s what will is—practical reason. When •reason is irresistible in its influence on the will, the actions that a rational being recognizes as objectively necessary are also subjectively necessary; i.e. the will is an ability to choose only what reason recognizes, independently of preferences, as practically necessary, i.e. as good. But when •unaided reason isn’t enough to settle the will, the will comes under the influence of subjective conditions (certain action-drivers) that don’t always agree with the objective conditions—in short, the will is not in complete accord with reason. In this case (which is the actual case with men) the actions that are recognized as •objectively necessary are •subjectively contingent, and if such a will is determined according to objective laws that is because it is constrained....i.e. is following principles of reason to which it isn’t by its nature necessarily obedient.

When the thought of an objective principle constrains a will, it is called a ‘command’ (of reason), and its verbal expression is called an ‘imperative’.

All imperatives are expressed with an ‘ought’, which indicates how an objective law of reason relates to a will that it constrains. An imperative says that it would be good to do or to refrain from doing something, but it addresses this to a will that doesn’t always do x just because x is represented to it as good to do. Practical good is what determines the will by means of the thoughts that reason produces—and thus not by subjective causes but objectively, on grounds that are valid for every rational being just because it is rational. This contrasts with the thought that it would be nice to act in a certain way; the latter influences the will only by means of a feeling that has purely subjective causes, which hold for the senses of this or that person but not as a principle of reason that holds for everyone.^4

^4 When the faculty of desire is affected by feelings, we speak of what the person •prefers, which always also indicates a •need. When a contingently determinable will is affected by principles of reason, we say that it has an •interest. Interests are to be found only in a dependent will, one that isn’t of itself always in accord with reason; we can’t make sense of the idea of God’s will’s having interests. But even the human will can have an interest without acting on it. The interest that one merely has is a practical interest in the •action; the interest on which one acts is a pathological interest in the •upshot of the action. [See the note on ‘pathological’ on page 9.] Whereas the former indicates only the effect on the will of principles of reason •in themselves, the latter indicates the effect on it of the principles of reason •in the service of the person’s preferences, since ·in these cases· all reason does is to provide the practical rule through which the person’s preferences are to be satisfied. In the former case, my focus is on the action; in the latter, it is on whatever is pleasant in the result of the action. We saw in chapter 1 that when an action is done from duty, attention should be paid not to any interest in its upshot but only to the action itself and the law which is its principle in reason.

18

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 2

Objective laws of the good would apply to a perfectly good will just as much to as to any other; but we shouldn’t think of them as constraining such a will, because it is so constituted that it can’t be determined to act by anything except the thought of the good. Thus no imperatives hold for God’s will or for any holy will. The ‘ought’ is out of place here, for the volition is of itself necessarily at one with the law. Thus, what imperatives do is just to express the relation of •objective laws of volition •in general to the •subjective imperfection of the will of this or that •particular rational being—the will of any human, for example.

All imperatives command either •hypothetically or categorically. The •former expresses the practical necessity of some possible action as a means to achieving something else that one does or might want. An imperative would be categorical if it represented an action as being objectively necessary in itself without regard to any other end.

Since every practical law represents some possible action as •good, and thus as •necessary for anyone whose conduct is governed by reason, what every imperative does is to specify some action that is

•necessary according to the principle of a will that has something good about it.

If the action would be good only as a means to something else, the imperative is hypothetical; but if the action is thought of as good in itself and hence as

•necessary in a will that conforms to reason, which it has as its principle,

the imperative is categorical.

The imperative thus says of some action I could perform that it would be good, and puts the practical rule into a relationship with my will; ·and it is no less an imperative if· I don’t immediately perform the ·commanded· action simply because it is good (I don’t know that it is good, or I do know this but ·I don’t care, because· my conduct is guided by other maxims that are opposed to the objective principles of practical reason).

A hypothetical imperative merely says that the action is good for some purpose that one could have or that one actually does have. In the •former case it is a problematic practical principle, in the •latter it is an assertoric one. The categorical imperative, which declares the action to be objectively necessary without referring to any end in view....holds as an apodictic practical principle.

Anything that could come about through the powers of some rational being could be an end ·or goal or purpose· for some will or other. So ·there are countless possible ends, and therefore· countless hypothetical imperatives, i.e. principles of action thought of as necessary to attain a possible end in view. Every science has a practical segment in which

•some purpose is set forth as a problem, and

•imperatives are offered saying how that purpose can be achieved.

So we can give these imperatives the general label ‘imperatives of skill’. The practical part of a science is concerned only with •what must be done to achieve a certain purpose; it doesn’t address the question of •whether the purpose is reasonable and good. The instructions to a physician for how to make his patient thoroughly healthy, and to a poisoner for how to bring certain death to his victim, are of equal value in that each serves perfectly to achieve the intended purpose. Since in early youth we don’t know what purposes we may come to have in the course of our life, parents •try above all to enable their children to learn many kinds of things, and •provide for skill in the use of means to any chosen end. For any given end, the parents can’t tell whether it will actually come to be a purpose that their child actually has, but ·they have to allow that· some day it may do so. They are

19

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 2

so focused on this that they commonly neglect to form and correct their children’s judgment about the worthwhileness of the things that they may make their ends.

But there is one end that can be supposed as actual in all rational beings to which imperatives apply, i.e. all rational beings that are dependent [see footnote 4 above]; and thus one purpose that they not only can have but that we can assume they all do have as a matter of natural necessity. This purpose is happiness. The hypothetical imperative that declares some action to be practically necessary for the promotion of happiness is an assertoric imperative. We should describe it not as

•necessary to a problematic purpose, one that is merely possible,

but as

•necessary to a purpose that we can a priori and with assurance assume for each person, because it belongs to his essence.

Skill in the choice of means to one’s own greatest welfare can be called ‘prudence’ in the narrowest sense.^5 Thus the imperative that refers to the choice of means to one’s own happiness (i.e. the precept of prudence) is still only hypothetical; it commands the action not outright but only as a means to another end.

·After those two kinds of hypothetical imperative· we come at last to one imperative that commands certain conduct •immediately, and not •through the condition that some purpose can be achieved through it. This imperative is categorical. It isn’t concerned with what is to result from the conduct, or even with what will happen in the conduct (its •matter), but only with the •form and the principle from which the conduct follows. What is essentially good in the conduct consists in the frame of mind—·the willingness to obey the imperative·—no matter what the upshot is. This may be called ‘the imperative of morality’.

Volition according to these three principles is plainly distinguished by the dissimilarity in the pressure they put on the will. As an aid to getting this dissimilarity clear, I believe we shall do well to call them, respectively,

rules of skill,

advice of prudence,

commands (laws) of morality.

For it is only law that carries with it the concept of a necessity (·‘This action must be performed’·) that is unconditional and objective and hence universally valid; and commands are laws that must be obeyed even when one would prefer not to. Advice also involves necessity, but it’s a necessity that can hold only under a subjectively contingent condition (i.e. whether this or that man counts this or that as part of his happiness). Whereas the categorical imperative isn’t restricted by ·or made dependent on· any condition. As absolutely (though practically) necessary, it can be called a ‘command’ in the strict sense. We could also call the first imperatives ‘technical’ (relevant to arts and skills), the second ‘pragmatic’ (relevant to well-being), and the third ‘moral’ (relevant to any free conduct whatsoever, i.e. to morals).^6

^5 The word ‘prudence’ may be taken in two senses, that of (1) ‘worldly prudence’ and that of 2 ‘private prudence’. (1) refers to a man’s skill in influencing others so as to get them serve his purposes. (2) is the insight to bring all these purposes together to his own long-term advantage. Any value that (1) has ultimately comes from (2); and of someone who is ‘prudent’ in sense (1) but not in sense (2) we might better say that he is over-all not prudent but only clever and cunning.
^6 This seems to me to be the right meaning for the word ‘pragmatic’. For constraints are called ‘pragmatic’ when they don’t strictly flow from the law of states as necessary statutes but rather from provision for the general welfare. A history is composed ‘pragmatically’ when it teaches prudence—i.e. instructs the world how it could look after its advantage better (or not worse) than it has in the past.

20

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 2

The question now arises:

•How are all these imperatives possible?

This question doesn’t ask, for any kind of imperative,

•How can the action that the imperative commands be performed?

Rather, it asks,

•How are we to understand the constraint that the imperative puts upon the will in setting it its task?

·We shall see that there is not much of a problem about this for the first of the three kinds of imperative, and the same is true—though with slight complications—of the second·.

(1) How an imperative of skill is possible requires no particular discussion. If someone wills an end, and if reason has decisive influence on his actions, then he also wills any steps he can take that are indispensably necessary for achieving that end. What this proposition implies about the will is analytic, and here is why:

When I will x as to-be-brought-about-by-me, I already have—·as a part of that act of will·—the thought of the means to x, i.e. the thought of my causality in the production of x. And the imperative extracts from the concept of willing x the concept of actions necessary for the achievement of x.

(Of course, truths about what means are necessary for achieving x are synthetic propositions; but those are only about how to achieve x and not about the act of the will.) ·Here’s an example of this interplay between analytic and synthetic propositions·. Mathematics teaches that

•to bisect a line according to an infallible principle, I must make two intersecting arcs from each of its extremities;

and this is certainly a synthetic proposition. But if I know that that’s the only sure way to bisect the line, the proposition

•if I fully will the effect, I must also will the action necessary to produce it

is analytic. For •conceiving of something as an effect that I can somehow bring about is just the same as •conceiving of myself as acting in this way.

(2) If only it were as easy to give a definite concept of happiness, the imperatives of prudence would perfectly correspond to those of skill and would likewise be analytic. For then we could say that, with prudence as with skill, whoever wills the end wills also (necessarily according to reason) the only means to it that are in his power. Unfortunately, however, the concept of happiness is so indefinite that, although each person wishes to attain it, he can never give a definite and self-consistent account of what it is that he wishes and wills ·under the heading of ‘wanting happiness’·. The reason for this is that

all the •elements of the concept of happiness are empirical (i.e. must be drawn from experience),

whereas

the •·completed· idea of happiness requires ·the thought of· an absolute whole—the thought of a maximum of well-being in my present and in every future condition.

Now it is impossible for a finite being—even one who is extremely clear-sighted and capable—to form a definite ·and detailed· concept of what he really wants here ·on this earth·. ·Consider some of the things people say they aim for·! •Wealth: but in willing to be wealthy a person may bring down on himself much anxiety, envy, and intrigues. •Great knowledge and insight: but that may merely sharpen his eye for the dreadfulness of evils that he can’t avoid though he doesn’t now see them; or it may show him needs ·that he doesn’t know he has, and· that add to the burden his desires already place on him. •Long life: but who can guarantee

21

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 2

him that it wouldn’t be a long misery? •Health: but often enough ill-health has kept him from dissolute excesses that he would have gone in for if he had been perfectly healthy! In short, he can’t come up with any principle that could with complete certainty lay down what would make him truly happy; for that he would need to be omniscient. So in his pursuit of happiness he can’t be guided by detailed principles but only by bits of empirical advice (e.g. concerning diet, frugality, courtesy, restraint, etc.) which experience shows to be usually conducive to well-being. It follows from this •that imperatives of prudence can’t strictly speaking command (i.e. present actions objectively as practically necessary); •that they should be understood as advice rather than as commands of reason; •that the problem:

Settle, for sure and universally, what conduct will promote the happiness of a rational being

is completely unsolvable. There couldn’t be an imperative that in the strict sense commanded us to do what makes for happiness, because happiness is an ideal not of reason but of imagination, depending only on empirical grounds. ·This means that whether a person will achieve happiness depends on countlessly many particular facts about his future states·; and there is absolutely no chance of picking out the actions that will produce the right infinite totality of consequences that will constitute happiness. If the means to happiness could be stated with certainty, this imperative of prudence would be an analytic practical proposition, for it would then differ from the imperative of skill only in ·the way described in paragraph (1) above, namely·: the imperative of skill is addressed merely to a purpose that a person may have, while the purpose of the imperative of prudence—·namely happiness·—is given for every person. That leaves them the same in this respect: each commands the means to something that the person is assumed to have as a willed purpose, so each commands the willing of the means to someone who wills the end; and so each is analytic. So there is no difficulty about how such an imperative is possible. [Both here, and at the start (2) of the discussion of imperatives of prudence, Kant makes it pretty clear that such imperatives are not actually analytic because of the indeterminateness about what happiness amounts to, though they would be analytic otherwise. He evidently thinks that if there is only this barrier to their being analytic, their status as nearly analytic (so to speak) makes them unproblematic.]

(3) On the other hand, the question of how the imperative of morality is possible does call for an answer, for this imperative is not hypothetical, and so what it presents as objectively necessary can’t be based on any presupposed purpose as in the case of hypothetical imperatives. But don’t lose sight of the fact that it can’t be shown empirically—can’t be shown by producing an example—that there are any imperatives of morality; perhaps every imperative that seems to be categorical is tacitly hypothetical. For example,

Someone says ‘You oughtn’t to promise anything deceitfully’ and we ·take this to be categorical; we· assume •that an action of this kind must be regarded as in itself bad and thus that the imperative prohibiting it is categorical. (The alternative is to think •that the necessity involved in this prohibition is mere advice about how to avoid something else that is bad, along the lines of ‘You oughtn’t to promise falsely, in case people find out about it and your credit rating is wrecked’.)

But we can’t point with certainty to any example in which the will is directed by the law alone without any other action-drivers, ·i.e. in which the will obeys a categorical imperative·. In a given case this may appear to be so, but it’s always possible that a fear of disgrace and perhaps also a dim sense of other dangers may have had a secret influence

22

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 2

on the will. ·We can’t rule this out on empirical grounds·: who can prove by experience that something doesn’t have a cause ·of a certain sort· when experience can only show us that we don’t perceive such a cause? In such a case—·i.e. when other incentives are secretly affecting the will·—the so-called ‘moral imperative’, which appears to be categorical and unconditional, is in fact only a pragmatic injunction that calls on us to attend to our own advantage.

With each of the other two kinds of imperative, experience shows us that imperatives of the kind in question do exist, and the inquiry into their possibility is the search only for •an explanation of them, not for •evidence that they exist. It is not so with categorical imperatives. Our investigation of their possibility will have to proceed purely a priori—starting with no empirical presuppositions, and in particular without the advantage of the premise that such imperatives actually exist. ·That they do exist is one of the things we may hope to establish through our inquiry into their possibility·. (In the meantime—·though this is an aside·—this much at least may be seen: the categorical imperative is the only one that can be taken as a practical law, while all other imperatives may be called principles of the will [here = ‘movers of the will’] but not laws. This is because what is merely necessary-for-attaining-some-chosen-end can be regarded as itself contingent, ·as can be seen from the fact that· when we give up the end in question we get rid of the instruction stated in the imperative. In contrast with this, an unconditional command leaves the will no freedom to choose the opposite, so that it (and only it) involves the necessity that we require of a law.)

·I have spoken of one thing we are up against when trying to show the possibility of categorical imperatives, namely that we must do this a priori, without being able to appeal to any empirical evidence that such imperatives do actually exist·. Now for a second point about getting insight into the possibility of a categorical imperative or law of morality, namely: there’s a very solid reason why it will be hard to do this, because this imperative is an a priori synthetic •practical proposition.^7

·We know already that· it is hard to see that •theoretical propositions of this sort—·i.e. ones that are synthetic and known a priori·—are possible, so we must be prepared for at least as much difficulty when it comes to •practical ones.

In approaching this task, let us first ask:

Doesn’t the mere concept of a categorical imperative provide us with the form of words expressing the proposition—the only ·kind of· proposition—that can be a categorical imperative?

·Don’t think that answering Yes to this ends our task·. For even when we know •how the imperative sounds—·i.e. how it is worded·—the question of •how such an absolute command is possible will require difficult and special labours to answer; I shall get into these in the final chapter.

When I have the general thought of a hypothetical imperative, I can’t tell just from this thought what such an imperative will contain. To know that, I have to know what the condition is. But when I have the thought categorical

^7 ·When I affirm a categorical imperative·, I connect the action with the will a priori, and hence necessarily, without making this conditional on the person’s preferring to achieve this or that end. (Though I do this objectively, i.e. under the idea of a reason that has complete control over all its subjective motivators.) So this is a practical proposition that doesn’t analytically derive the willing of an action from some other volition already presupposed (for we don’t have the perfect will that would be needed for there always to be such a volition, ·namely a volition to obey the moral law·) Rather, the proposition connects the action directly with the concept of the will of a rational being as something that •isn’t contained in it ·so that the connection •isn’t analytic·.

23

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 2

imperative, I know right away what it will contain. For all the imperative contains is

the law,

and the necessity that the maxim conform to the law;

and the law doesn’t contain any condition limiting it (·comparable with the condition that is always part of a hypothetical imperative·). So there is nothing left for the maxim to conform to except the universality of a law as such, and what the imperative represents as necessary is just precisely that conformity of maxim to law.^8

So there is only one categorical imperative, and this is it: ·Act only on that maxim through which you can at the same time will that it should become a universal law·.

Now if all imperatives of duty can be derived from this one imperative as a principle, we’ll at least be able to show what we understand by the concept of duty, what the concept means, even if we haven’t yet settled whether so-called ‘duty’ is an empty concept or not.

The universality of law according to which effects occur constitutes what is properly called nature in the most general sense,....i.e. the existence of things considered as determined by universal laws. So the universal imperative of duty can be expressed as follows: Act as though the maxim of your action were to become, through your will, a universal law of nature.

I want now to list some duties, adopting the usual division of them into •duties to ourselves and •duties to others, and into •perfect duties and •imperfect duties.^9

(1) A man who has been brought by a series of troubles to the point of despair and of weariness with life still has his reason sufficiently to ask himself: ‘Wouldn’t it be contrary to my duty to myself to take my own life?’ Now he asks: ‘Could the maxim of my action ·in killing myself· become a universal law of nature?’ Well, here is his maxim:

For love of myself, I make it my principle to cut my life short when prolonging it threatens to bring more troubles than satisfactions.

So the question is whether this principle of self-love could become a universal law of nature. If it did, that would be a nature that had a law according to which a single feeling •created a life-affirming push and also •led to the destruction of life itself; and we can see at a glance that such a ‘nature’ would contradict itself, and so couldn’t be a nature. So the maxim we are discussing couldn’t be a law of nature, and therefore would be utterly in conflict with the supreme principle of duty.

(2) Another man sees himself being driven by need to borrow money. He realizes that no-one will lend to him unless he firmly promises to repay it at a certain time, and he is well aware that he wouldn’t be able to keep such a promise. He is disposed to make such a promise, but he has enough conscience to ask himself: ‘Isn’t it improper and opposed to duty to relieve one’s needs in that way?’ If he does decide to make the promise, the maxim of his action will run like this:

^8 A maxim is a subjective principle of acting, and must be distinguished from the objective principle, which is the practical law. The maxim contains the practical rule that reason comes up with in conformity with the state the person (the subject) is in, including his preferences, his ignorances, and so on; so it is the principle according to which the subject acts. The law, on the other hand, is the objective principle valid for every rational being, and the principle by which the subject ought to act; that is, it is an imperative.
^9 Please note that I reserve the ·serious, considered· division of duties for a future metaphysic of morals, and that the present division is merely one I chose as an aid to arranging my examples...

24

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 2

When I think I need money, I will borrow money and promise to repay it, although I know that the repayment won’t ever happen.

·Here he is—for the rest of this paragraph—reflecting on this·: ‘It may be that this principle of self-love or of personal advantage would fit nicely into my whole future welfare, ·so that there is no prudential case against it·. But the question remains: would it be right? ·To answer this·, I change the demand of self-love into a universal law, and then put the question like this: If my maxim became a universal law, then how would things stand? I can see straight off that it could never hold as a universal law of nature, and must contradict itself. For if you take a law saying that anyone who thinks he is in need can make any promises he likes without intending to keep them, and make it universal ·so that everyone in need does behave in this way·, that would make the promise and the intended purpose of it impossible—no-one would believe what was promised to him but would only laugh at any such performance as a vain pretence.’

(3) A third finds in himself a talent that could be developed so as to make him in many respects a useful person. But he finds himself in comfortable circumstances, and would rather indulge in pleasure than take the trouble to broaden and improve his fortunate natural gifts. But now he asks whether his maxim of neglecting his gifts, agreeing as it does with his liking for idle amusement, also agrees with what is called ‘duty’. He sees that a system of nature conforming with this law could indeed exist, with everyone behaving like the Islanders of the south Pacific, letting their talents rust and devoting their lives merely to idleness, indulgence, and baby-making—in short, to pleasure. But he can’t possibly will that this should become a universal law of nature or that it should be implanted in us by a natural instinct. For, as a rational being, he necessarily wills that all his abilities should be developed, because they serve him and are given to him for all sorts of possible purposes.

(4) A fourth man, for whom things are going well, sees that others (whom he could help) have to struggle with great hardships, and he thinks to himself:

What concern of mine is it? Let each one be as happy as heaven wills, or as he can make himself; I won’t take anything from him or even envy him; but I have no desire to contribute to his welfare or help him in time of need.

If such a way of thinking were a universal law of nature, the human race could certainly survive—and no doubt that state of humanity would be better than one where everyone chatters about sympathy and benevolence and exerts himself occasionally to practice them, while also taking every chance he can to cheat, and to betray or otherwise violate people’s rights. But although it is possible that that maxim should be a universal law of nature, it is impossible to will that it do so. For a will that brought that about would conflict with itself, since instances can often arise in which the person in question would need the love and sympathy of others, and he would have no hope of getting the help he desires, being robbed of it by this law of nature springing from his own will.

Those are a few of the many duties that we have (or at least think we have) that can clearly be derived from the single principle that I have stated on the preceding page. We must be able to will that a maxim of our action become a universal law; this is the general formula for the moral evaluation of our action. •Some actions are so constituted that their maxim can’t even be thought as a universal law of nature without contradiction, let alone being willed to be such. It’s easy to see that an action of that kind conflicts with stricter or narrower (absolutely obligatory) duty. •With

25

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 2

other actions, the maxim-made-universal-law is not in that way internally impossible (·self-contradictory·), but it is still something that no-one could possibly will to be a universal law of nature, because such a will would contradict itself. It’s easy to see that an action of that kind conflicts with broader (meritorious) duty. Thinking of duties in terms not of the object of their action but rather of the kind of obligation they involve, what I have given is a complete display of all the kinds of duty, in terms of their dependence on a single principle.

If we attend to what happens in us when we act against duty, we find that we don’t (because we can’t) actually will that our maxim should become a universal law. Rather, we are willing that the opposite of the maxim on which we are acting should remain as a law generally, but we take the liberty of catering to our preferences by making an exception—‘just for me, just this once!’. So if we weighed everything from a single standpoint, namely that of reason, we would find a contradiction in our own will: willing that a certain principle •be objectively necessary as a universal law and yet •subjectively not hold universally but rather admit of exceptions. However, ·we don’t consider our actions in this unitary way; rather·, we regard our action ·at one time· from the point of view of a will wholly conformable to reason and then ·at another time· from the point of view of a will affected by preferences; so there is actually no contradiction, but rather the preference’s resisting the command of reason. In this the •universality of the principle is changed into mere •generality—·i.e. the move is made from all to ever so many or almost all·—so that the practical principle of reason meets the maxim half-way. This procedure, whether or not it can be justified in our own impartial judgment, shows that we really do acknowledge the validity of the categorical imperative and allow ourselves (while keeping a wary eye on it) only a few exceptions—ones that strike us as unimportant and as forced on us.

I have thus at least shown that if duty is a concept that is to have significance and actual law-giving authority for our actions, it has to be expressed in categorical imperatives, never in hypothetical ones. And along with that I have made clear—and ready for any use—the content that the categorical imperative must have if it is to contain the principle of all duty (if there is such a thing as duty). This is a substantial result; but I haven’t yet reached the point where I can prove a priori that •this kind of imperative really exists, that •there is a practical law that of itself commands absolutely and without any action-drivers, and that •obedience to this law is duty.

If we want to reach that point, it is extremely important that we pay heed to this warning:

Don’t slip into thinking that the reality of this principle can be derived from the special constitution of human nature!

For duty has to be practical-and-unconditional necessity of action; so it has to hold for all rational beings (the only beings to which an imperative has anything to say), and is a law for all human wills only because they are rational beings. In contrast with that, anything that is derived from

•the temperament of human beings in particular, from

•certain feelings and propensities ·of human beings·,

or even from (if this is possible)

•a particular tendency of the human reason that might not hold for the will of every rational being,

—such a thing can yield a •maxim that is valid for us, but not a •law. That is, it can yield •a subjective principle on which we might act if our desires and dispositions take us that way, but not •an objective principle telling us how to act even if all our dispositions, preferences, and natural tendencies

26

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 2

were pulling us in the opposite direction. Indeed, the •fewer subjective causes there are for acting in a certain way and •the more there are against, the more clearly we can see the sublimity and intrinsic dignity of duty’s command to act in that way. The pulls in the other direction don’t weaken the constraint of the law or lessen its validity.

Here we see philosophy put into a precarious position, which has to be made firm even though there is nothing in heaven or on earth to hang it from or stand it on! Here philosophy has to show its purity as the •sustainer of its own laws, and not as the •herald of laws that are whispered to it by an implanted ‘sense’ or by who knows what guardian ‘nature’! ‘Laws’ of the latter kind may always be better than nothing, but they can’t yield fundamental principles. Such principles can only be dictated by reason: they must have an entirely a priori origin, getting none of their commanding authority from the preferences of mankind and all of it from the supremacy of the law and due respect for it. Otherwise—·that is, if human nature were the only basis for morality·—mankind would be condemned to self-contempt and inner disgust.

Thus if anything empirical were brought in as an ingredient in the principle of morality, it would not only •be utterly useless in this role but would also •do terrific harm to the purity of morality ·in practice·—for in morals the proper, priceless value of an absolutely good will consists precisely in action’s being driven by something that is free from all influences from contingent grounds that only experience can make available. We can’t too strongly or too often warn against this slack—indeed this low—cast of mind, that looks for its principles [here = ‘the sources of moral energy’] among empirical motives and laws. ·The warning is constantly and urgently needed·, because reason in its weariness is glad to rest on this pillow and dreamily....substitute for •morality a botched-up •bastard assembled from limbs of very different species—it looks like anything you want to see in it, but not like virtue to anyone who has ever beheld her in her true form.^10

So this is our question:

Is it a necessary law for all rational beings that they should always judge their actions by maxims that they themselves could will to hold good as universal laws?

If there is a such a law, it must already be connected—wholly a priori—with the concept of the will of a rational being. But in order to discover this connection, we must, however reluctantly, take a step into metaphysics; but it will be into the metaphysic of morals, not the region of metaphysics involved in •speculative philosophy. [The ‘speculative’/’practical’ contrast is explained on pages 3-4.] A •practical philosophy doesn’t commit itself to explanations of what happens but to laws about what ought to happen even if it never does—i.e. objective-practical laws. [Kant means that they are ‘objective’ at least in the sense that they are not ‘subjective’, i.e. don’t have anything to say about what the person, the subject, wants or hopes or prefers or fears or aims at. For another example of this contrast at work, see pages 7-8.] In practical philosophy, therefore, we needn’t inquire into

•why something pleases or displeases,

•how merely sensory pleasure differs from taste,

•whether taste is different from a general satisfaction of reason,

•what the feelings of pleasure and unpleasure depend on,

^10 To behold virtue in its proper form is simply to present morality with •nothing sensuous stirred into the mixture and •every spurious adornment of reward or self-love stripped off. Viewed in that way, it outshines everything that appears charming to the senses, as can easily be seen by anyone whose reason hasn’t been spoiled for all abstraction.

27

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 2

•how such feelings give rise to desires and inclinations.

•how desires and preferences, with the co-operation of reason, give rise to maxims.

All of that belongs ·not to practical philosophy but· to empirical psychology. (If we think of natural science as the philosophy of nature based on empirical laws, then empirical psychology is the second part of it, ·empirical physics being the first·.) In contrast with that, our present concern is with objectively-practical laws and thus with how a will relates to itself when it determines itself only by reason, and ·in that inquiry· every empirical consideration automatically falls away. Why? Because if unaided reason determines conduct, it must necessarily do so a priori, ·and thus without bringing in anything empirical·. Can reason determine conduct in this way? That is what we are now to investigate.

The will is thought of as someone’s capacity ·or ability· to control how he behaves in conformity with the representation of certain laws. [Slightly correcting what Kant wrote, which literally means: ‘The will is thought of as a capacity to control itself...’.] Such a capacity can be found only in rational beings. Now, what serves the will as the objective ground for its action upon itself is an end, and if it is given by reason alone it must be an end for all rational beings. On the other hand, what contains the ground of the possibility of the action that leads to the end is called the means. The subjective ground of desire is the action-driver, while the objective ground of volition is the motive. And so we have a distinction between

•subjective ends resting on action-drivers, and

•objective ends depending on motives that are valid for every rational being.

Practical principles are formal when they abstract from all subjective ends; they are material when they are based on subjective ends and thus on certain action-drivers. All of the ends—material ends—that a rational being voluntarily sets before himself as things to be achieved through his conduct are merely •relative, for their value comes solely from how they •relate to the particular way in which the subject’s faculty of desire is constituted; and from this we can’t get any practical laws, i.e. any universal and necessary principles that hold for all rational beings and for every act of the will. So the only imperatives that these relative ends support are hypothetical ones.

But suppose there were something whose existence in itself had absolute value, something which as an end in itself could support determinate laws. That would be a basis—indeed the only basis—for a possible categorical imperative, i.e. of a practical law.

·There is such a thing! It is a human being!· I maintain that man—and in general every rational being—exists as an end in himself and not merely as a means to be used by this or that will at its discretion. Whenever he acts in ways directed towards himself or towards other rational beings, ·a person serves as a means to whatever end his action aims at; but· he must always be regarded as also an end. Things that are preferred have only conditional value, for if the preferences (and the needs arising from them) didn’t exist, their object would be worthless. ·That wouldn’t count against the ‘objects’ in question if the desires on which they depend did themselves have unconditional value, but they don’t·! If the preferences themselves, as the sources of needs, did have absolute value, one would want to have them; but that is so far from the case that every rational being must wish he were altogether free of them. So the value of any objects to be obtained through our actions is always conditional. Beings whose existence depends not on our will but on nature, if they are not rational beings, have only relative value as means, and are therefore called ‘things’ [Sachen]; whereas rational beings are called ‘persons’, because their nature

28

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 2

already marks them out as ends in themselves (i.e. as not to be used merely as means)—which makes such a being •an object of respect, and •something that sets limits to what anyone can choose to do. Such beings are not merely subjective ends whose existence as a result of our action has value for us, but are objective ends, i.e. things [Dinge] whose existence is an end in itself. It is indeed an irreplaceable end: you can’t substitute for it something else to which it would be merely a means. If there were no such ends in themselves, nothing of absolute value could be found, and if all value were conditional and thus contingent, no supreme practical principle for reason could be found anywhere.

So if there is to be a supreme practical principle, and a categorical imperative for the human will, it must be an objective principle of the will that can serve as a universal law. Why must it? Because it has to be drawn from the conception of something that is an end in itself and therefore an end for everyone. The basis for this principle is: rational nature exists as an end in itself. Human beings necessarily think of their own existence in this way, which means that the principle holds as a subjective principle of human actions. But every other rational being also thinks of his existence on the same rational ground that holds also for myself;^11 and so it is at the same time an objective principle—·one that doesn’t depend on contingent facts about this or that subject·—a supreme practical ground from which it must be possible to derive all the laws of the will. So here is the practical imperative: Act in such a way as to treat humanity, whether in your own person or in that of anyone else, always as an end and never merely as a means. Let us now see whether this can be carried out.

To return to our previous examples: (1) Someone thinking of committing suicide will, if he is guided by the concept of necessary duty to oneself, ask himself

•Could my suicide be reconciled with the idea of humanity as an end in itself?

·And his answer to this should be No·. If he escapes from his burdensome situation by destroying himself, he is using a person merely as a means to keeping himself in a tolerable condition up to the end of his life. But a man is not a thing [Sache], so he isn’t something to be used merely as a means, and must always be regarded in all his actions as an end in himself. So I can’t dispose of a man by maiming, damaging or killing him—and that includes the case where the man is myself. (This basic principle needs to be refined so as to deal properly with questions such as ‘May I have one of my limbs amputated to save my life?’ and ‘May I expose my life to danger in order to save it?’ I shan’t go into these matters here; they belong to morals and not to the metaphysic of morals.)

(2) [Three times in this next paragraph, and nowhere else in this work, Kant writes of someone’s ‘containing’ the end of an action by someone else. Presumably for B to ‘contain’ the end of A’s action is for B to have A’s end as his end also, to seek what A seeks.] As concerns necessary....duties to others, when someone A has it in mind to make someone else B a deceitful promise, he sees immediately that he intends to use B merely as a means, without B’s containing in himself the end of the action. For B can’t possibly assent to A’s acting against him in this way, so he can’t contain in himself the end of this action. This conflict with the principle about treating others as ends is even easier to see in examples of attacks on people’s freedom

^11 Here I put this proposition forward as a postulate. The reasons for it will be given in the last chapter.

29

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 2

and property; for in those cases it’s obvious that someone who violates the rights of men intends to make use of the person of others merely as means, without considering that as rational beings they should always be valued at the same time as ends, i.e. as beings who can contain in themselves the end of the very same action.^12

(3) With regard to contingent (meritorious) duty to oneself [for ‘meritorious’ see page 26], it isn’t sufficient that the action not conflict with humanity in our person as an end in itself; it must also harmonize with it. In human nature there are predispositions to greater perfection that are part of nature’s purpose for humanity....; to neglect these might perhaps be consistent with the preservation of humanity as an end in itself but not with the furtherance of that end.

(4) With regard to meritorious duty to others: Humanity might survive even if

•no-one contributed to the happiness of others, but also

•no-one intentionally took anything away from the happiness of others;

·and this is a likely enough state of affairs, because· the end or purpose that all men naturally have is their own happiness. This would put human conduct into harmony with humanity as an end in itself, but only in a negative manner. For a positive harmony with humanity as an end in itself, what is required is that everyone ·positively· tries to further the ends of others as far as he can. For the ends of any person, who is an end in himself, must as far as possible be also my ends, if that thought ·of him as an end in himself· is to have its full effect on me.

This principle concerning the status of each human being—and more generally of each rational creature—as an end in himself is the supreme limiting condition on the freedom of action of each man. (·Supreme in the sense that it trumps everything else, e.g. prudential considerations·.) It isn’t drawn from experience; ·there are two reasons why it can’t be·. •One reason is the principle’s universality: it applies to absolutely all rational beings, and experience doesn’t stretch out that far. •The other is the fact that the principle isn’t about humanity considered subjectively, as something that men do take to be an end, i.e. do choose to aim at, but rather about humanity considered as the objective end that ought to constitute the supreme limiting condition of all subjective ends, whatever they may be. ·Experience can inform us about what subjective ends men do set before themselves, but not about what non-subjective end ought to trump every subjective end·. So this principle ·can’t arise from experience, and· must arise from pure reason.

According to the first principle, the •objective basis for all practical legislation lies in •the rule and the form of universality, which makes it capable of being a natural law [bold type on page 24]. Its •subjective basis is •the end; and according to the second principle the subject of all ends is every rational being as an end in itself. From this we now derive the third practical principle of the will, as the supreme condition of its harmony with universal practical reason, namely, the idea of the will of every rational being as a will laying down universal law.

^12 Don’t think that the banal ‘Don’t do to anyone else what you wouldn’t want done to you’ could serve here as a guide or principle. It is only a consequence of the real principle, and a restricted and limited consequence at that. It can’t ·as it stands· be a universal law, because it doesn’t provide a basis for •duties to oneself, or •benevolent duties to others (for many a man would gladly consent to not receiving benefits from others if that would let him off from showing benevolence to them!), or •duties to mete out just punishments to others (for the criminal would argue on this ground against the judge who sentences him). And so on.

30

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 2

By this ·third· principle, any maxim is rejected if it isn’t consistent with the will’s role as a giver of universal law. Hence the will is not merely subject to the law, but subject to it in such a way that it must be viewed as

•prescribing the law to itself,

and for just that reason as

•being subject to the law,

the law of which it sees itself as the author.

I have presented two kinds of ·categorical· imperative: one kind tells us to act in a manner that is lawful, like the lawfulness of the natural order; the other lays down that rational beings are in themselves supreme ends; and just because both of these are categorical, their commanding authority owes nothing to any action-driver involving one’s interests. But so far I have been assuming them to be categorical—an assumption I had to make if I was to explain the concept of duty. But are there any such imperatives, practical propositions that command categorically? Back there I couldn’t prove independently that there are, any more than I can prove it in this present chapter. But there’s something that I could have done—namely to point out an inherent feature of an imperative that specifically marks it off as categorical rather than hypothetical. The feature I have in mind is the renunciation of all one’s interests when one wills from duty. And now we have an example of this in the formulation of the principle ·of morality· that is now before us, the third, which involves the idea of the will of every rational being as a will that gives ·or legislates· universal law.

A will that is subject to laws can be bound to them by some interest that it has; but a will that is itself the supreme law-giver can’t depend upon any interest for this role. Why can’t it? Because if it did, it would need another law saying that its interests could be satisfied only if the first law were universally valid; ·in which case the first law wouldn’t be supreme, after all·.

Thus the principle of every human will as a will giving universal law in all its maxims,^13 provided it is otherwise correct, is very well suited to being a categorical imperative because of this feature: it involves the idea of giving universal law, so it isn’t based on any interest, and thus it is the only possible imperative that can be unconditional....

Look back on all the previous attempts to discover the principle of morality—no wonder they all failed! The searchers saw that

•man is bound by his duty to laws;

but it didn’t occur to them that

•all man is subject to are laws—universal laws—legislated by himself,

and that

•all he bound to is to act in accordance with his own will,

a will designed by nature to be a giver of universal law. The thought of him only as subject to some law or other brings with it the need for some interest that will pull or push him to obey the law—his will has to be constrained to act thus and so by something else—because the law hasn’t arisen from his will. This strictly valid inference means that all the work of looking for a supreme ground for duty was wasted labour; it never brought them to duty but only to the necessity for acting from a certain interest. It might be the person’s own interest or someone else’s; either way, the imperative always had to be conditional, and couldn’t serve as a moral command. I shall call this principle—·the third of

^13 I needn’t clarify this principle with fresh examples, because the ones I have already used to illustrate the categorical imperative and its formulation can here serve the same purpose.

31

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 2

my three·—the principle of autonomy of the will in contrast with every others, which I accordingly count as heteronomy. [From Greek: auto/hetero = self/other, and nomos = law. So Kant’s terminology distinguishes self-governed from other-governed.]

The concept of •every rational being as one who must regard himself as giving universal law through all the maxims of its will, so as to judge himself and his actions from this standpoint, leads to thje fruitful concept of •a realm of ends. [The German Reich mainly means ‘kingdom’ or ‘empire’, but the less highly charged ‘realm’ seems to fit well enough here.]

By ‘realm’ I understand the systematic union of different rational beings through shared laws. (The next sentence presents a thought-experiment; in conducting it, we have to abstract from personal differences of rational beings, and thus from all content of their private ends or purposes.) Because laws determine which ends have universal validity, we can think of a ·unified· whole of all ends in systematic connection—a whole composed of •rational beings who are ends in themselves and of •ends that they may individually set for themselves. This is a realm of ends, which is possible on the principles stated above.

That is because all rational beings stand under the law that each of them should treat himself and all others never merely as a means but always also as an end in himself. This gives rise to a systematic union of rational beings through shared objective laws, i.e. a realm; and it may be called a realm of ends because what these laws have as their purpose is just the relation of these beings to each other as ends and means. (Admittedly this realm of ends is only an ideal.)

A rational being is a member of the realm of ends if he gives universal laws in it while also being subject to those laws. He is sovereign in the realm of ends if, as law-giving, he isn’t subject to anyone else’s will. A rational being must always regard himself as law-giving in a realm of ends that is possible only through the freedom of the will, and this holds whether he belongs to the realm as a member or as sovereign. Being sovereign in the realm of ends isn’t a matter of choice; to be sovereign a rational being must •be completely independent ·of everything else·, •have no needs, and •have unlimited power adequate to his will.

So the morality of any action is constituted by how the action relates to the law-giving that is indispensable if there is to be a realm of ends. But this law-giving must be found in every rational being, being able to arise from his will. So the principle that drives his will is:

•never to act on a maxim that couldn’t consistently be a universal law,

and thus

•to act only so that the will could regard itself as giving universal law through its maxim.

In the case of a rational being whose maxims don’t by their nature already necessarily conform to this objective principle, the necessity of acting according to that principle is called practical compulsion ·or constraint·, i.e. duty. The sovereign in the realm of ends doesn’t have duties; all the mere members have duties, and are indeed burdened by duty to the same extent.

[Of the two versions of the end of this next sentence, the first fits Kant’s thought better: the only things he has called ends in themselves are rational beings. The second doctrinally drops out of the blue. But it is what Kant wrote; to get the first reading we must replace Kant’s sie by sich.] The •practical necessity of acting in accordance with this principle, i.e. •duty, doesn’t rest at all on feelings, impulses, and preferences; its sole basis is the way rational beings relate to one another—a relationship in which the will of a rational being must always be regarded as law-giving,

32

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 2

plausible reading: otherwise it couldn’t think of itself as an end in itself.
literal reading: otherwise it couldn’t think of duty as an end in itself.
Reason accordingly checks out every maxim of your will, ·in its role· as giver of laws, to see how it relates to everyone else’s will and also to every action towards yourself. It doesn’t do this from any external practical motive or future advantage, but rather from the idea of the dignity of a rational being who obeys no law except one that he himself gives while obeying it.

In the realm of ends everything has either a price or an intrinsic value. Anything with a price can be replaced by something else as its equivalent, whereas anything that is above all price and therefore admits of no equivalent has intrinsic value. [In this paragraph, ‘intrinsic value’ translates Würde, which is usually translated—here and in the Kantian literature generally—by ‘dignity’. At the end of the next paragraph Kant explicitly equates those two meanings.]

Something that involves general human desires and needs has a market price. Something that doesn’t involve anyone’s needing anything but accords with a certain taste (i.e. with pleasure in the purposeless play of our feelings) has a luxury price [Affektionspreis = ‘price related to the feelings’]. But if something makes it possible—and is the only thing that makes it possible—for something to be an end in itself, then it doesn’t have mere relative value (a price) but has intrinsic value (i.e. dignity). [Kant wrote: hat... einen innern Wert, d. i. Würde.]

Now, it is only through morality that

•a rational being can be a law-giving member in the realm of ends;

so it is only through morality that

•a rational being can be an end in himself.

So morality, and humanity so far as it is capable of morality, are the only things that have dignity. Skill and diligence in work have a •market price; wit, lively imagination, and humour have a •luxury price; but fidelity in promises and benevolence on principle (not benevolence from instinct) have •intrinsic value ·which I have called dignity·. If you don’t have these, neither nature nor art can supply anything that would make up for that lack in you; for their value doesn’t lie in the effects that flow from them—their usefulness, the advantages they bring—but only in the attitudes, i.e. the maxims of the will, that are ready to express themselves in this manner through actions, even if the actions don’t meet with success. For us to look on these actions with immediate favour and pleasure, we don’t have to bring in any of our subjective states, any immediate liking for or attraction to such actions. The actions exhibit the will that generates them as the object of an immediate respect, since nothing but reason is required to get the will to act like that. (Note that reason imposes these actions on the will; it doesn’t coax it into performing them, for that would flatly contradict the notion of duty.) This esteem lets the value of such a turn of mind be recognized as dignity ·or intrinsic value·, and puts it infinitely above any price; to compare it with, or weigh it against, things that have price would be to violate its holiness, as it were.

And what is it, then, that justifies virtue, or a morally good frame of mind, in making such lofty claims ·for itself·? It is its enabling the rational being to have a share in the giving of universal laws and thus to become fit to be a member in a possible realm of ends. (His nature has already marked him out for this role, as an end in himself and therefore as a law-giver in the realm of ends.).... For a rational being has no value except what the law confers on it. The law-giving that confers all value must therefore have dignity (i.e. an

33

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 2

unconditional and incomparable value); and the •esteem that a rational being must have for this is best described as ‘respect’ [Achtung; some of Kant’s uses of this suggest that ‘reverence’ would be a better translation]. Autonomy is thus the basis for the dignity of human nature and of every rational nature.

·I remind you that I have presented the principle of morality in three ways:

•Act as though the maxim of your action were to become, through your will, a universal law of nature. [page 24]

•Act in such a way as to treat humanity, whether in your own person or in that of anyone else, always as an end and never merely as a means. [page 29]

•Act only so that your will could regard itself as giving universal law through its maxim. [page 32]

· The above three ways of presenting the principle of morality are basically only so many different formulations of the very same law, and any two of them come together in the third. They do differ in a certain way, but the difference is subjective rather than objective—·i.e. the three formulations don’t express different moral principles, but they offer different ways for our minds to come at morality·. This difference is intended to introduce a certain analogy that will bring an idea of reason closer to intuition and thus nearer to feeling. All maxims have:

(1) A form; specifically, they are all universal. That leads to this formulation of the moral imperative: maxims must be chosen as if they were to hold as universal laws of nature.

(2) A matter ·or content·, i.e. an end. That leads to this formulation: all merely relative ends, ones that people choose, must be restricted by ·and subordinated to· the status of rational beings, which are ·not chosen as ends but are· ends by their very nature, and are therefore ends in themselves.

(3) A complete fixing of all maxims through this formulation: all the maxims that come from your own law-giving should harmonize with a possible realm of ends as with a realm of nature.^14

Moving through these three items is like moving through the Categories ·of Quantity, as set forth in my Critique of Pure Reason·:

the •Unity of the form of the will (its universality),

the •Plurality of the matter (the objects, ends), and

the •Totality of the system of ends.

In arriving at moral judgments one does better ·to go by just one of the three formulations, specifically· to follow the strict method and base one’s thinking on the universal formulation of the categorical imperative: Act in accordance with a maxim that can at the same time make itself a universal law. But if one wants to enable the moral law to have access to a mind, it is very useful to bring one and the same action under the three concepts I have listed, and thus, so far as possible, to bring it nearer to intuition.

We can now end where we started, with the concept of an unconditionally good will. A will is absolutely good if it can’t be bad, and thus never adopts maxims that conflict with themselves when they are generalized into universal laws. So this principle is also its supreme law: Always act on maxims whose universality as laws you can at the same time will. That’s the only way a will can avoid ever coming into conflict with itself, and such an imperative is categorical.

^14 •Teleology considers nature as a realm of ends; •morals regards a possible realm of ends as a realm of nature. In the •former the realm of ends is a theoretical idea for explaining what exists. In the •latter it is a practical idea for bringing about something that doesn’t yet exist but will become real through our conduct, in conformity with this very idea.

34

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 2

Because the •validity of the will as a universal law for possible actions has an analogy with the •way existing things are inter-connected under universal laws, this being the formal aspect of nature in general, the categorical imperative can be put like this: ·Act on maxims that can at the same time have themselves as universal laws of nature as their object·. That gives us the formula for an absolutely good will.

Rational nature is distinguished from the rest of nature in that it sets for itself an end. This end would be the material of every good will, but ·its relation to the absolutely good will involves a little wrinkle which I shall now explain·. The idea of an absolutely good will doesn’t have anything to do with this or that end that the will seeks to •bring about; the ends that a will aims to •bring about can only make it relatively good, not absolutely good; so we must understand the end of an absolutely good will

not as an end to be •brought about but as an independently existing end

which connects with the absolutely good will negatively—it is

an end which must never be acted against,

which implies that

it must never, in any act of the will, be valued merely as a means but always also as an end.

....The principle: ·Act in relation to every •rational being (whether yourself or another) so that in your maxim •he is an end in himself· is thus basically identical with the principle: Act on a maxim that involves its own universal validity for every rational being. That’s because the statement ‘In my use of means to any end I should restrict my maxim to the condition of its universal validity as a law for every subject’ is equivalent to the statement ‘The subject of ends (i.e. the rational being itself) must be made the basis of every maxim of action and thus be treated never as a mere means but as the supreme limiting condition in the use of all means—i.e. also as an end.

It •follows from this—no-one could question that it follows—that every rational being, as an end in himself, must be able to regard himself as a giver of universal laws that include any laws to which he may be subject. For what marks him off as an end in himself is just this fitness of his maxims for universal law-giving. It also •follows that this dignity that he has, his prerogative over all merely natural beings, involves his having to take his maxims from the point of view of himself and every other rational being as law-givers—which is why they are called ‘persons’. In this way, a world of rational beings....is possible as a realm of ends, through the law-giving activities of all the persons who are its members. Consequently every rational being must act as if his maxims made him at all times a law-giving member of the universal realm of ends. The formal principle of these maxims is: Act as though your maxims were also to serve as universal law for all rational beings. A realm of ends is thus possible only by analogy with a realm of nature. The realm of ends is possible only through

•maxims, i.e. rules imposed on oneself,

while the realm of nature is possible only through

•laws governing how things are acted on by other things.

Despite this difference, nature as a whole, though looked on as a machine, is given the name ‘realm of nature’—to the extent that, and because, it has reference to rational beings as its ends. [This is one of the places where ‘kingdom’ might be better than ‘realm’.] Such a realm of ends would actually come into existence through maxims whose rule is prescribed to all rational beings by the categorical imperative, if every rational being followed them all the time. A rational being who scrupulously follows this maxim can’t expect every other

35

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 2

rational being to follow suit; nor can he expect the realm of nature....to favour his expectation of happiness. Despite that, the law:

Act in accordance with the maxims of a universal-law-giving member of a merely possible realm of ends

remains in full force because it commands categorically. And just here lies the ·two-part· paradox: (1) the will is subject to an inflexible rule ·concerning the place of humanity in its deliberations·, simply because of the dignity of humanity as rational nature without any end or advantage to be gained by being human, and thus out of respect for a mere idea; and (2) what makes some maxims sublime, and makes every rational subject worthy to be a law-giver in the realm of ends, is just precisely this independence of his maxims from all such action-drivers ·as chosen ends and possible advantages·. If it weren’t for this independence, the rational being would have to be seen as subject only to the natural law of his needs. Even if the realm of nature and the realm of ends were thought of as united under one sovereign, so that the realm of ends •moved from being a mere •idea to becoming a reality and •gained reinforcement from a strong action-driver, still there would be no increase in its intrinsic value. For when we think about this possibility ·of a world in which a unique sovereign brings it about that principled actions do always lead to good consequences·, we have to think of the sole absolute law-giver as judging the value of rational beings only on the strength of the disinterested conduct that they prescribe to themselves merely from the •idea. The essence of things isn’t changed by their external relations, and the absolute [= ‘non-relational’] value of a man doesn’t involve his relations to other things either; so whoever is estimating a man’s absolute worth must set aside his external-relational properties—and this holds for anyone doing such an estimation, even the supreme being. Morality is thus the relation of actions ·not to anything external to the person, but· to the autonomy of the will.... ·Now here are definitions, in terms of the autonomy of the will, of five key terms in morality·. •An action that can co-exist with the autonomy of the will is permitted. •One that clashes with autonomy of the will is forbidden. •A will whose maxims are necessarily in harmony with the laws of autonomy is a holy or absolutely good will. •If a will is not absolutely good, it is morally constrained by the principle of autonomy and its relation to that principle is obligation (so a holy will can’t have obligations). •The objective necessity of an action from obligation is called duty.

From what I have been saying, it is easy to understand how this happens: although in thinking of duty we think of subjection to law, we nevertheless also ascribe a certain sublimity and dignity to the person who fulfils all his duties. There is nothing sublime about being subject to the moral law, but this person is also a giver of the law—that’s why he is subject to it, and only to that extent is he sublime. Also, I have shown above how the only action-driver that can give an action moral value is respect for the law, not any kind of fear or desire. The proper object of •respect is our own will to the extent that it tries to act only on maxims that could contribute to a system of universal legislation (such a will is ideally possible for us), and the •dignity of humanity consists just in its capacity to give universal laws to which it is also subject.

The autonomy of the will as the supreme principle of morality

A will’s autonomy is that property of it by which it is a law to itself, independently of any property of the objects of its volition. So the principle of autonomy is:

36

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 2

Always choose in such a way that the maxims of your choice are incorporated as universal law in the same volition.

That this practical rule is an imperative, i.e. that the will of every rational being is necessarily bound to it as a constraint, can’t be proved by a mere analysis of the concepts occurring in it, because it is a synthetic proposition. This synthetic proposition presents a command, and presents it as necessary; so it must be able to be known a priori. To prove it, then, we would have to go beyond knowledge of •objects to a critical examination of the •subject (i.e. to a critique of pure practical reason). But that is not the business of the present chapter. But mere analysis of moral concepts can show something to our present purpose, namely that the principle of autonomy that we are discussing is the sole principle of morals. This is easy to show, because conceptual analysis shows us •that morality’s principle must be a categorical imperative and •that the imperative ·in question· commands neither more nor less than this very autonomy. [See note on page 32 for ‘autonomy’ and ‘heteronomy’.]

The heteronomy of the will as the source of all spurious principles of morality

A will is looking for a law that will tell it what to do: if it looks anywhere except in the fitness of its maxims to be given as universal law, going outside itself and looking for the law in the property of any of its objects, heteronomy always results. For in that case the law is not something the will gives to itself, but rather something that the ·external· object gives to the will through its relation to it. This relation, whether it rests on preference or on conceptions of reason, admits of only hypothetical imperatives: •I should do x because I want y. The moral or categorical imperative, on the other hand, says that •I should do x whether or not I want anything else. For example, the hypothetical says that •I shouldn’t lie if I want to keep my reputation. The categorical says that •I shouldn’t lie even if lying wouldn’t bring the slightest harm to me. So the categorical imperative must abstract from every object thoroughly enough so that no object has any influence on the will; so that practical reason (the will), rather than catering to interests that are not its own, shows its commanding authority as supreme law-giving. Thus, for instance, I ought to try to further the happiness of others, but not in the spirit of ‘it matters to me that these people should be happier, because...’ with the blank filled by a reference to some preference of mine, whether directly for the happiness of the people in question or indirectly via some satisfaction that is related to their happiness through reason. Rather, I should to try to further the happiness of others solely because a maxim that excludes this can’t be included as a universal law in one and the same volition.

Classification of all possible principles of morality that you’ll get if you take heteronomy as the basic concept

·Why the interest in all possible principles that come from this underlying mistake? Because· in the absence of a critical examination of the pure use of reason, human reason always—including here—tries every possible wrong way before it succeeds in finding the one true way!

If you start with the idea of heteronomy—i.e. of how the will can be directed from outside itself—you will be led to principles of one of two kinds: empirical and rational. (1) The empirical ones have to do with happiness, and are based on ·the thought of the will as being influenced by· either (1a) physical feelings ·concerning one’s own happiness· or (1b) moral feelings. (2) The rational ones have to do with

37

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 2

perfection and are based on the thought of the will as being influenced by either (2a) the rational concept of perfection as a possible result ·of our activities· or (2b) the concept of an independently existing perfection (the will of God). ·You can see that all four of these have the will being influenced from outside itself. Let us now look into them in detail·.

(1) Empirical principles are not at all fit to serve as the basis of moral laws. For moral laws should be universal, valid for all rational beings without distinction, that being what makes them unconditionally practically necessary; but this universality is lost if moral laws are derived from the specific constitution of human beings—·a constitution that may not be shared by other rational beings·—or the particular circumstance in which human beings happen to live. (1a) But the principle of one’s own happiness is the most objectionable of the empirical bases for morality. ·There are at least three reasons for this, of which the third is the weightiest·. •This basis for morality is just false: experience contradicts the allegation that well-being is always proportional to good conduct. •The principle contributes nothing to the establishment of morality, because making a man happy is very different from making him good, and making him prudent and sharp in seeing what is to his own advantage is far from making him virtuous. •Above all: this principle supports morality with action-drivers that undermine it and destroy all its sublimity, for it puts the motives to virtue and those to vice in the same class, obliterating the difference of kind between them, and teaching us merely to make a better job of calculating ·what will make us happy·. (1b) Now for the supposed special sense, moral feeling.^15 There are endless differences in degree between different kinds of feeling, so that feelings can’t give us a uniform standard of good and bad; and anyway one can’t validly judge for others by means of one’s own feeling. So the appeal to moral feelings is superficial. Those who believe that feelings can help them to grasp universal laws are people who can’t think! Despite all this, the moral-feeling approach is nearer to morality and the dignity of morality, because it honours virtue by ascribing immediately to her the satisfaction and esteem we have for her, and does not, as it were, (1a) tell her to her face that what attaches us to her is not her beauty but only our advantage! [The use of ‘her’ to refer to virtue is based not on Kant’s using a personal pronoun (German doesn’t have them) but just on the content of the metaphor that he uses.]

(2) Among the rational principles of morality—the ones based on reason—there is (2a) the ontological concept of perfection. It is empty, indefinite, and consequently useless for finding in the immeasurable field of possible reality the greatest possible sum ·of perfections· that is suitable to us. Also, when we try to say what marks off this reality—·perfection·—from all other realities, we inevitably tend to move in a circle and can’t avoid tacitly •presupposing the morality that we are trying to •explain. Nevertheless, this is better than (2b) the theological concept, which derives morality from a most perfect divine will. ·There are two reasons for the inferiority of the theological concept; or, more accurately, they are two halves of a single reason which constitutes a dilemma confronting the theological approach to morality·. The perfection of the divine will is not something that is given to us in intuition ·analogous to how items are given to us through the senses·; so we have to derive it from our own concepts. •Foremost among these is our concept

^15 I bring moral feeling under the heading of happiness because every empirical interest promises to contribute to our well-being by the agreeableness that a thing affords, either (1a) indirectly, through the thing’s contributing to our happiness, or (1b) directly, through our finding the thing itself agreeable without any thought of our own future advantage....

38

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 2

of morality; if we let this generate our concept of God’s perfection, and then use the latter as a basis for morality, we are guilty of a flagrantly circular explanation. •And if we don’t get at God’s perfection in that way, our only remaining concept of it is made up of

the attributes of desire for glory and dominion,

combined with

the awe-inspiring conceptions of power and vengefulness;

and any system of ethics based on these would be directly opposed to morality.

The (1b) concept of the moral sense and (2a) that of perfection in general have this to be said for them, that they don’t weaken morality; but neither is capable of serving as its foundation. Still, if I had to choose between them, I would opt for (2a) perfection in general, because it takes the decision ·about the basis for morality· away from the realm of sensibility and submits it to the court of pure reason. It doesn’t get a decision there, but at least it preserves the indefinite idea of a will that is good in itself, without falsifying it—·saving a place for it· until it can be more narrowly defined.

You won’t mind if I don’t grind through a long refutation of all these doctrines. There’s no need for me to do that, because it is so easy to do and so well understood—even by those whose official positions require them to declare for one of these theories because their hearers wouldn’t tolerate suspension of judgment. What matters more to us here is to know this: All these principles try to base morality purely on heteronomy of the will, so they are bound to fail.

[An addition to this paragraph is marked by * rather than ·, because of its length.] Whenever an object of the will has to be laid down as prescribing the rule that is to tell the will what to do, the rule is none other than heteronomy. In such a case the imperative is conditional—

If or because you want such and such an object, you ought to act thus and so

—so it can’t command morally, i.e. categorically. The object’s influence on what my will does may go through my preference (as in the principle of my own happiness) or through my reason directed to objects of my possible volitions (as in the principle of perfection); but the will in these cases never determines itself directly by the conception of the action itself. It is always directed ·by an object through something other than the will, namely· through the action-driver that is stirred up in the will by the prospect of getting a certain result:

I ought to do x because I will y;

and then another law must be planted in me, a law saying that I must will y; and this law in its turn would require an imperative to restrict this maxim—*i.e. an imperative of the form

I ought to will y if I want z.

Why? Because if instead we had simply

I ought to will y,

that involves no appeal to anything outside the will; it is a categorical imperative, and doesn’t involve heteronomy of the will. But that puts it outside the scope of the present discussion, which is of the consequences of trying to base morality on heteronomy, i.e. on the influence on the will of factors outside it. Relying on heteronomy has one bad consequence that I haven’t yet mentioned*. With a hypothetical imperative such as we get with heteronomy of the will, the aim is for •the thought of a result to be obtained by one’s own powers to stir up in the will •an impulse of a certain kind (·the thought of achieving y is to stir up an impulse to do x·); but whether and how that thought generates that impulse depends on the natural constitution of the person

39

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 2

concerned—i.e. depends either on his sensibility (preference and taste) or on his understanding and reason. Now, what the person’s sensibility or intellect makes of any intended upshot—e.g. whether it takes pleasure in it—depends on the details of what kind of sensibility or intellect nature has endowed the person with; which implies that strictly speaking the source of this law is nature. As a law of nature, this would have to be known and proved by experience, which means that it would be contingent and therefore unfit to be a necessary practical rule such as the moral rule must be. This is still heteronomy of the will: the law is given to the will not by •the will itself but by •an impulse from outside it, an impulse that influences the will because the person’s nature makes him susceptible to it.

So an absolutely good will, the principle of which must be a categorical imperative, doesn’t specify any object, and contains only the form of volition as such, and this form is autonomy. That is,

•the sole law that the will of every rational being imposes on itself

is just

•the fitness of the maxims of every good will to turn themselves into universal laws;

and there is no need for this to be supported by any action-driver associated with an interest.

How can there be such a synthetic practical a priori proposition, and why it is necessary? The solution of that problem doesn’t lie within the boundaries of the metaphysic of morals; and I haven’t here affirmed its truth, let alone claimed to have a proof of it in my power. All I have done is to show, by spelling out the generally accepted concept of morality, that an autonomy of the will is unavoidably connected with morality—is indeed its foundation. So anyone who holds that morality is something and not a chimerical idea without truth must accept, along with morality, the principle that I have derived here. Consequently, this chapter like the first was merely analytic; ·it reached its conclusions by analysing, spelling out the content of, the generally accepted concept of morality·. If the categorical imperative, and with it the autonomy of the will, is true and absolutely necessary as an a priori principle, it follows that morality isn’t a phantom; but to prove that it isn’t we must be able to make a synthetic use of pure practical reason. But we mustn’t venture on this use without first making a critique of this faculty of reason. In this next chapter—the last—I shall give the chief features of such a critique, in enough detail for our purpose.

40

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 3

Chapter 3:

Moving from the metaphysic of morals to the critique of pure practical reason

The concept of freedom is the key to explaining the autonomy of the will

Will is a kind of causality that living beings exert if they are rational, and when the will can be effective independent of outside causes acting on it, that would involve this causality’s property of freedom; just as natural necessity is the property of the causality of all non-rational beings, through which they are caused to act in specific ways by the influence of outside causes.

The account of freedom I have just given is negative (·it says there is freedom when the active will does not have external causes acting on it·), and so it isn’t fruitful for insight into what freedom is; but there flows from it a concept of freedom that is positive, and accordingly richer and more fruitful. Although freedom is not a property of the will according to •laws of nature, it doesn’t follow that freedom is lawless! It must in fact be a causality according to immutable •laws of a special kind. The ‘concept’ of lawless free-will would be an absurdity, because the concept of causality brings with it the concept of laws according to which if something we call a cause is given then something else, the effect, must occur. ·And since

freedom conceptually involves causality, and

causality conceptually involves law,

it follows that

freedom conceptually involves law.

We saw that· natural necessity is a •heteronomy of effective causes, because each effect can come about only through a law according to which •something else gets the cause to exercise its causality. What can the freedom of the will be, then, but •autonomy, i.e. the will’s property of •itself being a law? However, the proposition:

•The will itself is a law in all its actions

only expresses the principle:

•Act only on a maxim that can also have itself as a universal law for its object.

And this is just the formula of the categorical imperative and is the principle of morality. Therefore a •free will and a •will under moral laws are identical. [Earlier in this paragraph Kant said that all causality involves an effect’s being caused by something else. What he is now treating as the mark not of causality as such but of heteronomous causality in particular is the cause’s being stirred into action by something else. In the next paragraph, ‘something else’ occurs again in a manner that does seem to conflict with what Kant first said about causality in general.]

So if we start with freedom of the will, we get morality (together with its principle) from it merely by •analysing its concept. But the principle of morality:

An absolutely good will is one whose maxim can always include itself regarded as a universal law,

is a •synthetic proposition, because that property of the maxim can’t be found by analysis of the concept of an absolutely good will. What makes such a synthetic proposition possible is there being two cognitions [= ‘items of knowledge’] that are connected with each other through their both being contained in some third cognition. In the case of physical causes, the ‘third cognition’ that ties the cause to the effect is the •nature of the sensible world; but the concept of that conjoins the two concepts of something as cause in relation

41

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 3

to something else as effect; so it doesn’t meet our present needs. In our present context, the ‘third cognition’ that does the job is the •positive concept of freedom. Two tasks present themselves: (1) To show what this third cognition is to which freedom directs us and of which we have an a priori idea, and (2) To make comprehensible the deduction of the concept of freedom from pure practical reason, and along with that the possibility of a categorical imperative. But I can’t do either of these right here and now; first, some further preparation is needed.

Freedom must be presupposed as a property of the will of all rational beings

It isn’t enough to ascribe freedom to •our will, on whatever grounds, if we don’t also have sufficient grounds for attributing it to •all rational beings. For morality serves as a law for us only because we are rational beings, so it must hold for all rational beings; and morality must be derived solely from the property of freedom; so freedom must be shown to be a property of the will of all rational beings. And it doesn’t suffice to do this on the basis of certain supposed empirical facts concerning human nature: we need an a priori proof (·which empirical facts can’t provide·), and we need a result concerning absolutely all rational beings endowed with a will (·and not merely concerning human beings·). Now I say this:

Any being who can’t act otherwise than under the idea of freedom is, just for that reason, really free in his conduct—i.e. all laws that are inseparably bound up with freedom hold for him just as if his will were validly pronounced free in itself as a matter of theoretical philosophy.^16

Now I maintain this:

We must necessarily equip every rational being who has a will with the idea of freedom, this being an idea under which he must act.

For the thought of such a being includes the thought of a reason that is practical, i.e. has causality with respect to its object. Now we can’t conceive of a reason that would consciously take direction (about how to judge) from outside itself, for then the person ·whose reason it was· would think that what settled how he judged was not his reason but some ·external· impulse. Reason must regard itself as the author of its principles, owing nothing to external influences; so it must—as practical reason, or as the will of a rational being—regard itself as free. That is to say, the will of a rational being can be his will only under the idea of freedom, so that from a practical point of view such a will must be ascribed to all rational beings.

Why should I be moral?

We have finally traced the determinate concept of morality back to the idea of freedom, but we couldn’t prove freedom to be actual in ourselves and in human nature. We saw only that we must presuppose it if we want to think of a being as rational and as conscious of himself as the cause of his own actions, i.e. as endowed with a will; and so we find that on just those same grounds we must ascribe to each being

^16 I start in a way that is sufficient for my purposes, with freedom as something posited by all rational beings merely in idea as the basis for their actions. I go about things in this way so as to avoid having to prove freedom also in its theoretical respect. Even if the latter—·actual, factual, theoretical freedom·—is left unproved, ·it makes no difference, because· the laws that would hold for a being who was really free hold also for a being who cannot act except under the idea of his own freedom. Thus we escape the burden ·of proof· that the theoretical assertion of freedom would impose upon us.

42

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 3

endowed with reason and will this property of settling for himself how he will act, doing this under the idea of freedom.

From the presupposition of this idea ·of freedom· there flowed also the consciousness of a law of action:

The subjective principles of actions (i.e. maxims) must always be adopted in such a way that they can hold also as objective, i.e. hold as universal principles, thereby serving as universal laws that we give to ourselves.

But why ought I, just because I am a rational being, subject myself to this law? And why should all other beings endowed with reason do so? Admittedly no interest impels me to do this, for that wouldn’t yield a categorical imperative; but I must still take an interest in it, and have insight into how it comes about. For this ‘ought’ is really a ‘shall’ that holds for every rational being whose reason isn’t hindered in its generating of actions. For beings like ourselves, that necessity of action is expressed only as ‘ought’, and the subjective necessity is thus distinguished from the objective. By ‘beings like ourselves’ I mean ones who are affected not only by reason but also by action-drivers that come from the senses—beings who don’t always do what reason would have done if left to itself.

So it seems that all we have done with respect to the moral law (i.e. the principle of the autonomy of the will) is to presuppose it in the idea of freedom, as though we couldn’t independently prove its reality and objective necessity. Even that would bring some gain, because in doing it we would at least have defined the genuine principle more accurately than had been done before; but we wouldn’t have made any progress regarding the validity of the moral law or the practical necessity of subjecting ourselves to it. If anyone asked:

•Why do our actions have to be based on maxims that could be universally valid as laws?

•What is the basis for the value that we ascribe to this way of acting—a value so great that no interest, anywhere, can outweigh it?

•How does it come about that a man believes that it is only through this that he feels his own personal value, in contrast to which that of a pleasant or unpleasant state is to be regarded as nothing?

we couldn’t give him any satisfactory answer.

We do indeed find that we can take an interest in a personal quality that makes us fit to enjoy some condition if reason were to allot that condition to us, even though the personal quality doesn’t automatically bring the condition with it. ·An example might be: taking an interest in being the sort of person who would be a good spouse, this being distinct from taking an interest in being married·. That is, we can take an interest in being worthy of happiness without having being happy as a motive. But this judgment ·about value—this taking of an interest·—is in fact only the effect of the importance we have already ascribed to the moral law (when through the idea of freedom we detach ourselves from every empirical interest). But ·we are confronted by the proposition that·

We ought to detach ourselves from every empirical interest, to regard ourselves as free in acting and yet as subject to certain laws, in order to find right there within ourselves a value that would compensate for the loss of everything that could make our situation desirable.

How this is possible, and hence on what grounds the moral law is binding, can’t be grasped through my procedure up to here.

43

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 3

It has to be admitted that there is a kind of circle here from which there seems to be no escape. We take ourselves to be free in the order of effective causes so that we can think of ourselves as subject to moral laws in the order of ends; and then we think of ourselves as subject to these laws because we have ascribed to ourselves freedom of the will. This is circular because •freedom and •self-legislation by the will are both •autonomy; so they are equivalent concepts, which is why neither of them can be used to explain or support the other. At most they can be used for the logical purpose of bringing apparently different representations of the same object under a single concept (like reducing the both of the fractions 51/68 and 69/92 to 3/4).

There remains open to us, however, one way out ·of the circle·, namely, to pursue an inquiry into these:

•thinking of ourselves as causes that are effective a priori through freedom, and

•thinking of ourselves in terms of our actions considered as empirically observable effects.

·For example: •thinking of myself as voluntarily raising my arm, and •thinking of myself as seeing my arm go up·. The question is: Don’t these involve different standpoints?

[In this next paragraph and later on, Kant refers to a certain ‘world’ that he calls Verstandeswelt = ‘world of understanding’. Evidently this ‘world’ has at least as much to do with •reason as with •understanding, and we shall see on the next page that Kant distinguishes these from one another. So ‘world of understanding’ would be a misleading label, and ‘intelligible world’ is used instead. In some places where Verstandeswelt would be especially misleading, Kant instead uses intelligibel Welt.] What I am about to say requires no subtle reflection, and presumably even the most ordinary intellect could arrive at it (doing so in its own way, through an obscure exercise of judgment that it calls ‘feeling’!). All mental representations that come to us involuntarily (as do those of the senses) enable us to know objects only •as they affect us, which leaves us still ignorant of what they are •in themselves; and therefore representations of this kind, however closely and sharply we attend to them, can give us only knowledge of appearances, never knowledge of things in themselves. This distinction may be made just by noticing the difference between •representations that we passively receive from somewhere else and •ones that we actively produce out of ourselves. Once the distinction has been made ·somehow·, it automatically follows that we must admit and assume behind the appearances something else that is not appearance, namely things in themselves. But we have to accept that we can’t get any closer to them, and can’t ever know what they are in themselves, because all we can know of them is how they affect us. This must yield a distinction, though a rough one, between

•a sensible world, which can be very different to various observers, because of differences in their sensibilities, and

•an intelligible world, which underlies the sensible world, and remains always the same.

A man shouldn’t claim to know even himself as he really is by knowing himself through inner sensation—·i.e. by introspection·. For since he doesn’t produce himself (so to speak) or get his concept of himself a priori but only empirically, it is natural that he gets his knowledge of himself through inner sense and consequently only through how his nature appears and how his consciousness is affected. But beyond the character of his own subject, which is made up out of these mere appearances, he necessarily assumes something else underlying it, namely his I as it is in itself. Thus in respect to mere perception and receptivity to sensations he must count himself as belonging to the sensible world;

44

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 3

but in respect to whatever pure activity there may be in himself (which reaches his consciousness •directly and not •by affecting the ·inner or outer· senses) he must count himself as belonging to the intellectual world—though he doesn’t know anything more about it.

A thoughtful person must come to some such conclusion as this about all the things that present themselves to him. Even someone with a very ordinary mind is likely to have this thought, because we know that such people are strongly inclined to expect something invisibly active at work behind the objects of the senses; but they don’t learn anything from this because they soon spoil it by trying to make the ‘invisible something’ perceptible, i.e. to make it an object of intuition. ·They do this by wondering ‘What is it like, this unknown something that lurks behind the appearances of things?’, when their only concept of what a thing can be like is made from the concept of how things appear to them·.

Now a human being really finds within himself a capacity by which he distinguishes

•himself from •all other things,

and that includes distinguishing

•himself ·as something active· from •himself considered as affected by objects.

This capacity or faculty is reason. Its pure, spontaneously active nature puts reason on a higher level even than understanding, ·and here is why·. Understanding ·is like reason in this: it· is spontaneously active, and does not—like the faculty of sense—merely contain representations that come from our being passively affected by things. But ·it is unlike reason in that· the only concepts it can produce through its activity are ones whose only role is to bring the representations of sense under rules.... ·The intellectual management of the data of the senses is the understanding’s only task·. Without this use of sensibility the understanding wouldn’t have any thoughts at all. In contrast with this, reason shows in its ideas, as we call them (·ideas relating to reason as concepts do to the understanding·), a spontaneity so pure that it goes far beyond anything that sensibility can come up with. The highest occupation of reason is to distinguish the sensible world from the intellectual world, thereby marking out limits for the understanding itself.

Because of this, a rational being must regard himself—in his role as an intelligence, setting aside his lower faculties—as belonging not to the sensible world but to the intelligible world. So he has two standpoints from which he can •consider himself and •recognize the laws for the use of his powers and hence for all his actions. (1) As belonging to the sensible world, ·he falls· under the laws of nature (heteronomy). (2) As belonging to the intelligible world, ·he is· under ·the moral authority of· laws that are independent of nature, and so are not empirical but based entirely on reason.

As a rational being and thus as belonging to the intelligible world, a human being can never think of the causality of his own will except under the idea of freedom; because reason must always take itself to be independent of the determining causes of the sensible world, and that independence is what freedom is. Now we have the idea of freedom inseparably connected with the concept of autonomy, which is bound up with the universal principle of morality, which is ideally the ground of all actions of rational beings, just as the law of nature is the ground of all appearances.

That allays the suspicion (the one that I stirred up earlier) that there might be a hidden circle in our reasoning from •freedom to •autonomy and from •that to •the moral law—that we might have laid down the idea of freedom for the sake of the moral law so that we could later derive the law from freedom! That would have made us unable to give

45

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 3

any basis for the law.... But now we see that when we think of ourselves as free, we carry ourselves into the intelligible world as members of it and recognize •the autonomy of the will and •the morality that autonomy brings with it; whereas when we think of ourselves as under an obligation, we regard ourselves as belonging to the sensible world and at the same time also to the intelligible world.

How is a categorical imperative possible?

A rational being counts himself, as an intelligence, as belonging to the intelligible world, and only as an effective cause belonging to this world does he call his causality a ‘will’. On the other side, though, he is conscious of himself as a bit of the sensible world in which his actions are encountered as mere appearances of that causality ·of his will·. But we aren’t acquainted with that causality ·of his will·, so there’s no way we can grasp how these actions can arise from it; and so they must instead be regarded as caused by other appearances, namely, desires and preferences belonging to the sensible world. Considered only as a member of the intelligible world, my behaviour would completely accord with the principle of the autonomy of the pure will; considered as a bit of the sensible world, my behaviour would have to be assumed to conform wholly to the natural law of desires and preferences and thus to the heteronomy of nature. (The former behaviour would rest on the supreme principle of morality, and the latter on that of happiness.) But the intelligible world contains the ground or basis of the sensible world and therefore of its laws, and so the intelligible world is (and must be conceived as) directly law-giving for my will, which belongs wholly to the intelligible world. Therefore I see myself, in my status as an intelligence, •as subject to the law of the intelligible world, i.e. the law of reason which is contained in the idea of freedom, and •as subject to the autonomy of the will. Therefore the laws of the intelligible world must be regarded as imperatives for me, and actions that conform to them must be regarded as duties. All this holds, despite the fact that on the other side I am a being that belongs to the sensible world.

So this is how categorical imperatives are possible: The idea of freedom makes me a member of an intelligible world; if I were a member only of that world, all my actions would always conform to the autonomy of the will; but since I confront myself also as a member of the world of sense, my actions ought to conform to it. This categorical ‘ought’ presents a priori a synthetic proposition. ·It is synthetic· because ·in it· (1) my will affected by my sensuous desires has added to it the idea of (2) something that reason says contains its supreme condition, namely •that very same will considered as pure, self-sufficiently practical, and belonging to the intelligible world. ·It is a genuine addition; there’s no way you could extract (2) from (1) by sheer analysis·. [Kant adds a not very helpful comparison of this with his doctrine, expounded in his Critique of Pure Reason, about a priori synthetic propositions that are essential to our knowledge of any system of nature.]

The practical application of common-sense confirms the correctness of this deduction. When we present examples of honesty of purpose, of steadfastness in following good maxims, and of sympathy and general benevolence (even with great sacrifices of advantage and comfort), there is no man, not even the most malicious villain (provided he is otherwise accustomed to using his reason), who doesn’t wish that he also might have these qualities. It’s merely because of his preferences and impulses that he can’t make himself be like this; but he would like to be free of the burden of such preferences. He thus shows himself as having a thought in which he, with a will free from all impulses of sensibility,

46

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 3

transfers himself into an order of things altogether different from that of his desires in the field of sensibility. In this thought he doesn’t look for any gratification of desires or any state of affairs that would satisfy any desire that he has or can imagine having; for if that were his aim, the very idea that elicits this wish from him would lose its pre-eminence. All he can be looking for is a greater intrinsic value as a person. He believes himself to be this better person when he shifts himself to the standpoint of a member of the intelligible world, to which he is automatically taken by the idea of freedom (i.e. of not being acted on by causes in the sensible world). And in this standpoint he is conscious of a •good will which on his own confession constitutes the law for his •bad will as a member of the sensible world. He recognizes the status of the law even while he breaks it. The moral ‘ought’ is therefore his own necessary will as a member of the intelligible world, and it is conceived by him as an ‘ought’ only because he regards himself at the same time as a member of the sensible world.

Concerning the outermost boundary of all practical philosophy

All human beings think of themselves as having free will. That is the source of all judgments that acts that weren’t performed ought to have been performed. But this freedom isn’t ·something of which we have· an experiential concept; it can’t be, because even when

experience shows the opposite of things that are represented as •necessary on the supposition of freedom,

freedom still remains, ·which shows that it can’t be defeated by facts of experience because it isn’t in the same arena, so to speak, as they are·. On the other hand it is equally •necessary that everything that happens should be inexorably caused in accordance with natural laws; and this natural necessity [a single word in German] is also not ·something of which we have· an experiential concept, because it brings with it the concept of necessity and thus of something that can be known a priori, ·i.e. without consulting experience·. But this concept of a ·system of· nature is confirmed by experience, and it has to be presupposed if experience is to be possible—experience being knowledge of the objects of the senses interconnected by universal laws. So •freedom is only an idea of reason, whose objective reality in itself is doubtful, whereas •nature is a concept of the understanding, which does and necessarily must exhibit its reality in examples drawn from experience.

From this there arises a dialectic of reason—·a seeming conflict of reason with itself·—because the freedom ascribed to the will seems to contradict natural necessity, ·and reason finds itself drawn to each side of the apparent conflict· at this parting of the ways. •For speculative purposes ·such as the pursuit of scientific theories·, reason finds the road of •natural necessity more well-trodden and usable than that of freedom. •But for practical purposes—thinking about what to do and what not to do—the only way of bringing reason to bear is along the path of •freedom; which is why even the subtlest philosophy can’t argue freedom away, any more than the most ordinary common-sense can. So philosophy has to assume that no real contradiction will be found between freedom and natural necessity as applied to the very same human actions, for it can’t give up the concept of nature any more than it can that of freedom.

We’ll never be able to grasp how freedom is possible, but in the meantime we should at least eradicate in a convincing way this apparent contradiction. For if the very thought of freedom contradicted itself or contradicted nature (which is

47

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 3

equally necessary), freedom would have to be surrendered in favour of natural necessity.

But this contradiction couldn’t be escaped if the subject who seems to himself to be free were thinking of himself in the same sense or in the same relationship when he •calls himself free as when he •takes himself to be subject to natural law with respect to the very same action. So speculative philosophy can’t be excused from its task of showing at least this much: •that ·the ways of talking that produce· the illusion of contradiction come from our thinking of the person in a different sense and relationship when we call him free from that in which we consider him as a part of nature and subject to its laws; and •that these two ·standpoints· not only can very well coexist but must be thought of as necessarily united in one and the same subject. If this much is not shown, we are left with no basis for burdening reason with an idea ·as troublesome as that of freedom·—an idea which, though it can without contradiction be united with the well-established concept ·of natural necessity·, nevertheless entangles us in troubles that sorely embarrass reason in its theoretical use. It is only theoretical philosophy that has this duty; its purpose is to clear the way for practical philosophy. So it isn’t up to the philosopher to decide whether to remove the apparent contradiction or rather to leave it untouched; for if he doesn’t remove it, the theory about it would be a no-man’s-land which the fatalist would be entitled to take over, as a squatter, driving all morality out.

But we still haven’t reached the boundary of •practical philosophy. For the settling of the controversy ·over freedom· doesn’t belong to •it. The situation is just that practical philosophy demands that theoretical reason put an end to the discord in which •it entangles itself in theoretical questions, so that practical reason may have peace and security from outward attacks that could put into dispute the land on which it wants to build.

The common-sense claim to have freedom of the will is based on the person’s consciousness of something that has also been conceded as a presupposition, namely that

•reason is independent of causes that determine a person’s psychological state—causes that are all of the sort that sensation can inform us about, and that can be brought under the general name ‘sensibility’.

A human being, who in this way regards himself as an intelligence,

•when he thinks of himself as an intelligence with a will, and consequently with causality,

puts himself in a different order of things and in a relationship to determining grounds of an altogether different kind from what comes into play

•when he perceives himself as a phenomenon in the world of sense (as he really is also), and subjects his causality to external causal factors according to natural laws.

Now he soon realizes that both can exist together—indeed, that they must. For there is not the slightest contradiction between (1) a thing in appearance (belonging to the sensible world) being subject to certain laws from which as (2) a thing in itself it is independent. That he must think of himself in this twofold way rests on (1) his consciousness of himself as an object affected through the senses, and (2) his consciousness of himself as an intelligence (i.e. as independent of sensible impressions in the use of reason), and thus as belonging to the intelligible world.

[The indented portion of this paragraph is a first-person rendition of something that Kant writes using ‘he’ rather than ‘I’.] That’s how it comes about that a human being •claims to have a will that doesn’t make him accountable for what belongs only to his desires and preferences, but •thinks of this same

48

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 3

will as making possible—indeed necessary—actions that he can perform only by disregarding all his desires and sensuous attractions. The causality of these actions lies in •him as an intelligence and in •an intelligible world’s principles concerning effects and actions. All he knows about this intelligible world is this:

In this sensible world the law is given only by reason, and indeed pure reason independent of sensibility. Moreover, since it is only as an •intelligence that I am a genuine self (as a •human being I am only an appearance of myself), those laws apply to me immediately and categorically; so that nothing that I am pushed into doing by preferences or impulses—thus, nothing caused by the sensible world—can count against the laws of my volition as an intelligence.

Indeed, he doesn’t hold himself responsible for those ·preferences and impulses· or attribute them to his genuine self (i.e. to his will); though when he •allows them to influence his maxims in ways that go against the rational laws of his will, he holds his will to account for •that.

By thinking itself into an intelligible world, practical reason doesn’t at all step across that world’s boundaries, but it would do so if it tried to see or feel its way into it. The ·thought of the· intelligible world is only a negative thought with respect to the sensible world; it doesn’t give reason any laws for determining the will. The only positive thing about it is this:

Freedom as a negative determination—·i.e. as something that involves not being interfered with by sensible causes·—is also connected with a positive power and even a causality of reason, a causality that we call a ‘will’.

....But if practical reason were to borrow an object of the will (i.e. a motive) from the intelligible world, it would be overstepping its boundaries and pretending to be acquainted with something of which it knows nothing. So the concept of an intelligible world is only a standpoint that reason sees itself as having to take, outside appearances, in order to think of itself as practical. Reason couldn’t be practical if the influences of sensibility settled how the human being behaved, but it must be practical unless his consciousness of himself as an intelligence, and thus as a rational and rationally active cause (i.e. a cause acting in freedom), is to be contradicted. This thought certainly brings with it the idea of an order and a law-giving different from that of the mechanism of nature, which has to do with the sensible world; and it necessitates the concept of an intelligible world, i.e. the totality of rational beings as things in themselves; but without the slightest pretence to have any thoughts about it that go beyond its formal condition—i.e. the universality of the maxim of the will as law, and thus the will’s autonomy which is required for its freedom. All laws that are fixed on an object make for heteronomy, which belongs only to natural laws and can apply only to the sensible world.

We can explain things only by bringing them under laws governing things that could be confronted in experience. But freedom is only an idea ·of reason·; there is no way its objective reality could be shown through natural laws or, therefore, through any experience. Because it can’t be illustrated even in an analogical way with examples, we can’t ever grasp it or even see into it a little. It holds only as a necessary presupposition of reason in a being who believes himself conscious of having

a will, i.e. a faculty or capacity different from that of mere desire—a capacity to get himself to act as an intelligence, and thus to act according to laws of reason and independently of natural instincts.

But when we come to an end of causation according to

49

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 3

natural laws, we are at an end of all explanation, and all that is left for us to do is to defend—i.e. to refute objections from those who purport to have seen more deeply into the essence of things and who boldly declare freedom to be impossible. We can only show them that the supposed contradiction they have discovered in the idea of freedom lies simply in this:

They have to regard a human being as •appearance in order to bring natural laws to bear on his actions; and now when we require them to think of him-as-intelligence as a •thing in itself, they still persist regarding considering him as appearance.

Separating his causality (his will) from all natural laws of the sensible world does indeed involve a contradiction if this is the very same subject that we previously brought under natural laws; but the contradiction will disappear if they will think again, and admit that behind appearances things in themselves must stand as their hidden ground, and that we can’t insist that the laws of operation of these grounds must be the same as those that govern their appearances.

The subjective impossibility of explaining the freedom of the will is the same as the impossibility of discovering and making graspable an interest which a human being can take in moral laws.^17 Yet he does actually take an interest in them, and our name for the foundation of this is ‘moral feeling’. Some have wrongly offered this moral feeling as our standard for moral judgment, whereas really it should be seen as the subjective effect that the law has on the will; the objective grounds ·for moral judgment· come ·not from feeling but· from reason.

If a sensuously affected rational being is to will an action that reason alone prescribes as what he ought to do, reason must of course be able to instil a feeling of pleasure or satisfaction in the fulfilment of duty, and hence must have a causal power to affect sensibility in accordance with its own principles. But it is wholly impossible to conceive a priori how a mere thought with nothing sensuous in it produces a sensation of pleasure or unpleasure. For that is one particular kind of causality which, like every kind of causality, we can learn about only by consulting experience, not a priori. But ·we can’t understand this causality through experience either, because· we can do that only for cause-effect pairs where both items are objects of experience, whereas here the effect •does lie within experience but the cause—namely, reason acting through mere ideas, which furnish no object for experience—•does not. So it is completely impossible for us human beings to explain how and why we have an interest in the universality of the maxim as law and thus an interest in morality. Only this much is certain: (1) It is not the case that the law holds for us because we have an interest in it (for that would be heteronomy, making practical reason depend on sensibility in the form of an underlying feeling, which could never yield a moral law); and (2) It is the case that we have an interest in the moral law because it holds for us as human beings, because it has arisen from our will as intelligence, and hence from our genuine self. That source for the moral law is what gives it its authority, what

^17 It is by interest that reason becomes practical, i.e. becomes a cause acting on the will. That is why it is only of a being with reason that we say ‘He takes an interest in’ something; non-rational creatures don’t have interests—only sensuous impulses. Reason takes an •immediate interest in actions only in cases where what has moved the will in that direction is the universal validity of the action’s maxim. That’s the only kind of interest that is pure [= ‘non-empirical’]. In contrast with that, reason takes an indirect or •mediated interest in an action if it acts on the will only through the intervention or •mediation of another object of desire or under the supposition of some particular feeling that the subject has; and since such objects of desire and particular feelings can’t be found out by reason itself, unaided by experience, this mediated kind of interest is only empirical and not a pure interest of reason....

50

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 3

makes it hold for us, because reason necessarily makes what belongs to mere •appearance subordinate to the character of the •thing in itself.

So the question How is a categorical imperative possible? can be answered to this extent: We can •cite the only presupposition under which it is possible, namely the idea of freedom; and we can •have insight into the necessity of this presupposition. That is all we need for the practical use of reason (i.e. to be convinced of the categorical imperative’s validity and hence also of the moral law). But how this presupposition itself is possible can never be grasped by any human reason. However,....the presupposition of the freedom of the will is quite •possible, as speculative philosophy can prove, for it doesn’t involve itself in a contradiction with the principle that natural necessity interconnects all the appearances in the sensible world. More than that, it is unconditionally •necessary for any rational being. I mean that it is practically necessary for him, meaning that he needs it for his consciousness of his causality through reason,....needs the idea of it as the fundamental condition of all his voluntary acts. But the question still stands:

How can pure reason, all by itself without any outside help from other action-drivers, be practical? How can the mere principle of the universal validity of its maxims as laws....create, unaided, an action-driver and produce an interest that would be called ‘purely moral’? In short: How can pure reason be practical?

All human reason is wholly incompetent to explain this, and it is a waste of trouble and labour to try.

It is just the same as if I tried to find out how freedom itself as the causality of a will is possible, for in making that attempt I would be leaving the philosophical basis of explanation behind, and I have no other. I would still have the intelligible world, the world of intelligences, and I could drift around in that; but ·it couldn’t supply the desired explanation, because· although I have a well-founded idea of that world I don’t have the least knowledge of it—and I can’t have such knowledge, however hard I exercise my natural faculty of reason. This intelligible world signifies only a something—·a whatever-it-is·—that is left after I have excluded from the factors acting on my will everything belonging to the sensible world, which I did merely so as to shut the principle of motives out of field of sensibility. I did this by limiting this field and showing that it doesn’t contain absolutely everything, and that outside it there is still more; but that’s all I know about this ‘more’, ·namely that it lies outside the sensible world·. It is pure reason that has this ·idea, that is· the thought of this ideal entity, ·the intelligible world·; it has been deprived of all matter (i.e. all knowledge of objects); so all that I am left with ·in trying to make sense of pure reason· is

•the form, namely the practical law of the universal validity of maxims, and

•the possible role of pure reason as an effective cause acting on the will in accordance with that form.

There is no room here for any ·external· action-driver. If we insist on there being one, then the action-driver—i.e. that in which reason directly takes an interest—would have to be this idea of an intelligible world. But to understand how this could drive action is precisely the problem we can’t solve.

Here, then, is the outermost boundary of all moral inquiry [assuming that Kant wrote oberste = ‘highest’ when he meant to write äußerste = ‘outermost’, as in the heading on page 47]. It’s very important to locate it accurately, because if we don’t, ·either of two disasters may occur·. On the one hand, •reason may search for the supreme ·moral· motive in the sensible world, in a way harmful to morals.... On the other hand, •reason may impotently flap its wings in the space—so far as reason

51

Groundwork Immanuel Kant Chapter 3

is concerned it’s an empty space!—of....the intelligible world, without being able to move from its starting point and so losing itself among phantoms. For the rest, the idea of a pure intelligible world, as a whole of all intelligences to which we ourselves belong as rational beings (though on the other side we also belong to the sensible world), is always a useful and permissible idea for the purpose of a rational •belief, even though all •knowledge terminates at that world’s boundary. Its service is that of awakening in us a lively interest in the moral law through the noble ideal of a universal realm of ends in themselves (rational beings) to which we can belong as members only when we scrupulously conduct ourselves by maxims of freedom as if they were laws of nature.

Concluding remark

The speculative use of reason with respect to nature leads to the absolute necessity of some supreme cause of the world. The practical use of reason with regard to freedom leads also to an absolute necessity, but only of the laws of actions of a rational being as such. Now, it is an essential principle of all use of our reason to push its knowledge to an awareness of its necessity, for otherwise it wouldn’t be rational knowledge. But it is also an equally essential limitation of this very same reason that it can’t see that

necessarily x exists or y happens, or

necessarily z ought to happen,

except on the basis of some condition that applies to x or y or z. ·But the obtaining of a condition won’t make something necessary unless the condition itself is necessary; and so· if reason keeps searching for conditions it only pushes its satisfaction further and further into the future. So reason, restlessly seeking the unconditionally necessary, sees itself as having to assume it, though it has no way of making it comprehensible to itself; it is happy enough if it can merely discover the concept that is compatible with this presupposition. According to my account of the supreme principles of morality, reason can’t render comprehensible the absolute necessity of an unconditional practical law (such as the categorical imperative must be). If you want to complain about this, don’t blame my account—blame reason! ·Not that blame is appropriate·: reason can’t be blamed for being unwilling to explain the moral law through a condition—i.e. by making some interest its basis—for a law explained in that way would no longer be if it did, the law would cease to be moral and would no longer be the supreme law of freedom. So we truly don’t comprehend the unconditional practical necessity of the moral imperative; but we do comprehend its incomprehensibility, which is all that can fairly be demanded of a philosophy that in its principles forces its way out to the boundaries of human reason.

52

Discourse on Metaphysics

G. W. Leibniz

Copyright © Jonathan Bennett
[Brackets] enclose editorial explanations. Small ·dots· enclose material that has been added, but can be read as though it were part of the original text. Occasional •bullets, and also indenting of passages that are not quotations, are meant as aids to grasping the structure of a sentence or a thought.—-The division into sections is Leibniz’s; the division of some sections into paragraphs is not. Leibniz wrote brief summaries of the 37 sections of this work, but did not include them in the work itself. Some editors preface each section with its summary, but that interrupts the flow. In this version the summaries are given at the end. First launched: September 2004 Last amended: July 2007
[This single-column (but otherwise unrevised) version by Philosophy Ink derives from the original two-column PDF version at http://www.earlymoderntexts.com. Even Bennett's pagination has been retained since he sometimes makes in-text references to his own page numbers.]

Contents

Sections 1–13     1
Sections 14–23     9
Sections 24–37     17
Leibniz’s summaries     27

Discourse on Metaphysics G. W. Leibniz

Sections 1–13

1. The most widely accepted and sharpest notion of God that we have can be expressed like this:

God is an absolutely perfect being;

but though this is widely accepted, its consequences haven’t been well enough thought out. As a start on exploring them, let us note that there are various completely different ways of being perfect, and that God has them all, each in the highest degree. We also need to understand what a perfection is. Here is one pretty good indicator: a property is not a perfection unless there is a highest degree of it; so number and shape are not perfections, because there cannot possibly be a largest number or a largest thing of a given shape—·that is, a largest triangle, or square, or the like·. But there is nothing impossible about the greatest knowledge or about omnipotence [here = ‘greatest possible power’]. So power and knowledge are perfections, and God has them in unlimited form. It follows that the actions of God, who is supremely—indeed infinitely—wise, are completely perfect. This is not just metaphysical perfection, but also the moral kind. His moral perfection, so far as it concerns us, amounts to this: the more we come to know and understand God’s works, the more inclined we shall be to find them excellent, and to give us everything we could have wished.

2. Some people—·including Descartes·—hold that there are no rules of goodness and perfection in the nature of things, or in God’s ideas of them, and that in calling the things God made ‘good’ all we mean is that God made them. I am far from agreeing with this. If it were right, then God would not have needed after the creation to ‘see that they were good’, as Holy Scripture says he did, because he already knew that the things in question were his work. In saying this—·‘And God saw everything that he had made·, and, behold, it was very good’ (Genesis 1:31)—Scripture treats God as like a man; but its purpose in doing this appears to be to get across the point that a thing’s excellence can be seen by looking just at the thing itself, without reference to the entirely external fact about what caused it. Reinforcing that point is this one: the works must bear the imprint of the workman, because we can learn who he was just by inspecting them. I have to say that the contrary opinion strikes me as very dangerous, and as coming close to the view of the Spinozists that the beauty of the universe, and the goodness we attribute to God’s works, are merely the illusions of people who conceive God as being like themselves. Furthermore, if you say ·as Descartes did· that things are good not because •they match up to objective standards of goodness, but only because •God chose them, you will unthinkingly destroy all God’s love and all his glory. For why praise him for what he has done, if he would be equally praiseworthy for doing just the opposite? Where will his justice and wisdom be,

if there is only a kind of despotic power, if reason’s place is taken by will, and if justice is tyrannically defined as what best pleases the most powerful?

[Leibniz here relies on his view that it is through reason that we learn what things are good.] And another point: it seems that any act of the will presupposes some reason for it—a reason that naturally precedes the act—·so that God’s choices must come from his reasons for them, which involve his knowledge of what would· be good; so they can’t be the sources of the goodness of things. That is why I find it weird when Descartes says that the eternal truths of metaphysics and geometry, and therefore also the rules of goodness, justice, and perfection, are brought about by God’s will. Against this, they seem to me to be results of his •understanding, and no more to depend on his •will than his intrinsic nature does.

1

Discourse on Metaphysics G. W. Leibniz

3. Nor could I ever accept the view of some recent philosophers who have the nerve to maintain that God’s creation is not utterly perfect, and that he could have acted much better. This opinion, it seems to me, has consequences that are completely contrary to the glory of God. Just as a lesser evil contains an element of good, so a lesser good contains an element of evil. To act with fewer perfections than one could have done is to act imperfectly; showing an architect that he could have done his work better is finding fault with it. Furthermore, this opinion goes against holy scripture’s assurance of the goodness of God’s works. ·That goodness can’t consist simply in the fact that the works could have been worse; and here is why·. Whatever God’s work was like, it would always have been good in comparison with some possibilities, because there is no limit to how bad things could be. But being praiseworthy in this way is hardly being praiseworthy at all! I believe one could find countless passages in the holy scriptures and the writings of the holy fathers that support my opinion, and hardly any to support the modern view to which I have referred—a view that I think was never heard of in ancient times. It has arisen merely because we are not well enough acquainted with the general harmony of the universe and of the hidden reasons for God’s conduct; and that makes us recklessly judge that many things could have been improved. Furthermore, these moderns argue—subtly but not soundly—from the false premise that however perfect a thing is, there is always something still more perfect. They also think that their view provides for God’s freedom, ·through the idea that if God is free, it must be up to him whether he acts perfectly or not·; but really it is the highest freedom to act perfectly, in accordance with sovereign reason. For the view that God sometimes does something without having any reason for his choice, besides seeming to be impossible, is hardly compatible with his glory. Suppose that God, facing a choice between A and B, opts for A without having any reason for preferring it to B. I see nothing to praise in that, because all praise should be grounded in some reason, and in this case we have stipulated that there is none. By contrast, I hold that God does nothing for which he does not deserve to be glorified.

4. The love that we owe to God, above all things, is based (I think) on our grasp of the great truth that God always acts in the most perfect and desirable way possible. For a lover looks for satisfaction in the happiness or perfection of the loved one and of his actions. Friendship is wanting the same things and not-wanting the same things. And I think it will be hard to love God properly without being disposed to want what he wants, even if one had the power to get something different. Indeed, those who are not satisfied with what God does strike me as being like malcontent subjects whose set of mind is not much different from a rebel’s. These principles lead me to maintain that loving God requires a certain attitude to everything that happens to us through his will: not merely accepting it patiently because one has no alternative, but being truly satisfied with it. I am saying this about the past; for we shouldn’t be quietists about the future, stupidly waiting with folded arms for what God will do, as in the fallacy of ‘the argument for idleness’ (as the ancients called it). So far as we can judge what God wants, in a general way, we should act in accordance with that, doing our very best to contribute to the general good, and in particular to adorning and perfecting the things that concern us—what is close to us, within reach (so to speak). The outcome may show that in a particular instance God didn’t want our good will to have its effect, but it doesn’t follow that he didn’t want us to do what we did. On the contrary, as he is the best of masters, he never asks more than the right intention, and it is up to him to know when and where good

2

Discourse on Metaphysics G. W. Leibniz

intentions should succeed.

5. So it is enough to be sure of this about God: that he does everything for the best, and that nothing can harm those who love him. But to know in detail his reasons for ordering the universe as he has, allowing sin, and granting his saving grace in one way rather than another, is beyond the power of a finite mind, especially one that has not yet attained the delight of seeing God. Still, some general remarks can be made about how God goes about governing things. Thus, we can liken someone who acts perfectly to an •expert geometer who knows how to find the best construction for a problem; to a •good architect who exploits the location and the budget for his building to the best advantage, not allowing anything nasty, or less beautiful than it could be; to a •good head of a household, who manages his property so that no ground is left uncultivated or barren; to a •clever special-effects technician in the theatre, who produces his effect by the least awkward means that can be found; or to a •learned author, who gets the largest amount of subject-matter into the smallest space he can. Now, minds are the most perfect of all things, occupying the least space and thus providing the least hindrance to one another ·because they don’t take up space at all·; and their perfections are virtues. That is why we should be sure that the happiness of minds is God’s principal aim, which he carries out as far as the general harmony will permit. I’ll say more about this later. The simplicity of God’s ways relates to the •means he adopts, while their variety, richness or abundance relate to •ends or effects. These should be in balance with one another, as the money for putting up a building has to be balanced against its desired size and beauty. Admittedly, whatever God does costs him nothing—even less than it costs a philosopher ·or scientist· to invent theories out of which to build his imaginary world—for God can bring a real world into existence merely by decreeing it. But in the exercise of wisdom ·by God or a scientist· there is something analogous to the cost of a building, namely the number of independent decrees or theories that are involved. ·For God’s creative activity to be economical is for it to involve very few separate decrees; for a scientific theory to be economical in its means is for it to have very few basic principles or axioms·. Reason requires that multiplicity of hypotheses or principles be avoided, rather as the simplest system is always preferred in astronomy.

6. God’s wishes or actions are usually divided into the ordinary and the extraordinary. But we should bear in mind that God does nothing that isn’t orderly. When we take something to be out of the ordinary, we are thinking of some particular order that holds among created things. ·We do not, or ought not to, mean that the thing is absolutely extraordinary or disordered, in the sense of being outside every order; because· there is a universal order to which everything conforms. Indeed, not only does nothing absolutely irregular ever happen in the world, but we cannot even feign [= ‘tell a consistent fictional story about’] such a thing. Suppose that someone haphazardly draws points on a page, like people who practise the ridiculous art of fortune-telling through geometrical figures. I say that it is possible to find a single formula that generates a geometrical line passing through all those points in the order in which they were drawn. And if someone drew a continuous line which was now straight, now circular, now of some other kind, it would be possible to find a notion or rule or equation that would generate it. The contours of anyone’s face could be traced by a single geometrical line governed by a formula. But when a rule is very complex, what fits it is seen as irregular. So one can say that no matter how God had created the world, it would have been regular and in some general order. But God chose the most perfect order, that is, the order that is at

3

Discourse on Metaphysics G. W. Leibniz

once simplest in general rules and richest in phenomena—as would be a geometrical line whose construction was easy yet whose properties and effects were very admirable and very far-reaching. These comparisons help me to sketch some imperfect picture of divine wisdom, and to say something that might raise our minds to some sort of conception, at least, of what cannot be adequately expressed. But I don’t claim that they explain this great mystery ·of creation· on which the whole universe depends.

7. Now, because nothing can happen that isn’t orderly, miracles can be said to be as orderly as natural events. The latter are called ‘natural’ because they conform to certain subordinate rules—·ones that are not as general and basic as God’s fundamental creative decrees·—which we call the nature of things. This ‘Nature’ is only a way in which God customarily goes about things, and he can give it up if he has a reason for doing so—a reason that is stronger than the one that moved him to make use of these ·subordinate· maxims in the first place. General acts of the will are distinguished from particular ones. Using one version of this distinction, we can say that God does everything according to his most general will, which conforms to the most perfect order that he has chosen; but that he also has particular wills, which are exceptions (not to the most general of God’s laws, which regulates the whole order of the universe, and to which there are no exceptions, but) to the subordinate maxims I have mentioned, ·the ones that constitute ‘Nature’·. Any object of God’s particular will is something he can be said to want. But when it comes to the objects of his general will—such as are actions of created things (especially rational ones) which God chooses to allow—we ·cannot say that God wants them all, and· must make a distinction. (1) If the action is intrinsically good, we can say that God wants it, and sometimes commands it, even if it doesn’t happen. (2) But an action may be intrinsically bad, and only incidentally good because later events—especially ones involving punishment and reparations—correct its wickedness and make up for the bad with some to spare, so that eventually there is more perfection overall than if this bad thing had not been done. In a case like that we must say that God allows the action but not that he wants it, even though he goes along with it because of the laws of Nature that he has established and because he sees how to derive from it a greater good.

8. It is quite hard to distinguish God’s actions from those of created things. Some believe that God does everything, and others suppose that he only conserves the •force he has given to created things, ·allowing them to decide in what •directions the force shall be exercised·. We shall see later on what truth there is in each of these. Now since actions and passions properly belong to individual substances (when there is an action there is something, some subject, that acts), I have to explain what such a substance is. This much is certain: when several predicates are attributed to the same subject, and this subject is not attributed to any other, it is called an individual substance. ·For example, we call John a substance because we can attribute to him honesty, intelligence, and so on; but we don’t call his honesty a substance because, although we can attribute predicates to it (‘His honesty is charming, and surprising’) we can attribute it to something else, namely to John. In contrast, John cannot be attributed to anything else·. But that explanation is only nominal—·all it does is to relate our calling a thing a ‘substance’ to other facts concerning what we say about it·. Beyond that, we need to think about what it is for something to be truly attributed to a certain subject—·e.g. what it is for honesty to be a property of John·. Now it is certain that all true predication is founded in the nature of things, and when a proposition is not identical, that is, when

4

Discourse on Metaphysics G. W. Leibniz

the predicate is not explicitly included in the subject ·as in ‘The man who governs Somalia governs Somalia’·, it must be implicitly included in it. This is what philosophers call in-esse [being-in] when they say that the predicate is in the subject. So the ·notion of the· subject term must always include ·that of· the predicate, so that anyone who understood the subject notion perfectly would also judge that the predicate belongs to it. We can therefore say that the nature of •an individual substance or of a complete being is to have a notion so complete that it is sufficient to include, and to allow the deduction of, all the predicates of the subject to which that notion is attributed. •An accident, on the other hand, is a being whose notion doesn’t involve everything that can be attributed to the subject to which that notion is attributed. Thus Alexander the Great’s kinghood is an abstraction from the subject, ·leaving out much detail·, and so is not determinate enough to pick out an individual, and doesn’t involve the other qualities of Alexander or everything that the notion of that prince includes; whereas God, who sees the individual notion or ‘thisness’ of Alexander, sees in it at the same time the basis and the reason for all the predicates that can truly be said to belong to him, such as for example that he would conquer Darius and Porus, even to the extent of knowing a priori (and not by experience) whether he died a natural death or by poison—which we can know only from history. Furthermore, if we bear in mind the interconnectedness of things, we can say that Alexander’s soul contains for all time traces of everything that did and signs of everything that will happen to him—and even marks of everything that happens in the universe, although it is only God who can recognise them all.

9. Several considerable paradoxes follow from this, amongst others that it is ·never· true that two substances are entirely alike, differing only in being two rather than one. It also follows that a substance cannot begin except by creation, nor come to an end except by annihilation; and because one substance can’t be destroyed by being split up, or brought into existence by the assembling of parts, in the natural course of events the number of substances remains the same, although substances are often transformed. Moreover, each substance is like a whole world, and like a mirror of God, or indeed of the whole universe, which each substance expresses in its own fashion—rather as the same town looks different according to the position from which it is viewed. In a way, then, the universe is multiplied as many times as there are substances, and in the same way the glory of God is magnified by so many quite different representations of his work. It can even be said that each substance carries within it, in a certain way, the imprint of God’s infinite wisdom and omnipotence, and imitates him as far as it can. For it expresses (though confusedly) everything that happens in the universe—past, present, and future—and this is a little like infinite perception or knowledge. And as all the other substances express this one in their turn, and adapt themselves to it—·that is, they are as they are because it is as it is·—it can be said to have power over all the others, imitating the creator’s omnipotence.

10. The ancients, as well as many able teachers of theology and philosophy a few centuries ago—men accustomed to deep thought, and admirable in their holiness—seem to have had some knowledge of the things I have been saying, and to have been led by that to introduce and defend substantial forms. These are much sneered at today, but they are not so far from the truth, nor so ridiculous, as the common run of our new philosophers suppose. I agree that these forms have no work to do in explaining particular events, and thus no role in the details of physics. That is where our scholastics [= mediaeval Christian philosophers influence

5

Discourse on Metaphysics G. W. Leibniz

by Aristotle, Thomas Aquinas being the most famous example] went wrong, and the physicians of the past followed them into error: they thought they could invoke forms and qualities to explain the properties of bodies, without bothering to find out how the bodies worked—like settling for saying that a clock’s form gives it a ‘time-indicative quality’, without considering what that consists in—·that is, without considering what mechanisms are involved·. Actually, that might be all the clock’s owner needs to know, if he leaves the care of it to someone else. But this misuse and ·consequent· failure of ‘forms’ shouldn’t make us reject them. Metaphysics needs a knowledge of them, so much so that without that knowledge—I maintain—we couldn’t properly grasp the first principles ·of metaphysics·, and couldn’t raise our minds to the knowledge of immaterial natures and the wonders of God. However, ·important truths need not be taken into account everywhere·. A geometer need not worry about the famous labyrinth of the composition of the continuum [that is, the puzzles that arise from the idea that a line has no smallest parts]; and the huge difficulties to be found in trying to reconcile free will with God’s providence need not trouble a moral philosopher, still less a lawyer or politician; for the geometer can do all his proofs, and the politician can complete his plans, without getting into those debates, necessary and important though they are in philosophy and theology. In the same way a physicist can explain his experiments—sometimes using simpler experiments he has already made, sometimes proofs in geometry and mechanics—without needing to bring in general considerations belonging to another sphere. And if he does ·go outside his sphere, and· appeal to God’s cooperation, or to some soul or ‘spiritual force’ or other thing of that kind, he is talking nonsense, just as much as someone who drags large-scale reflections about the nature of destiny and our freedom into an important practical deliberation. Indeed men often enough unthinkingly make this mistake, when they let the idea of what is ‘fated’ to happen tangle their thoughts, and sometimes are even deterred by that idea from some good decision or some important precaution.

11. I know I am putting forward a considerable paradox in claiming to rehabilitate the ancient philosophy, in a way, and to re-admit substantial forms when they have been all but banished. But perhaps you won’t just brush me off if you realize that I have thought a lot about the modern philosophy, that I have spent much time on experiments in physics and proofs in geometry, and that for a long time I was sure that these entities [substantial forms] are futile. Eventually I had to take them up again—against my will, as though by force—after my own researches made me recognize that thinkers these days do less than justice to St. Thomas and to other great men of his time, and that the views of scholastic philosophers and theologians contain much more good stuff than people suppose, provided they are used relevantly. I am convinced, indeed, that if some exact and thoughtful mind took the trouble to clarify and digest their thoughts, in the way the analytic geometers do, he would find them to be a treasure-house of important and completely demonstrable truths.

12. Picking up again the thread of our reflections, I believe that anyone who thinks about the nature of substance, as I have explained it above, will find that there is more to the nature of body than extension (that is, size, shape, and motion), and that we can’t avoid attributing to body something comparable with a soul, something commonly called ‘substantial form’—though it has no effect on particular events, any more than do the souls of animals, if they have souls. It can be proved, indeed, that the notion of size-shape-movement is less sharp and clear than we imagine, and that it includes an element that belongs to imagination

6

Discourse on Metaphysics G. W. Leibniz

and the senses, as do—to a much greater degree—colour, heat, and other such qualities, which we can doubt are really there in the nature of external things. That is why qualities of such kinds could never constitute ·the basic nature of· any substance. Moreover, if there is nothing but size-shape-movement to make a body the thing that it is, then a body can never persist for more than a moment ·because bodies constantly gain and lose tiny bits of matter·. However, the souls and substantial forms of bodies other than ours are quite different from ·our· thinking souls. Only the latter know their own actions; and they don’t naturally go out of existence, but ·last for ever and· always retain the foundation of the knowledge of what they are. This is what makes them alone liable to punishment and reward, and what makes them citizens of the republic of the universe, of which God is the monarch. It also follows that all other creatures must serve them. I shall say more about that later.

13. The foundations that I have laid down give rise to a big problem, which I must try to solve before moving on. I have said that the notion of an individual substance involves, once and for all, everything that can ever happen to it; and that by looking into that notion one can see in it everything that will ever be truly sayable of the substance, just as we can see in the nature of a circle all the properties that are deducible from it. But this seems to destroy the difference between contingent and necessary truths, to rule out human freedom, and to imply that all the events in the world—including our actions—are governed by an absolute fate. To this I reply that we have to distinguish what is certain from what is necessary. Everyone agrees that future contingents are assured, because God foresees them; but we don’t infer from this that they are necessary. You may say:

But if some conclusion can be infallibly deduced from a definition or notion, it is necessary. And you contend that everything that happens to a person is already included implicitly in his nature or notion, just as a circle’s properties are contained in its circle; so you are still in trouble.

I shall now resolve this problem completely. To that end, I remark that there are two kinds of connection or following-from. One is absolutely necessary, and its contrary implies a contradiction; such deduction pertains to eternal truths, such as those of geometry. The other is necessary ·not absolutely, but· only ex hypothesi, and, so to speak, accidentally. ·It doesn’t bring us to It is necessary that P, but only to Given Q, it follows necessarily that P·. Something that is necessary only ex hypothesi is contingent in itself, and its contrary doesn’t imply a contradiction. This ·second· kind of connection is based not purely on ideas and on God’s understanding alone, but also on his free decrees, and on the history of the universe. Let us take an example. Since Julius Caesar will become the permanent dictator and master of the Republic, and will overthrow the freedom of the Romans, these actions are comprised in his ·perfect or complete· notion; because we are assuming that it is the nature of such a perfect notion of a subject to include everything, so that the predicate can be contained in the subject. It could be put like this: it is not because of that notion or idea that Caesar will perform the action, since that notion applies to him only because God knows everything. You may object: ‘But his nature or form corresponds to that notion, and since God has imposed this character ·or nature or form· on him, from then on he must necessarily act in accordance with it.’ I could reply to that by bringing up the case of future contingents: they have as yet no reality except in God’s understanding and will, yet since God has given them that form in advance, they will nevertheless have to correspond to it. ·So I could counter-attack by challenging you to choose between two options, each of

7

Discourse on Metaphysics G. W. Leibniz

which you will find uncomfortable: either (1)·· say that future contingents are really necessary, and not contingent, or (2) say that God does not know them in advance·. But I prefer to •resolve difficulties rather than •excusing them by likening them to other similar ones; and what I am about to say will throw light on both of the above problems. Applying now the distinction between different kinds of connection, I say that whatever happens in accordance with its antecedents is assured but is not necessary; for someone to do the contrary ·of such an assured outcome· is not impossible in itself, although it is impossible ex hypothesi—·that is, impossible given what has gone before·. For if you were capable of carrying through the whole demonstration proving that this subject (Caesar) is connected with this predicate (his successful ·power-grabbing· enterprise), this would involve you in showing that Caesar’s dictatorship had its foundation in his notion or nature, that a reason can be found there—·in that notion or nature·—why he decided to cross the Rubicon rather than stop at it, and why he won rather than lost the day ·in the battle· at Pharsalus. ·You would be discovering· that it was rational and therefore assured that this would happen, but not that it is necessary in itself, or that the contrary implies a contradiction. (In a somewhat similar way it is rational and assured that God will always do the best, although ·the idea of his doing· what is less perfect implies no contradiction.) What you discovered would not be something whose contrary implies a contradiction because, as you would find, this ·supposed· demonstration of this predicate of Caesar’s is not as absolute as those of numbers or of geometry. It presupposes ·(you would find)· the course of events that God has freely chosen, and that is founded on (1) his primary free decision, which is always to do what is most perfect, and, on the basis of that, (2) his decision regarding human nature, namely that men will always (though freely) do what seems the best. Now, any truth which is founded on this sort of decision is contingent, even though it is certain, because •decisions have no effect whatsoever on the •possibility of things. And (to repeat myself) although God is sure always to choose the best, that doesn’t stop something less perfect from being and remaining possible in itself, even though it won’t happen—for what makes God reject it is its imperfection, not its being impossible ·which it is not·. And nothing is necessary if its opposite is possible. So we are well placed to resolve these kinds of difficulty, however great they may seem (and in fact they are equally serious for everyone else who has ever dealt with this matter). All we need is to bear in mind •that each such contingent proposition has reasons why it is so rather than otherwise—or (to put the same thing in other words), •that there is an a priori proof of its truth which makes it certain, and which shows that the connection of its subject with its predicate has its foundation in the nature of each; but •that this proof is not a demonstration of the proposition’s necessity, because those reasons ·for its truth· are based only on the principle of contingency or of the existence of things, that is, on what is or what appears the best among a number of equally possible things. Necessary truths, on the other hand, are based on the principle of contradiction, and on the possibility or impossibility of essences themselves, without any regard to the free will of God or of created things.

8

Discourse on Metaphysics G. W. Leibniz

Sections 14–23

14. Now that we have some grasp of what the nature of substances consists in, I should try to explain their dependence on one another, and the active and passive aspects of their goings-on. Well, firstly, it is very evident that created substances depend on God, who conserves them and indeed produces them continuously by a kind of emanation, just as we produce our thoughts. For God considers from every angle the general system of particular events that he has thought fit to produce in order to manifest his glory, turning it on all sides, so to speak. And as he considers all the faces of the world in all possible ways—for no aspect escapes his omniscience—each view of the universe, as though looked at from a certain viewpoint, results in a substance that expresses the universe in just that way, if God sees fit to actualize his thoughts by producing such a substance. And as God’s view is always correct, so too are our perceptions; where we go wrong is in our judgments, which are our own. I said above, and it follows from what I have said here, that each substance is like a separate world, independent of every other thing except God. So all our phenomena—all the events that occur in us—are simply consequences of our being [here = ‘of our nature’]. These events maintain a certain order in conformity with our nature, or with the world that is in us, so to speak, and this enables us to set up rules which we can use to guide our conduct, and which are justified by their fit with future events; so that often we can judge the future by the past without falling into error. That would give us a basis for saying that these phenomena are veridical [= ‘that they tell the truth’], without bothering about whether they are external to us, or whether others are aware of them too. Still, it emphatically is the case that the perceptions or expressions of all substances correspond with one another, in such a way that each one, by carefully following certain principles or laws that it has conformed to, finds itself in agreement with others which do the same—as when several people agree to meet together in some place on a certain day, and succeed in doing this. For them all to express the same phenomena their expressions don’t have to be perfectly alike; it is enough that they are correlated—just as a number of spectators think they are seeing the same thing, and do in fact understand each other, even though each one sees and speaks according to his point of view. Now it is God alone (from whom all individuals continuously emanate, and who sees the universe not only •as they do but also •completely differently from them all) who is the cause of this correspondence in their phenomena, and brings it about that what is particular to one is public to all. Without that there would be no connection between them. This gives us a basis for saying that no particular substance ever acts on or is acted on by another particular substance. The sense in which this is true is far removed from common usage, but it is good nevertheless. Bear in mind that what happens to each substance is a consequence of its idea or complete notion and of nothing else, because that idea already involves all the substance’s predicates or events, and expresses the whole universe. In reality nothing can happen to us except thoughts and perceptions, and all our future thoughts and perceptions are only the consequences—contingent ones—of our preceding thoughts and perceptions. So if I could command a clear view of everything that is happening or appearing to me right now, I would be able to see in it everything that will ever happen or appear to me. And it would not be prevented, and would still happen to me, even if everything outside of me were destroyed except for God. But when we have perceptions of a certain kind, we think that they come from outer things acting on us; and I want to look into what this belief

9

Discourse on Metaphysics G. W. Leibniz

is based on, and what truth there is in it.

15. I needn’t spend long on this. All I need just now is to reconcile what is said as a matter of metaphysics with what is said in everyday talk, which I do by saying that we rightly [or: reasonably] attribute to ourselves the phenomena that we express more perfectly, and attribute to other substances what each expresses best. So a substance that •expresses everything, ·as every substance does·, and is in that ·metaphorical· sense •infinitely extended, comes to be limited by the more or less perfect manner of its expression. This gives us a notion of how substances obstruct or limit one another; and consequently we can say that in this sense they act on one another, and are obliged to adjust themselves to one another, so to speak. ·What follows is the reason why this way of speaking, though not correct as a matter of strict and basic metaphysics, is nevertheless reasonable, or right in its own way·. It can happen that a change that raises the level of expression of one substance lowers that of another. Now, a particular substance has power in expressing well the glory of God, and in doing that it is less limited. And each thing, when it exercises its power, that is to say when it is active, changes for the better, and extends itself, in proportion to how active it is. So when a change occurs that affects several substances (and actually all changes touch them all), I believe we can ·properly· say that •one that immediately passes to a higher level of perfection or to a more perfect expression exercises its power and acts; and •one that passes to a lower level shows its weakness and is acted on. I hold also that every action of a substance that has perception signifies some pleasure, whereas every passivity [= ‘every instance of being-acted-on’] involves some sadness, and vice versa. It can easily happen, though, that a present advantage is destroyed by a greater evil later on; which is why we can sin when we are active or exerting our power and enjoying doing so.

16. My remaining task is to explain how it is possible that God should sometimes have influence on men or on other substances by an out-of-the-ordinary or miraculous concourse. [Leibniz’s word concours can mean co-operation, or (more weakly) going-along-with or permitting. He here ties it to influence (French), suggesting that in these cases God acts upon men and other substances, though that is not his considered view about what happens.] ·This question arises because· whatever happens to created substances is purely a consequence of their nature, which seems to imply that nothing extraordinary or miraculous can happen to them. Remember, though, what I said above about the place of miracles in the universe: that they always conform to the universal law of the general order, even though they over-ride subordinate rules ·and are in that sense out of the ordinary·. And since each person and each substance is like a little world that expresses the larger world, anything that happens within a substance belongs to the general order of the universe, which is indeed expressed by the essence or individual notion of that substance. Yet an extraordinary action by God on a single substance, though it does conform to the general order, can still be called miraculous. This is why if we include in our nature everything that it expresses, nothing is supernatural to it, because it extends to everything—because an effect always expresses its cause, and God is the true cause of substances. But the powers and the limits of our nature come (as I have just explained) from ·the facts about· what it expresses more perfectly; and for that reason what it expresses more perfectly belongs to it in a particular manner. Many things are beyond the powers of our nature, indeed of all limited natures. So in order to make this easier to grasp, I say that what marks off miracles and the extraordinary concourse of God is that they cannot be foreseen by the reasoning of any created mind, however

10

Discourse on Metaphysics G. W. Leibniz

enlightened, because no such mind can rise to having a clear view of the general order. On the other hand, everything that is called ‘natural’ depends on less general rules that created things can understand. In order, then, to have not only meanings but words that are above reproach, it would be good if we linked certain modes of speech with certain thoughts ·in the following way·. We can use ‘our essence’ to stand for something including •all that we express ·however imperfectly; and in that sense·, our essence has no limits, and can rise to anything, because it expresses our union with God himself. We can use ‘our nature’ or ‘our power’ to designate what is limited in us, ·that is, to designate •the more-perfectly-expressed fragment of all we express·; and anything that surpasses the nature ·or power·—in this sense—of any created substance is supernatural.

17. Having several times mentioned subordinate rules, or laws of Nature, I think it would be good to give an example. Our new philosophers standardly employ the famous rule that God always conserves the same quantity of motion in the world. This is indeed most plausible, and in days gone by I thought it to be beyond doubt. But I have since realised where the mistake lies. It is that Descartes and many other able mathematicians have believed that •the quantity of motion (i.e. the speed at which a thing moves) multiplied by •its size exactly equals •the moving force ·that it exerts·; or, geometrically speaking, that forces are directly proportional to speeds and bodies. Now it is rational that the same force should always be conserved in the universe. ·Here are reasons for the two halves of that thesis. As regards the addition of force·: Looking carefully at the observable facts, we can clearly see that perpetual mechanical motion doesn’t occur; because if it did the force of a machine, which is always slightly lessened by friction and so must soon come to an end, would be restored, and consequently would increase of itself without any input from outside. ·As regards the loss of force·: We also observe that a body’s force is lessened only to the extent that it gives some of it to adjacent bodies, or to its own parts in so far as they have their own independent motion. ·So the new philosophers were right about the conservation of force. Where they went wrong was in this·: they thought that what can be said of •force could also be said of •quantity of motion. I am now going to show the difference between force and quantity of motion. In doing this I shall make an assumption: that a body falling from a certain height gains enough force to rise back up again, if its direction carries it that way, unless it is prevented. For example, a pendulum would return exactly to its starting position unless the resistance of the air and other little obstacles didn’t slightly lessen the force it had acquired. I shall also make this assumption: that as much force is necessary to raise a one-pound body A to the height of four fathoms, as to raise a four-pound body B to the height of one fathom. All this is accepted by our new philosophers. It is clear, then, that body A, having fallen four fathoms, has acquired exactly as much force as has body B that has fallen one fathom. For body B, when it has completed its fall, has the force needed to climb back up to the start (by the first assumption), and so has the force to carry a four-pound body (its own body, that is) to the height of one fathom; and, similarly, the body A, when it has completed its fall, has the force needed to climb back to its start, and so has the force to carry a one-pound body (its own body, that is) to the height of four fathoms. Therefore (by the second assumption) the forces of these two bodies are equal. Let us now see whether the quantities of motion are the same on the one side as on the other. Here they will be surprised to find that there is a very great difference. For Galileo has demonstrated that the speed acquired in A’s fall is double the speed acquired in B’s,

11

Discourse on Metaphysics G. W. Leibniz

although the height is quadruple. So let us multiply body A (= 1) by its speed (= 2), and the resultant quantity of motion = 2. On the other hand, multiply the body B (= 4) by its speed (= 1), and the resultant quantity of motion = 4. Therefore the quantity of motion of body A at the end of its fall is half that of body B at the end of its fall, yet their forces are equal. So quantity of motion is clearly different from force, QED. This shows how force should be calculated from the size of the effect it can produce—for example by the height to which a heavy body of a particular size and type can be raised, which is very different from the speed it can reach. To double the speed you must more than double the force. Nothing is simpler than this proof. M. Descartes got this wrong through putting too much trust in his thoughts, even when they were not properly mature. But I am amazed that his followers have not since recognised this mistake. They are, I’m afraid, starting to resemble some of the Aristotelians whom they mock, getting into their habit of consulting their master’s books rather than reason and Nature.

18. This point about how force differs from quantity of motion is of some importance, not only (1) in physics and in mechanics for discovering the true laws of Nature and rules of motion, and indeed for correcting some practical errors that have glided into the writings of certain able mathematicians, but also (2) in metaphysics for understanding its principles better. ·What follows illustrates point (2)·. Motion, if one considers only what it strictly consists in just in itself (namely, change of place), is not an entirely real thing; when several bodies change their relative positions, those changes in themselves do not settle which of the bodies should be said to have moved and which to have remained at rest. (I could show this geometrically, if I were willing to interrupt myself to do so.) But the force or immediate cause behind those changes has more reality to it; and there is an adequate basis for ascribing it to one body rather than to another, that being our only way to know to which body the motion mainly belongs. Now, this force is something different from size, shape, and motion, and this shows us that—contrary to what our moderns have talked themselves into believing—not everything that we can conceive in bodies is a matter of extension and its modifications. So here again we have to reintroduce certain beings or ‘forms’ that the moderns have banished. And it becomes more and more apparent that although all particular natural events can be explained mathematically or mechanically by those who understand them, the general principles of corporeal nature and even ·the somewhat less general principles· of mechanics belong to metaphysics rather than to geometry, and have to do with certain indivisible forms or natures, as the causes of appearances, rather than with corporeal or extended mass. This line of thought could reconcile the mechanical philosophy of the moderns with the caution of some intelligent and well-intentioned people who fear, with some reason, that we might be endangering piety by moving too far away from immaterial beings. ·In case that remark is too compressed, I shall now—down to the end of this section—amplify it. On the one hand, my position enables us to agree with the moderns that in scientifically explaining physical events we can proceed as though we were materialists, appealing to nothing but material bodies and their properties. On the other hand, we are saved from outright materialism (and thus from the risk of sliding into atheism, which materialism brings with it), by my views about what is needed to complete the physics of bodies. (1) I hold that the laws governing the behaviour of bodies involve a concept of force that cannot be extracted from the concept of body; so it is sheerly additional to anything the materialists are comfortable with; and it points in the direction of immaterial beings as what might contain or

12

Discourse on Metaphysics G. W. Leibniz

exert the forces. (2) I hold that after we have established all the laws of matter, there remains the question ‘Why are these the laws of matter?’, and that the only tenable answer is ‘Because God chose that they should be’·.

19. As I don’t like to judge people harshly, I shan’t make accusations against our new philosophers who claim to expel final causes from physics; but still I can’t deny that the consequences of this view seem to me dangerous. [The final cause of an event is what it was for, what goal it was aimed at, what intention it was done with. Its efficient cause is what makes it happen, causing it from behind, as it were. A tidal wave might have as its efficient cause an under-sea earthquake; and if it had a final cause, it might be to punish the people in a sinful coastal city.] It is especially dangerous when it is combined with the view I refuted in section 2 of this Discourse, which seems to go as far as to eliminate purposes altogether—·from theology as well as from physics·—as if God acted without intending or aiming at any end or good! Against this, I hold that it is to final causes that we should look for the principle [= ‘ultimate explanation’] of all existent things and of the laws of Nature, because God always aims at the best and the most perfect. I freely admit that we may go wrong in trying to work out what God’s ends or purposes are; but that happens only when we want to limit them to some particular design, thinking he had only some single thing in view, whereas in fact he takes account of everything all at once. So for example it is a great mistake to think that God made the world only for us, although it is true that he did make it—all of it—for us, and that there is nothing in the universe that does not touch us [Leibniz uses the same verb here as when saying in section 15 that all changes ‘touch’ all substances], and which is not also adjusted to fit the concern he has for us, in accordance with the principles laid down above. So when we see some good effect or some perfection that happens or follows from the works of God, we can safely say that God intended it. We sometimes fail to act well, but not God: he doesn’t do things by accident. This is why, far from risking exaggeration in this—like political observers who go to absurd lengths in attributing subtlety to the designs of princes, or like literary commentators who look for too much learning in their author—one could never over-state the complexity of thought that this infinite wisdom involves. On no subject do we run less risk of error, so long as we only make affirmations, and avoid negative propositions that limit the designs of God. Everyone who sees the admirable structure of animals is led to recognise the wisdom of the creator of things; and I advise those who have any feelings of piety, and indeed of true philosophy, to avoid saying—as do certain self-proclaimed free-thinkers—that we see because we happen to have eyes, but not that the eyes were made for seeing. If one seriously maintains these views that hand everything over to the necessity of matter or to some kind of chance (although each of these must seem ridiculous to those who understand what I have explained above), one will have trouble recognising an intelligent author of Nature. For an effect must correspond to its cause; indeed, the best way to know an effect is through its cause. If you introduce a supreme intelligence as the organiser of things, it doesn’t make sense to go on to explain events purely in terms of the properties of matter, without bringing in the organizing intelligence. It would be as though, in explaining a great prince’s victory in a successful siege, a historian were to say:

It was because the small particles of gunpowder, released by the touch of a spark, shot off fast enough to impel a hard, heavy body against the walls of the place, while the particles making up the strands of copper in the cannon were so densely interwoven that they were not pulled apart by that speed;

13

Discourse on Metaphysics G. W. Leibniz

instead of showing how the conqueror’s foresight made him choose the appropriate time and means, and how his power overcame all obstacles.

20. This reminds me of a beautiful passage by Socrates in Plato’s Phaedo, which agrees splendidly with my views on this point, and seems to have been aimed straight at our over-materialist philosophers. This agreement made me want to translate it, although it is a little long. Perhaps this sample will stimulate someone to make available to us many other beautiful and solid thoughts to be found in the writings of this famous author. [At this point there is a gap in Leibniz’s manuscript, into which, he wrote, ‘The passage from Plato’s Phaedo where Socrates ridicules Anaxagoras, who introduces mind but does not make use of it, is to be inserted.’ He had included an abridged version of that passage in another of his writings a few years earlier. That version constitutes the remainder of the present section.]

START OF QUOTATION FROM PHAEDO

[It is Socrates who speaks.] I once heard someone reading from a book that he said was by Anaxagoras, containing these words: ‘All things were caused by an intelligent being that set them out and embellished them.’ This pleased me greatly, for I believed that if the world was caused by an intelligence, everything would be made in the most perfect possible manner. That is why I believed that someone wanting to explain why things are produced, and why they perish or survive, should search for what would be most suitable to each thing’s perfection. So such a person would only have to consider, in ·the thing he was studying, whether· himself or in something else, what would be the best or most perfect. For someone who knew what was most perfect would also know what would be imperfect, for the knowledge of either is knowledge of the other. Considering all this, I rejoiced at having found an authority who could teach me the reasons for things: for example, whether the earth is spherical or flat, and why it is better that it should be one way rather than the other. I expected also that in the course of saying whether or not the earth is at the centre of the universe, he would explain to me why its position is the most suitable for it to have. And that he would tell me similar things about the sun, the moon, the stars, and their movements. And finally that after having told me what would be best for each thing in particular, he would show what would be best over-all. Filled with this hope, I lost no time in acquiring Anaxagoras’s books and whipping through them; but I found nothing like what I had been reckoning on: to my surprise, I found him making no use of ·the idea of· the governing intelligence that he had put forward, that he had nothing more to say about the embellishments and the perfection of things, and that he brought in an implausible ·notion of· ether. It’s as though someone were to say at the outset that Socrates acts with intelligence, and then move on to explaining the particular causes of Socrates’s actions thus: Socrates is seated here because he has a body composed of bone, flesh and sinews, the bones are solid but they are separated at joints, the sinews can be stretched or relaxed—all that is why the body is flexible, and, rounding out the explanation, why I am sitting here. Or as though someone, wanting to explain our present conversation, appealed to the air, and to the organs of speech and hearing and such things, forgetting the real causes, namely that the Athenians thought it better to condemn than to acquit me, and that I thought it better to remain here than to escape. If I had not had that thought—if I had not found it more just and honourable to suffer the penalty my country chooses to impose than to live as a vagabond in exile—I swear these sinews and bones would long ago have put themselves among the Boeotians and Megarans! That is why it unreasonable to call these bones and sinews causes. Someone might say that

14

Discourse on Metaphysics G. W. Leibniz

without bones and sinews I could not do what I do, and he would be right; but the true cause is different from a mere condition without which the cause could not be a cause. Some people offer as their whole explanation of what holds the earth in its place the movements of bodies surrounding it; they forget that divine power sets everything out in the most beautiful manner, and do not understand that the right and the beautiful join forces to form and maintain the world.

END OF QUOTATION FROM PHAEDO

21. Well now, since God’s wisdom has always been recognised in the detail of the physical structure of certain bodies, ·especially animals and plants·, it must also be shown display itself in the general economy of the world and in the constitution of the laws of Nature. That is so true that this wisdom can be seen in the general laws of motion. Here is how. If there were nothing to a body but extended mass, and motion were only change of place, and if everything should and could be deduced with geometrical necessity from those definitions alone, it would follow (as I have shown elsewhere) that a tiny body upon bumping into an enormous stationary body would give it the same speed as it itself had, without losing any of its own. And a number of other rules which, like this one, are completely contrary to the formation of a system, would have to be admitted. But a system is provided by the decision of the divine wisdom to conserve always the same total force and direction. I even find that some natural effects can be demonstrated twice over, first through efficient causes, and then through final causes—for example by bringing in God’s decision to produce his effect always in the easiest and the most determinate ways. I have shown this elsewhere, in explaining the rules of reflection and refraction of light, about which I shall say more presently.

22. It is good to point this out, in order to reconcile •those who hope to explain mechanically how the parts of an animal are initially inter-woven and what machine they compose, with •those who explain that same structure through final causes. Both are good, both can be useful, not only for admiring the great workman’s ingenuity but also for making useful discoveries in physics and medicine. Authors who go these different ways ought not to heap abuse on each other ·as they sometimes do·. For I see that those who focus on explaining the beauty of divine anatomy make fun of others who think that such a beautiful variety of organs could have come from a seemingly chance motion of certain fluids; they call such people rash and profane. The latter, on the other hand, call the others simple and superstitious, and liken them to the ancients who accused of impiety the physical scientists who maintained that thunder is produced not by Jupiter but by some kind of matter in the clouds. It would be best to combine the two approaches, because—if I may use a down-to-earth example—I recognise and praise a workman’s skill not only by showing what designs he had in making the parts of his machine, but also by explaining the tools he used to make each part, especially when those tools are simple and cleverly devised. God is such a skillful worker that he could produce a machine a thousand times more ingenious than those of our bodies, using only various quite simple fluids that were devised so that ordinary laws of Nature were all it took to arrange them in the right way to produce such an admirable effect; but that doesn’t alter the fact that none of this would happen if God were not the author of Nature. Explanations in terms of efficient causes are deeper and in some way more immediate and more a priori [here = ‘more truly explanatory’], but for the details of events such explanations are hard to come by, and I believe that our scientists usually fall far short of achieving them. By contrast, the way of final causes is easier, despite which it often enables us to conjecture important and useful truths, truths that

15

Discourse on Metaphysics G. W. Leibniz

the other more physical route—·that is, the way of efficient causes·—would have taken ages to reach. Anatomy provides substantial examples of this. I also think that Snell, who first formulated of the rules of refraction, would have been a long time finding them if he had tried to come at them first by ·way of efficient causes, which would put him in need of· discovering how light is formed. Instead of that, he seems to have followed the method the ancients used for reflection ·of light·, which is in fact that of final causes. They looked for the easiest way to get a ray of light from one point to another by reflection in a given plane (assuming that this is the way Nature was designed), and this led them to the discovery that the angle of incidence always equals the angle of reflection. Snell, I think, more ingeniously applied this to refraction. [Leibniz here gives an extremely cryptic and unclear statement of what Snell discovered about how light is bent when it passes from one medium to another, e.g. from air to water; and he says that it implies that light always follows the easiest or anyway the most determinate route from a given point in one medium to a given point in another. He is taking it for granted that the concepts of easiest and most determinate somehow involve final causes.] (Fermat came at the matter in the same way, though without knowing of Snell’s work.) Descartes tried to demonstrate this same theorem in terms of efficient causes, but his demonstration is nowhere near as good; and there is room to suspect that he would never have found the theorem by his method if he had not been told in Holland of Snell’s discovery ·through final causes·.

23. I have thought it appropriate to emphasize a little the relevance to bodies of •final causes, •incorporeal natures and an •intelligent cause, so as to show that these have a role even in physical science and mathematics. I have wanted to do this because it may (on the one hand) clear contemporary physics of the charge of impiety that has been levelled at it, and (on the other) raise the minds of our philosophers from purely material considerations to thoughts of a nobler kind. Now it is appropriate to return from bodies to immaterial natures, and in particular to minds; and to say something about the means that God employs to enlighten them and to act on them. There is no doubt that here too there are certain laws of Nature, which I will be able to discuss more fully elsewhere. Just now it will be enough to say a little about ideas [sections 23-7], about whether w··e see all things in God [section 29], and about how God is our light [section 28]. I should point out that many errors arise from the misuse of ideas. ·For example·, some ancient and modern philosophers have based a very imperfect proof of God on the natural assumption that when we reason about something we have an idea of it. The ‘proof’ goes like this:

(1) I can think about God, so

(2) I have an idea of him.

(3) This idea involves his having all perfections.

(4) Existence is one of the perfections.

Therefore

(5) God exists.

·The defect in this is its move from (1) to (2) 2·. We often think of impossible absurdities—for example of the highest speed, or of the largest number, or of [a certain geometrical impossibility]—and the ideas involved in such thinking are in a certain sense ‘false’, in contrast with ‘true’ ideas of things that are possible. So we can boast of having an idea—·that is, a ‘true’ idea·—of a thing only when we are assured of its possibility. So the above argument falls short. Still, it does at least prove that God necessarily exists if he is possible. ·That is a significant result, because it attributes to God something that is not true of other things·. It is indeed an excellent privilege of the divine nature to need only its possibility or essence in order actually to exist.

16

Discourse on Metaphysics G. W. Leibniz

Sections 24–37

24. To understand the nature of ideas better, I must say a little about the different kinds of knowledge. When I can pick a thing out from among others, but cannot say what marks it out from them, my knowledge of it is confused. In this way we sometimes know vividly, without being in any way in doubt, whether a poem or a painting is good or bad, because it has a certain je-ne-sais-quoi that pleases or displeases us. But when I can explain the criteria I am going by, my knowledge is clear. An assayer’s knowledge is ·clear· like this; he can distinguish true from false gold by means of certain tests or marks that make up the definition of gold. But the clearness of knowledge is a matter of degree, because the notions entering into the definition usually need to be defined in their turn, and are known only confusedly. But when everything that comes into a definition or an item of clear knowledge is known clearly, right down to the primary notions, I call that knowledge adequate. And when my mind takes in, clearly and at once, all the primary ingredients of a notion, it has intuitive knowledge of it. This is very rare; most human knowledge is only confused, or suppositive. [Leibniz’s use of his invented word suppositif in section 25 shows that his thought is this: an item of knowledge to which this term applies involves a notion or idea that one supposes to be firmly included in one’s conceptual repertoire; this contrasts with consciously bringing the idea to mind and seeing that one has it in one’s repertoire.] It is also worthwhile to distinguish nominal definitions from real ones: I call a definition ‘nominal’ when we can still doubt whether the notion defined is possible. [Leibniz gives a complex geometrical example.] This shows that any reciprocal property [= ‘any statement of necessary and sufficient conditions’] can serve as a nominal definition; but when the property shows the thing’s possibility, it makes a real definition. [The source of ‘nominal’ is the Latin nomen, ‘name’; the source of ‘real’ is the Latin res, ‘thing’. A nominal definition, Leibniz holds, tells you only about the meaning of a word, whereas a real definition informs you about the thing.] Now as long as we have only a nominal definition, we can’t be sure of the consequences that we draw from it, because if it conceals some contradiction or impossibility it could also have opposing consequences. This is why truths don’t depend on names, and are not arbitrary as some new philosophers have believed. A final point: real definitions differ considerably from one another. When possibility is proved only by experience, the definition is merely •real and nothing more—as with the definition of quicksilver, which we know to be possible because we have encountered a fluid that is an extremely heavy yet fairly volatile. But when the thing can be shown to be possible a priori—·that is, without help from experience·—as when the definition shows how the thing could be generated, then the definition is both real and •causal. And when a definition takes the analysis the whole way down to the primary notions, without assuming anything that itself requires an a priori proof of its possibility, the definition is •perfect, or •essential.

[In this section and elsewhere, ‘vivid’ translates the French clair, and ‘clear’ translates the French distinct. These are usually rendered as ‘clear’ and ‘distinct’ respectively, but the first of those is nearly always a flat mistranslation (though not in the second sentence of section 37). The French word clair primarily means ‘vivid’, ‘bright’, ‘strongly present to consciousness’, so that Descartes can say that one’s awareness of an intense pain is clair, and bright light is lumière claire—even if it is dazzling and in no way clear. That is why Leibniz can say in this section, as Descartes did before him, that something’s presence to the mind can be at once confused and vivid—not confused and clear! Once ‘clear’ has been freed from that misuse, it becomes available as a good translation for the French distinct.]

25. ·Let us get clear about suppositive knowledge·. When

17

Discourse on Metaphysics G. W. Leibniz

I think of a thousand, I often do so without contemplating the idea—as when I say that a thousand is ten times a hundred, without bothering to think what 10 and 100 are, because I suppose I know, and see no immediate need to stop to think about it. ·On those occasions, my thought that a thousand is ten times a hundred is suppositive·. In cases like that, I relate to the idea in the same way as I do in a thought in which there lurks an impossibility. Even if in a given case the relevant idea is all right, and doesn’t involve an impossibility, I cannot learn that this is so by suppositive thinking. So it easily can and quite often does happen that I am mistaken about a notion that I suppose or believe I understand when in fact it is impossible, or at least incompatible with the others to which I join it; and whether I am mistaken or not, this suppositive manner of conceiving is the same.

26. To get a good grip on what ideas are, be warned of an ambiguity. Some people take an idea to be a form or differentia [= ‘aspect or property’] of our thought; so that we have the idea in our mind only when we are thinking of it, and whenever we think of it again, we have different but similar ideas of the same thing. Others, however, seem to take an idea to be the immediate object of a thought, or to be some kind of permanent form, which continues to exist even when we are not contemplating it. ·I side with the latter group, and here is why·. Our soul always possesses the ability to represent to itself any nature or form when the occasion for thinking of it arises. ·This ability is permanent, even though the individual thoughts in which it is exercised come and go·. And I believe that this •ability of our soul, when it expresses some nature, form, or essence, is properly called an •idea of the thing; and it is in us—always in us—whether or not we are thinking of the thing. For our soul ·always· expresses God and the universe, and all essences as well as all existences. ·That requires our soul to have ideas of all those things at all times, which it can do only if ideas are abilities rather than individual mental or events or aspects or properties of such events·. This fits in with my principles, for nothing naturally enters our mind from outside; and it is a bad habit of ours to think of our soul as receiving messenger species, or as if it had doors and windows. We have all these forms in our mind and indeed always have had; because the mind always expresses all its future thoughts, and is already thinking confusedly of everything it will ever think clearly. We couldn’t be taught something unless we already had the idea of it in our mind, the idea being like the matter out of which the thought is formed. Plato understood this very well, when he put forward his doctrine of reminiscence. The latter is very sound, provided we take it in the right way—cleansing it of the error about pre-existence, and not imagining that if a soul takes in and thinks about something now it must at some earlier time have clearly known and thought about it. He also confirmed his opinion by a beautiful experiment. He introduces a small boy whom he gradually leads to ·an acceptance of· very difficult geometrical truths about incommensurables, without teaching him anything, only asking him an orderly sequence of suitable questions. This shows that our souls have virtual knowledge of all these things; that to grasp truths they need only to have their attention drawn to them; and thus that our souls at least have the ideas on which those truths depend. They might even be said to possess these truths, if we consider the truths as relations between ideas.

27. Aristotle preferred to compare our souls to as-yet blank tablets that could be written on, and he held that there is nothing in our understanding that doesn’t come from the senses. This squares better with everyday notions, as Aristotle usually does (unlike Plato, who goes deeper). Ordinary usage does sanction these doctrines or rules of

18

Discourse on Metaphysics G. W. Leibniz

thumb, in the spirit in which people who follow Copernicus still say that the sun ‘rises’ and ‘sets’. Indeed, I often find that we can give them a good sense in which they are ·not merely passable or excusable, but· entirely true; in the way in which (as I have already remarked ·in section 15·) it can truly be said that particular substances act on each other, and that we receive knowledge from outside by the agency of the senses, because some external things contain or express more particularly the reasons why our soul has certain thoughts. But when we are pursuing precise metaphysical truths, it is important to recognise how much our soul contains and how independent it is of other things. These—its ‘extent’ and its independence—go infinitely further than plain folk imagine, although in ordinary talk we attribute to the soul only what we are most plainly aware of, only what belongs to us in one special manner, because there is no point in going any further. Still, it would be good to choose specific terms for each way of talking, so as to avoid ambiguity. So those expressions that are in our soul whether conceived or not, can be called ‘ideas’; but those that are conceived or formed ·in a consciously self-aware manner· can be called ‘notions’, or ‘concepts’. But in whatever way we take the term ‘notion’, it is always false to say that all our notions come from the so-called external senses. For my notion of myself and of my thoughts, and therefore of being, substance, action, identity, and many others, come from an internal experience.

28. Now in strict metaphysical truth God is the only external cause that acts on us, and he alone affects us directly in virtue of our continual dependence. Therefore no other external object touches our soul and directly triggers our perceptions. So it is the continual action of God upon us that enables us to have in our souls ideas of all things. ·Here is how that happens·. All effects express their causes, and so the essence [= ‘intrinsic nature’] of our soul is a particular expression, imitation or likeness of God’s essence, thought and will, and of all the ideas contained in it. So we can say that God alone is our immediate external object, and that we see all things through him. When we see the sun and the stars, for example, it is God who gave us the relevant ideas and who conserves them in us; and who by his ordinary concurrence, following the laws he has established, brings it about that we actually think of them when our senses are suitably disposed. God is the sun and the light of souls, ‘the light which lighteth every man that cometh into this world’ [John 1:9]; and this is not a new opinion. In addition to holy scripture and the fathers, who have always been more for Plato than for Aristotle, I remember having sometimes noticed that many people in the time of the Scholastics held that God is the light of the soul, or, as they used to say, ‘the active intellect of the rational soul’. The Averroists twisted this the wrong way, but others have taken it in a manner worthy of God and capable of raising the soul to knowledge of its true good.

29. However, I don’t share the opinion of some able philosophers—·most notably Malebranche·—who seem to maintain that our ideas themselves are in God and not at all in us. In my view this comes from their having ·partly grasped but· not yet thought through the points I have just been making about substances and about the whole extent and independence of our soul—points which imply that the soul contains everything that happens to it, and expresses God (and with him all possible and actual beings) as an effect expresses its cause. Anyway, it is inconceivable that I should think with someone else’s ideas! Furthermore, when the soul thinks of something it must actually come to be in a certain state, and it must have contained in advance not only a completely determinate •passive power of coming

19

Discourse on Metaphysics G. W. Leibniz

to be in that state, but also an •active power in virtue of which its nature has always contained signs of the future production of this thought, and •dispositions to produce it when the time comes. And all this—·the passive power, the active power that includes the forward-looking signs, and the disposition·—has wrapped up in it the idea involved in the thought.

30. As regards God’s action on the human will, there are a number of quite difficult issues that it would be tedious to pursue here. Here in outline is what we can say. In his ordinary concourse with our actions, God merely follows the laws he has established; that is to say, he continually preserves and produces our being in such a way that our thoughts occur spontaneously and freely in the order laid down by the notion of our individual substance, in which they could be foreseen from all eternity. Furthermore, he determines our will to choose what appears ·to us· the best, yet without necessitating it. He does this by decreeing that our will shall always tend towards the apparent good, thus expressing or imitating the will of God to the extent that this apparent good has (as it always does have) some real good in it. ·I comment now on ‘without necessitating it’·. Absolutely speaking, our will is in a state of indifference, as opposed to necessity: it has the power to do otherwise, or to suspend its action altogether, each alternative being and remaining possible. It is therefore up to the soul to take precautions against being caught off its guard by events that come into its ken; and the way to do this is to resolve firmly to be reflective, and in certain situations not to act or judge without mature and thorough deliberation. It is true, however, and indeed it was settled from all eternity, that a particular soul will not employ this power ·to pause, reflect, deliberate· on some particular occasion. But whose fault is that? Does the soul have anyone to complain of except itself? Any complaint after the fact is unfair if it would have been unfair before. But would it have been decent for this soul, just before sinning, to complain against God as if he were determining it to sin? What God determines in these matters cannot be foreseen, so how could a soul know that it was determined to sin unless it was already doing so? It is simply a matter of not choosing to; and God couldn’t have set an easier or fairer condition than that; and accordingly judges do not look for the reasons that led a man to have an evil intent, but concern themselves only with how evil it is. ‘But perhaps it is certain from all eternity that I shall sin?’ Answer that yourself: perhaps not! And instead of dreaming on about what you can’t know and can’t learn from, act according to your duty, which you do know. ‘But how does it happen that this man will certainly sin?’ The reply is easy: it is that otherwise it wouldn’t be this man. [Notice: He doesn’t say ‘he wouldn’t be this man’, which is how most translations have put it.] For God sees from all time that there will be a certain Judas whose notion or idea, which God has, contains that future free action. That leaves only the question of why such a Judas, the traitor, who in God’s idea is merely possible, actually exists. But no reply to that question is to be expected here on this earth, except that in general we should say: Since God found it good that Judas should exist, despite the sin that he foresaw, this evil must be repaid with interest somewhere in the universe; God will extract some greater good from it; and the bottom line is that this course of events—·the actual one· that includes the existence of this sinner—will turn out to be the most perfect out of all the possible ways things could have gone. But while we are journeying through this world we can’t always •explain the admirable economy of that choice; we must settle for •knowing it without •understanding it. And at this point it is time to acknowledge the richness and unfathomable depth of the divine wisdom, and not to look for a detailed

20

Discourse on Metaphysics G. W. Leibniz

account of it—an account that would be infinitely complex. It is quite clear, though, that God is not the cause of evil. Man’s soul been possessed by original sin ever since he lost his innocence, but ·that was not the start of it·. Even before that, all created things—·just because they were created·—were intrinsically limited or imperfect in a way that makes them capable of sin and of error. St. Augustine and others have held that the root of evil lies in •nothingness, and I think that this should be taken as saying what I have just said: namely, that evil comes from the •lacks and limits of created things, which God graciously remedies by the degree of perfection that he is pleased to give. This grace of God in both its ordinary and its extraordinary versions [see sections 6 and 16] varies in how deep and wide it goes. ·But· it is always enough not only to save a man from sin but also to secure his salvation, as long as he uses his own resources to combine himself with that grace. It is not always sufficient to overcome a man’s inclinations; if it were, ·his inclinations would have no effect on anything, and· he would no longer be responsible for anything. That kind of sufficiency belongs only to absolutely effective grace, which is always victorious, whether through itself or through the combination of circumstances.

31. Finally, God’s graces are purely gifts, and creatures have no claim on them. We can’t fully explain how God chooses to distribute them by appealing to his foreknowledge (whether absolute or conditional) of how men are going to act in the future; but we mustn’t think of them as absolute ·or arbitrary· decrees for which there are no rational grounds. As for God’s foreknowledge of our faith or good works: it is quite true that God has chosen only those whose faith and charity he foresaw, foreseeing that he would endow them with faith. But the old question comes up again: Why will God make a gift of faith or of good works to some people and not to others? ·A difficulty about this arises from the fact that grace is effective in a man only to the extent that he brings something of himself to it·. Although to act well a man needs to be stimulated to the good, and converted, he must also then do it ·by means of his own resources·, and men vary in what their inner resources are, corresponding to how they vary in what grace is given them. So included in God’s knowledge is not only his foresight of faith and of good deeds, but also his foresight of what a man himself will contribute towards them—his natural dispositions in that direction. It seems to many thinkers that we could say this: God sees what a man·’s natural dispositions will be, and thus what he· would do without grace or extraordinary assistance, or at least what he will contribute from his own side in addition to anything that may be contributed by grace. So God could have decided to give grace to those whose natural dispositions were the best, or at any rate were the least imperfect or sinful. But if that were so, those natural dispositions, to the extent that they are good, are also the effect of grace (ordinary grace, this time), because ·in this respect too· God has favoured some people more than others. Now, since according to this doctrine, God knows perfectly well that the natural advantages he gives will be the ground for his grace or extraordinary help, doesn’t everything in the end depend on his mercy? Well, we don’t know how or how much God takes account of natural dispositions in his dispensing of grace. So I think that the most exact and the safest thing to say is what is dictated by my principles (and I have already said it once), namely: Among possible beings there must be the person of Peter or of John whose notion or idea contains this whole sequence of ordinary and extraordinary graces, and all the rest of these events with their circumstances; and from amongst an infinity of other equally possible people it pleased God to choose that person for actual existence. After

21

Discourse on Metaphysics G. W. Leibniz

this it seems that there is nothing more to ask, and that all the difficulties disappear. For as to this single great question why it pleased God to choose this person from among all other possible persons, it would be very unreasonable not to be satisfied with the general reasons I have given, the details being beyond us. So, instead of having recourse to •an absolute ·and arbitrary· decree that is unreasonable because there are no reasons for it, or to •reasons that fail to resolve the difficulty because they need reasons in their turn, it would be best to say in agreement with St. Paul that there are •certain great reasons for God’s choices, reasons of wisdom or of fitness that are unknown to mortals; God has conformed to these reasons, which are founded on the general order whose aim is the greatest perfection of the universe. The themes of this Discourse—the glory of God and the manifestation of his justice, his mercy and his perfections generally, and finally the immense profundity of riches that enraptured the soul of St. Paul—all come down to that in the end.

32. I have to add only that the thoughts I have just been explaining—and in particular the great principle of

•the perfection of God’s operations, and that of

•the notion of a substance containing all its events with all their circumstances

- so far from harming religion, serve to reinforce it. They blow away some very serious difficulties, inspire souls with love of God, and elevate minds to the understanding of incorporeal substances—doing all this far better than did any previous theories. For it is quite clear that all other substances depend on God, as thoughts emanate from our substance ·and in that way depend on it·; that God is all in all, and is intimately united to all created things in proportion to how perfect they are; that he alone by his influence determines them from outside. ·Elaborating this last point·: If to act on something is to affect it immediately ·i.e. directly·—which is correct in the ·strict· language of metaphysics—it can be said that in this sense only God acts on me and can do me good or harm. Other substances ·cannot, strictly speaking, help or harm me, because they· contribute only to ·God’s· reason for ·making· those changes. ·The other substances do come into those reasons·, because God takes account of all substances when he shares out his blessings and makes them adjust to one another. So it is he alone who produces the connection or communication [= something like ‘interplay’] among substances: he brings it about that the states of one coincide or agree with those of another, and as a result that one substance can correctly perceive what state another is in. But we needn’t always mention the universal cause in particular cases; and in common parlance the items that we say ‘act on’ a given substance ·putting it into a certain state· are the ones that enter into God’s reasons ·for putting it into that state·, in the sense that I explained above. We can also see that every substance has a perfect spontaneity, that everything that happens to it is a consequence of its •idea or of its •nature. and that nothing affects it from outside except God alone. (In substances with intellect, this spontaneity becomes freedom.) This is why a certain person of very lofty mind and revered holiness used to say that the soul should often think as though there were only God and it in the world. [Garber says that this probably refers to St. Theresa.] Nothing can make us understand immortality better than this independence and extent of the soul, which absolutely shelters it from everything external, since it alone constitutes its whole world, and together with God is sufficient for itself. It is possible for the soul to come to an end through absolute annihilation; but its coming to end in any other way—·being destroyed by dissolution, through damage, like a machine·—is just as impossible as it is that the world should destroy

22

Discourse on Metaphysics G. W. Leibniz

itself unaided. Changes in the extended mass we call our body could not have any effect on the soul, nor could the dissolution of that body destroy what is indivisible, ·namely, the soul·.

33. We also see how to clear up that great mystery of the union of the soul and the body: how does it come about that the passive and active states [or: the undergoings and doings] of the one are accompanied by active and passive states—or anyway by corresponding states—in the other? ·This is a mystery because· it is utterly inconceivable that the one should influence the other, and it is not reasonable to fall back on the extraordinary operation of the universal cause—·God·—to explain normal everyday events. Here, however, is the true explanation ·of those events·. I have said that whatever takes place in the soul or in any substance is a consequence of its notion, so that the mere idea or essence of the soul carries with it ·the requirement· that all the soul’s states or perceptions must arise spontaneously from its own nature. And they must do this in just such a way that they correspond, unaided, to whatever happens in the whole universe,

but more particularly and more perfectly to what happens in the body that is assigned to the soul in question. That is because, in a way and for a time, the soul expresses the state of the universe through the relation of other bodies to its own.

This also tells us how our body belongs to us without being attached to our essence. And I believe that people who know how to think long and hard will favour my principles for just that reason: that they will be able easily to see what the connection between soul and body consists in, a connection that seems otherwise to be inexplicable. We can also see that the perceptions of our senses, even when they are vivid, must necessarily contain some confused feeling. For since all the bodies in the universe are in sympathy [= ‘harmony’, ‘correspondence’], our body receives the impressions of all the others, and although our senses •are related to everything, our soul cannot possibly •attend to each particular thing. Thus our confused feelings result from a downright infinite jumble of perceptions. In somewhat the same way the confused murmur that people hear when nearing the sea shore comes from the putting together of the reverberations of countless waves. For if several perceptions don’t fit together so as to make one, and no one of them stands out above the rest, and the impressions they make are all just about equally strong and equally capable of catching the soul’s attention, it can perceive them only confusedly.

34. ·In this section I use the notion of unum per se, a Latin phrase meaning ‘a unity through itself’. This applies to anything whose intrinsic nature makes it one, single, an individual, as distinct from something that is not inherently one though it may suit us to treat it as one. Each organism is a unum per se; a pile of leaves or a gallon of water is not·. If we suppose that bodies that compose a unum per se, such as ·the body of· a man, are substances and that they have substantial forms, and that lower animals have souls, we must acknowledge that these souls and substantial forms cannot completely come to an end, any more than, in the view of other philosophers, atoms or the ultimate parts of matter can come to an end. For no substance ever comes to an end, though a substance may greatly alter. These ·souls or substantial forms of lower animals· also express the whole universe, although more imperfectly than minds do. But the principal difference ·between them and minds· is that they don’t know what they are or what they do, and so—not being able to look into themselves reflectively—they can’t discover necessary and universal truths. ·That is because the way to discover necessary truths is to look into oneself and see how

23

Discourse on Metaphysics G. W. Leibniz

one’s ideas are inter-related·. For lack of such self-reflection, they have no moral quality; which means that as they pass through hundreds of transformations (as when a caterpillar changes into a butterfly), it would make no moral or practical difference if we said that they cease to exist. We can even say that they really do cease to exist, as when we say that bodies perish through dissolution. But the thinking soul, which knows what it is and can say that pregnant word ‘I’, not only (as a matter of metaphysics) is much more enduring than the others, but also (as a matter of morals) endures and constitutes the same person. For it is memory, or the knowledge of this I, which makes the thinking soul capable of punishment and reward. Similarly, the immortality required by morality and religion doesn’t consist merely in the lasting-for-ever that all substances have, for that would not be something to hope for if it didn’t involve the memory of what one has been. Suppose that someone could suddenly become the King of China, but only on condition of forgetting what he had been, as if he had just been born all over again. Would it not in practice, or in terms of perceivable effects, be the same as if he had been annihilated and a King of China created then and there? And that is something that that individual could have no reason to want.

35. ·In those remarks I have been separating morality from metaphysics; but in some contexts we must run the two in a single harness·. To show by natural reasons that God will preserve for ever not only our substance, but also our person (that is, the memory and the knowledge of what we are—although clear knowledge of this is sometimes suspended in sleep or in fainting spells), we must unite morality with metaphysics. That is, we must think of God not only as the •root cause of all substances and of all beings, but also as the •leader of all persons or thinking substances, or as the absolute monarch of the most perfect city or republic—which is what the universe composed of the assembled totality of minds is. For God himself is the most accomplished of all minds, as he is also the greatest of all beings. For minds certainly are the most perfect of beings, and express God best. If bodies are only true phenomena—·that is, reliable appearances to minds·—then minds are the only substances there are; and if they are not that, they are at any rate the most perfect. And since—as I have sufficiently explained—the expressing of God and the universe is the whole nature, goal, virtue or function of substances, there is no room to doubt that substances that do this knowing what they are doing, and able to understand great truths about God and the universe, express them incomparably better than the natures that belong to lower animals and are incapable of knowing any truths, or—·lower down still·—to things that lack feeling and knowledge altogether. The difference between substances that think and ones that don’t is as great as that between a mirror and someone who sees. God can have conversations (so to speak) with minds, and can even enter into society with them by telling them what he thinks and wants—doing this in a special way that lets them know and love their benefactor. Since he himself is the greatest and wisest of minds, it is natural to think that minds—thinking substances—must concern God infinitely more than all other things, which can serve only as the tools of minds. Similarly, we see that wise folk always value a man infinitely more than any other thing, however precious it may be; and it seems that the greatest satisfaction an otherwise contented soul can have is to see itself loved by others. Between our love for one another and our love for God, however, there is a difference. His glory and our worship could not add to his satisfaction, because his sovereign and perfect happiness leads to the knowledge that created things have, and so cannot be partly caused by that knowledge. However, whatever

24

Discourse on Metaphysics G. W. Leibniz

is good and rational in finite spirits is also possessed by God in a suitably higher form; and just as we would praise a king who preferred to save the life of a man rather than of the most precious and rarest of his animals, so we should not doubt that the most enlightened and just of all monarchs would think the same.

36. Minds are actually the most perfectible of substances, and their perfections have the special feature that they obstruct one another the least, or rather that they help one another—for only the most virtuous could be the most perfect friends. From which it plainly follows that God, who always aims at the greatest perfection in general, will have the greatest care for minds, and will give to them (not only in general, but also to each particular mind) the highest level of perfection that the universal harmony will allow. It can be said indeed that God’s being a mind is what qualifies him as the reason why things exist. If he couldn’t voluntarily choose the best, there would be no reason why one possible thing should exist rather than some other. So of all the features of created things that God takes into account, he attends first and foremost to the quality ·that he shares with them, namely that· of being a Mind. [In this section, mind/Mind tracks Leibniz’s esprit/Esprit.] Only minds are made in his image, are of his race (so to speak), are like children of his house, for only they can serve him freely, and act in imitation of the divine nature, knowing what they are doing. A single mind is worth a whole world, since it not only expresses the world, but also knows it, and governs itself there after the fashion of God. Thus, it seems that although each substance expresses the entire universe, Minds express God rather than the world, whereas other substances express the world rather than God. And this nobility in the nature of Minds—bringing them as near to divinity as is possible for mere created things—leads to God’s deriving infinitely more glory from them than from any other beings. That is why this moral quality of God’s, which makes him the lord or King of Minds, is one in which he takes a quite special interest—an interest that might be called personal. It is in this that he humanizes himself, willingly lays himself open to being thought of in anthropomorphic ways, and enters into society with us as a prince does with his subjects. This concern is so dear to him that the happy and flourishing state of his empire, which consists in the greatest possible happiness of the inhabitants, becomes the highest of his laws. For happiness is to people what perfection is to beings ·in general·. And if the ultimate explanation of the existence of the real world is the decree that it should have the greatest perfection that it can, then the ultimate aim for the moral world—the city of God, the noblest part of the universe—should be to infuse it with the greatest possible happiness. So we mustn’t doubt that God—in order that his city should never lose any person, as the world never loses any substance—has arranged everything so that Minds not only (of course) can live for ever, but also retain for ever their moral quality. Consequently they will always know what they are; otherwise they wouldn’t be liable for reward or punishment, which are essential to any republic, and especially to the most perfect one, where nothing could be neglected. In fact since God is at once the most fair and mild of kings, and since he demands of his subjects only a good will, provided it is sincere and serious, they couldn’t wish for a better condition. To make them perfectly happy, God asks only that they love him.

37. Ancient philosophers knew very little of these important truths. Only Jesus Christ expressed them divinely well, and in such a clear and down-to-earth way that even the dullest minds could understand them. Thus his gospel has entirely changed the face of human affairs. He has told us

25

Discourse on Metaphysics G. W. Leibniz

about the kingdom of heaven, that perfect republic of Minds meriting the title ‘City of God’, whose admirable laws he has revealed to us. He alone has shown how much God loves us, and how exactly he has provided for everything that affects us: •that, caring for sparrows, he will not neglect the rational creatures who are infinitely dearer to him; •that all the hairs of our heads are counted; •that the sky and the earth will perish before any change in the word of God or in any of the conditions for our salvation; •that God cares more about the least of thinking souls than about the whole machine of the world; •that we need not fear those who can destroy bodies but could not harm souls, because God alone can make souls happy or unhappy; •that the souls of the just are, in his hands, safe from all the revolutions of the universe, since nothing can act on them except God alone; •that none of our actions is forgotten; •that everything is taken into account, even an idle remark or a well used spoonful of water; and, finally, •that all must result in the greatest well-being for good people, that the righteous shall be like suns, and that we have never experienced or conceived anything giving us a fore-taste of the happiness that God prepares for those who love him.

26

Discourse on Metaphysics G. W. Leibniz

Leibniz’s summaries

1. God is perfect, and does everything in the most desirable way.

2. Against those who maintain that there is no goodness in God’s works, and that the rules of goodness and beauty are arbitrary.

3. Against those who think that God could have done better.

4. The love of God requires complete contentment and acceptance with regard to what he has done, but we don’t have to be quietists.

5. What the rules of perfection of God’s conduct consist in; the simplicity of means is balanced against the richness of ends.

6. God does nothing disorderly, and it isn’t possible even to feign events that are not regular.

7. Miracles conform to the general order, although they run counter to subordinate rules. What God wants and what he allows; general and particular will.

8. In order to distinguish between God’s actions and those of created things, it is explained what the notion of an individual substance consists in.

9. Each substance expresses the whole universe in its own way; and everything that happens to it is included in its notion, with all the circumstances and ·because it expresses everything else· the whole series of external things.

10. The doctrine of substantial forms has some value, but such forms make no difference to observable events, and shouldn’t be used to explain particular effects.

11. The reflections of the so-called Scholastic theologians and philosophers should not be completely despised.

12. The notions that make up extension involve something imaginary, and can’t constitute the substance of body.

13. Since the individual notion of each person involves once and for all everything that will ever happen to him, we can see in that notion the a priori proofs or reasons for the occurrence of every event—seeing why one thing happens rather than another. But although these truths are certain, they are still contingent, for they are based on the free will of God and of created things. It is true that there are always reasons for their choices, but those reasons incline without necessitating.

14. God produces a variety of substances according to his different views of the universe; and he intervenes so as to bring it about that the particular nature of each substance makes what happens to it correspond to what happens to all the others, without their directly acting on one another.

15. When one finite substance ‘acts on’ another, all that happens is that the first undergoes an increase in the degree of its expression while the other undergoes a decrease, which happens because God formed them in advance so that they would fit together.

16. Our essence expresses everything, so it expresses God’s extraordinary concourse. But our nature or clear expression is finite, and follows certain subordinate rules; it doesn’t extend far enough to take in God’s extraordinary concourse.

17. An example of a subordinate rule of natural law, which shows that God always systematically conserves the same force, but not (contrary to the Cartesians and others) the same quantity of motion.

18. The distinction between force and quantity of motion is important. For one thing, it shows that to explain how bodies behave we must bring in metaphysical considerations apart from extension.

19. The usefulness of final causes in physical science.

20. A memorable passage by Socrates in Plato’s Phaedo

27

Discourse on Metaphysics G. W. Leibniz

against over-materialist philosophers.

21. If mechanical rules depended only on geometry and not on metaphysics, the observed facts would be quite different.

22. Reconciliation of two methods, one working through final causes and the other through efficient ones, in order to satisfy both sides: those who explain Nature mechanically, and those who appeal to immaterial natures.

23. Returning to immaterial substances, I explain how God acts on the mind’s understanding, and discuss whether we always have an idea of what we are thinking about.

24. What vivid and dark, clear and confused, adequate and inadequate, intuitive and suppositive knowledge are; nominal, real, causal and essential definition.

25. In what cases our knowledge is combined with the contemplation of an idea.

26. That we have within us all ideas; Plato’s doctrine of reminiscence.

27. How our soul can be compared with a blank tablet, and in what way our notions come from the senses.

28. God alone is the immediate object of our perceptions, who exists outside of us, and he alone is our light.

29. However, we think directly through our own ideas and not through God’s.

30. How God inclines our soul without necessitating it; that we have no right to complain; we should not ask why Judas sinned, since that free act is included in his notion; we should only ask why Judas the sinner was admitted into existence in preference to some other possible people. Original imperfection or limitation, prior to sin; the different levels of grace.

31. The reasons for election, foreseen faith, absolute decrees. Everything comes down to God’s reason for deciding to admit into existence a certain possible person, whose notion contains a certain series of graces and free actions. Which removes the difficulties at a stroke.

32. The usefulness of these principles in matters of piety and religion.

33. Explaining the communication between the soul and the body, which has been taken to be inexplicable or miraculous. The origin of confused perceptions.

34. How minds differ from other substances, souls or substantial forms. The immortality that we require implies memory.

35. The excellence of minds; God attends to them ahead of other creatures; minds express God rather than the world, and other simple substances express the world rather than God.

36. God is the monarch of the most perfect republic, composed of all minds, and the happiness of this city of God is his main aim.

37. Jesus Christ revealed to men the wonderful mystery and laws of the Kingdom of Heaven, and the splendour of the supreme happiness that God prepares for those who love him.

2

28

The Principles of Philosophy

known as Monadology

G. W. Leibniz

Copyright © 2010–2015 All rights reserved. Jonathan Bennett
[Brackets] enclose editorial explanations. Small ·dots· enclose material that has been added, but can be read as though it were part of the original text. Occasional •bullets, and also indenting of passages that are not quotations, are meant as aids to grasping the structure of a sentence or a thought. Every four-point ellipsis .... indicates the omission of a brief passage that seems to present more difficulty than it is worth.
First launched: September 2004 Last amended: July 2007
[This single-column (but otherwise unrevised) version by Philosophy Ink derives from the original two-column PDF version at http://www.earlymoderntexts.com. Even Bennett's pagination has been retained since he sometimes makes in-text references to his own page numbers.]

* * * * * *

1. My topic here will be the monad, which is just a simple substance. By calling it ‘simple’ I mean that it has no parts, though it can be a part of something composite.

2. There must be simple substances, because there are composites. A composite thing is just a collection of simple ones that happen to have come together.

3. Something that has no parts can’t be extended, can’t have a shape, and can’t be split up. So monads are the true atoms of Nature—the elements out of which everything is made.

4. We don’t have to fear that a monad might fall to pieces; there is no conceivable way it could •go out of existence naturally.

5. For the same reason, there is no way for a simple substance to •come into existence naturally, for that would involve its being put together, assembled, composed, and a simple substance couldn’t be formed in that way because it has no parts.

6. So we can say that the only way for monads to begin or end—to come into existence or go out of existence—is •instantaneously, being created or annihilated all at once. Composite things, in contrast with that, can begin or end •gradually, through the assembling or scattering of their parts.

7. It doesn’t make sense to suppose that a monad might be altered or re-arranged internally by any other created

Monadology G. W. Leibniz

thing. Within a monad there’s nothing to re-arrange, and there is no conceivable internal motion in it that could be started, steered, sped up, or slowed down, as can happen in a composite thing that has parts that can change in relation to one another. [The passage from here to * is not by Leibniz. It makes explicit what was presumably at work in his mind when he made his remarkable jump.] That rules out every sort of influence that one might think a created thing might have on something else. (I stress ‘created’ because of course I don’t rule out God’s affecting a monad.) Some philosophers have held that one thing can affect another by sending an ‘accident’ across to it, understanding an accident to be an instance of a property as distinct from the thing that has the property. According to these philosophers, in addition to the •universal property heat and the •particular thing this poker there is a •particular property, an instance, an accident, namely the heat of this poker; and they hold that when the poker is plunged into cold water which then becomes warmer, the poker sends an accident—some of its particular heat—across to the water. Now, you might think that although a created thing can’t cause re-arrangements in a simple substance it might be able to affect it in a different way by sending an accident across to it. And because you might think this I should add that * monads have no windows through which anything could come in or go out! And ·anyway, quite apart from the imperviousness of monads to them, these supposed migrating accidents are philosophical rubbish·: accidents can’t detach themselves and stroll about outside of substances!.... So neither substance nor accident can come into a monad from outside.

8. Monads, ·although they have no parts·, must have some qualities. There are two reasons why this must be so. (1) If they didn’t have qualities they wouldn’t be real things at all. (2) If they didn’t differ from one another in their qualities, there would be no detectable changes in the world ·of composite things·. Here is why. [Leibniz starts the next sentence ‘If monads had no qualities,’ but this is obviously a slip.] If monads all had the same qualities, they would be indistinguishable from one another (given that they don’t differ in any quantitative way, e.g. in size). That would make all composite things ·such as portions of matter· indistinguishable from one another also, because whatever is the case about a composite thing has to come from its simple ingredients. ·Even if every portion of matter were exactly like every other, there might still be variety in the material world through differences in patterns of distribution of portions of matter in empty space. I think there is no empty space—the extended world is entirely full, a plenum·. So, assuming a plenum and no qualitative variety, any moving around of matter would only result in each place containing something exactly like what it had contained previously, so that one state of things would be indistinguishable from another.

9. ·That shows that some monads must be qualitatively unlike some others; but now I go further·. Indeed, every monad must be qualitatively unlike every other. That is because in Nature no two things are perfectly alike; between any two things a difference can be found that is internal—i.e. based on what each is like in its own nature ·rather than merely on how they relate to other things, e.g. where they are in space·.

10. I take it for granted that every created thing can change, and thus that created monads can change. I hold in fact that every monad changes continually.

11. From what I said in 7 it follows that natural changes in a monad—·ones that don’t come from divine intervention·—come from an internal force, since no external causes could ever influence its interior.

2

Monadology G. W. Leibniz

12. But in addition to this ·general· force for change ·that is the same in all monads·, there must be the detailed nature of the ·individual· changing simple substance, this being what makes it belong to one species rather than another.

13. This detailed nature must bring a •multiplicity within the •unity of the simple substance. ·The latter’s detailed nature is a ‘multiplicity’ in the sense that it has many components that don’t stand or fall together·. That is because every natural change happens by degrees, gradually, meaning that something changes while something else stays the same. So although there are no •parts in a simple substance, there must be a plurality of •states and of relationships.

14. The passing state that incorporates and represents a multitude within a unity—i.e. within the simple substance—is nothing but what we call •perception. This must be carefully distinguished from •awareness or consciousness, as will become clear in what follows. [‘Awareness’ here translates aperception. French had no noun for that job (nor did English), so Leibniz coined the aperception on the basis of the verb phrase s’apercevoir de, which meant and still means ‘to be aware of’.] In that the Cartesians failed badly, entirely discounting perceptions whose owners were not aware of them. That made them think that the only monads are minds, which led them to deny that animals have souls ·because those would be simple substances below the level of minds·.... Like the uneducated man in the street they confused a long stupor with death, ·whereas really a long period of unconsciousness is different from death· in the strict sense. This led them further into the Aristotelians’ wrong belief in souls that are entirely separated ·from any body·, as well as confirming misguided minds in the belief that souls are mortal.

15. The action of the internal force that brings about change—brings the monad from one perception to another—can be called •appetition. Appetite cannot always get the whole way to the perception towards which it is tending, but it always gets some of the way, and reaches new perceptions—·that is, new temporary states of the monad·.

16. A simple substance that incorporates a multiplicity—that’s something we experience in ourselves. ·We are simple substances·, and we find that every perception we can be aware of—right down to the least of them—involves variety in its object; ·and a perception representing variety in the object that it is of must itself be variegated in some way·. Thus everyone who accepts that the soul is a simple substance should accept this multiplicity in the monad, and Bayle oughtn’t to have found any difficulty in it, as he did in the article ‘Rorarius’ in his Dictionary.

17. It has to be acknowledged that •perception can’t be explained by mechanical principles, that is by shapes and motions, and thus that nothing that •depends on perception can be explained in that way either. ·Suppose this were wrong·. Imagine there were a machine whose structure produced thought, feeling, and perception; we can conceive of its being enlarged while maintaining the same relative proportions ·among its parts·, so that we could walk into it as we can walk into a mill. Suppose we do walk into it; all we would find there are cogs and levers and so on pushing one another, and never anything to account for a perception. So perception must be sought in simple substances, not in composite things like machines. And that is all that can be found in a simple substance—•perceptions and •changes in perceptions; and those changes are all that the internal actions of simple substances can consist in.

3

Monadology G. W. Leibniz

18. [The word ‘entelechy’, used in this section, is a Greek label that Leibniz gives to monads, especially when he wants to emphasize the monad’s role as a source of power, energy, or the like. He connects it here with the monad’s ‘perfection’, apparently meaning this in the sense of completeness, self-sufficiency, causal power. In 62 he will connect ‘entelechy’ with the monad’s central role in the life of a body of which it is the soul.] We could give the name ‘entelechy’ to all simple substances or created monads, because they have within them a certain perfection....; there is a kind of self-sufficiency which makes them sources of their own internal actions—makes them immaterial automata, as it were.

19. [In this section, the French word sentiment is left untranslated. It could mean ‘feeling’ or ‘sensation’ or ‘belief’.] If we are willing to label as a ‘soul’ anything that has perceptions and appetites in the general sense that I have just explained, then all simple substances—all created monads—could be called ‘souls’. But as there is more to sentiment than mere perception, I think that the general name ‘monad’ or ‘entelechy’ is adequate for substances that have mere perception and nothing more, and that we should reserve ‘soul’ for the ones with perceptions that are more distinct and accompanied by memory. ·In this context I shall use the phrase ‘mere monad’ to mean ‘monad whose perceptions have nothing special about them, are not distinct or accompanied by memory, are merely perceptions with nothing more to be said about them·.

20. For we experience ourselves being a state in which we remember nothing and have no distinct perception—for example when we fall into a faint, or are overtaken by a deep dreamless sleep. While our soul is in that state, there is nothing to mark it off from a mere monad; but for our soul that state doesn’t last—the soul recovers from it—which is why it is a soul, something more than a mere monad.

21. But it doesn’t at all follow that a mere monad has no perceptions at all. ·It not only doesn’t follow·; it couldn’t be true, for a three-part reason that I have given: •a monad can’t go out of existence, but •to stay in existence it has to be in some state or other, and •its states are all perceptions. But ·having perceptions is compatible with being in a very confused state, as we know from our own experience·. When we have a great many small perceptions none of which stand out, we are dazed; for example when you spin around continually in one direction for a time, you become dizzy, you can’t distinguish anything, and you may faint. That is the state animals are in, temporarily, when they meet their ·so-called· death.

22. And every momentary state of a simple substance is a natural consequence of its ·immediately· preceding one, so that the present is pregnant with the future.

23. When you recover from your dizzy spell and are aware of having perceptions, you obviously must have been having perceptions just before then, though you weren’t aware of them. That is because, ·as I said in 22·, in the course of Nature a perception can come only from another perception, just as a motion can come only from another motion.

24. We can see from this that if none of our perceptions stood out, if none were (so to speak) highly seasoned and more strongly flavoured than the rest, we would be in a permanent daze. And that is the state that bare monads—·what I am here calling ‘mere monads’·–are in ·all the time·.

25. Nature has given highly seasoned perceptions to animals. We can see this in the care Nature has taken to provide animals with sense-organs that bring together a number of light-rays or air-waves, increasing their effectiveness by combining them. Something like this ·also· happens with scent, taste and touch, and perhaps with numerous other senses

4

Monadology G. W. Leibniz

that we don’t know about. ·That concentration of influence on the •sense-organs is relevant to my present topic, which is the occurrence of ‘highly flavoured’ perceptions in the •soul·. I shall explain shortly how what happens in the •soul represents what goes on in the •organs.

26. Memory provides souls with a kind of following from which mimics reason but must be distinguished from it. It is what we see in an animal that has a perception of something striking of which it has previously had a similar perception; the representations in its memory lead it to expect •this time the same thing that happened •on the previous occasion, and to have the same feelings •now as it had •then. For example, when you show a stick to a dog, it remembers how the stick hurt it ·on a previous occasion·, and it whines or runs away.

27. The animal in this case is impressed and stirred up by a powerful imagining; and its power comes either from •the size [here = ‘strength’ or ‘intensity’] of the preceding perceptions or from •there being many of them. ·Either would do the job·; for the effect of •a long habituation, the repetition of many mild perceptions, is often achieved in a moment by •one powerful impression.

28. In human beings, the perceptions often follow from other perceptions under the influence of memory; as with empiric physicians, who have elementary technique without theory. [An ‘empiric’ is someone who cares about which generalizations hold up in practice, but not about why.] We are all mere •empirics in three quarters of what we do. For example, we are empirics in our expectation that the sun will rise tomorrow because it has always done so up to now. Only the •astronomer believes it on the basis of reason. In this empiric aspect of their lives, humans operate in the same way as the lower animals do.

29. What distinguishes us from the lower animals is our knowledge of necessary and eternal truths ·and, associated with that, our having a kind of ‘following from’ that •involves necessity and •depends on reason, rather than merely the ‘following from’ of the animals, which •is wholly contingent and depends on memory·. This is what gives us reason and science, raising us to the knowledge of ourselves and of God. And it’s what is called ‘rational soul’ or ‘mind’ in us.

30. Our knowledge of necessary truths, and ·our grasp of· the abstractions they involve, raise us to the level of acts of reflection [= ‘looking in on oneself’], which make ·each of· us aware of the thing that is called I, and lets us have thoughts about this or that thing in us. And by thinking of ourselves in this way we think of •being, of •substance, of •simples and •composites, of •what is immaterial—and of •God himself, through the thought that what is limited in us is limitless in him. And so these acts of reflection provide the principal objects of our reasonings.

31. Our reasonings are based on two great principles: •the principle of contradiction, on the strength of which we judge to be false anything that involves contradiction, and as true whatever is opposed or contradictory to what is false.

32. And •the principle of sufficient reason, on the strength of which we hold that no fact can ever be true or existent, no statement correct, unless there is a sufficient reason why things are as they are and not otherwise—even if in most cases we can’t know what the reason is.

33. There are also two kinds of truth: those of reasoning and those of fact.

•Truths of reasoning are necessary, and their opposite is impossible.

•Truths of fact are contingent, and their opposite is possible.

5

Monadology G. W. Leibniz

When a truth is necessary, the reason for it can be found by analysis in which it is teased apart into simpler ideas and truths until we arrive at the basic ones.

34. That is how mathematicians use analysis, reducing theorems of mathematical theory and canons of mathematical practice to definitions, axioms and postulates.

35. Eventually ·their analysis comes to an end, because· there are •simple ideas that can’t be given a definition; and ·their demonstrations also come to an end, because· there are •axioms and postulates—in a word, basic principles—which can’t be proved and don’t need to be proved; these are identical propositions, the opposites of which contain explicit contradictions.

36. ·What mathematicians do is to find sufficient reasons for the truth of •mathematical propositions·. But a sufficient reason must also be found for •contingent truths, truths of fact—for the series of things spread across the universe of created things. For truths of this sort reasons can be given in more and more detail, because of the immense variety of things in Nature and because of the infinite divisibility of bodies. Consider the movements of pen across paper that I am making right now. Their •efficient cause includes an infinity of •shapes and of motions, present and past; and their •final cause—·that is, their end or purpose·—involves an infinity of tiny •inclinations and dispositions of my soul, present and past.

37. But all this detail only brings in other contingencies—ones bringing in even more detail, or ones involving events that occurred earlier—and each of these further contingencies also needs to be explained through a similar analysis. So when we give explanations of this sort we move no nearer ·to the goal of completely explaining contingencies·. Infinite though it may be, the train of detailed facts about contingencies—·running down into ever more minute detail, or back to ever earlier times·—doesn’t contain the sufficient reason, the ultimate reason, for any contingent fact. For that we must look outside the sequence of •contingencies.

38. That is why the ultimate reason for things must be in a •necessary substance which we call ‘God’. The details of all the ·contingent· changes are contained in him only eminently, as in their source. [To say that x contains a property ‘only eminently’ is to say that x doesn’t literally have that property, but does have the resources to cause things to have it. For example, God is not politically astute, but he contains political astuteness eminently.]

39. This ·necessary· substance is a sufficient reason for all this detail, which is interconnected throughout; so there is only one God, and this God is sufficient.

40. This supreme substance is unique and universal, because nothing outside it is independent of it; and it is necessary because its •existing follows simply—·that is, directly, without help from any other premises·—from its •being possible. Given all this, we can conclude that the supreme necessary being must be incapable of limits and ·therefore· must contain fully as much reality as is possible. (·If there were some kind of reality which it did not have as fully as possible—e.g. if it were very powerful but not omnipotent—that would be a limit in it·.)

41. From which it follows that God is absolutely perfect. ·Why?· Because a thing’s perfection is simply the total amount of positive reality it contains, using ‘positive’ in its precise sense, in which it doesn’t apply to any of a thing’s limitations or boundaries; so that where there are no boundaries at all, namely in God, perfection must be absolutely infinite.

6

Monadology G. W. Leibniz

42. It also follows that created things get their perfections from the influence of God, but derive their imperfections from their own natures. Their natures have to have limits, for that is what distinguishes them from God.

43. Also, God is the source not only of existences but also of essences insofar as they are real; that is, he is the source of what reality there is among possibilities. This is because God’s understanding is the realm of eternal truths, or the realm of the ideas on which such truths depend. Without God’s understanding there would be no reality among possibilities....

44. That is because if there is to be any reality among essences or possibilities, or among eternal truths, that reality must be grounded in something actually existent; so it must be grounded in the existence of the necessary being, in whom essence includes existence, meaning that in the case of God being possible is sufficient for being actual.

45. Thus only God (the necessary being) has this privilege: if he is possible then he must exist. Now, something that has no limits involves no negation; ·every truth about it is positive·; so it involves no contradiction (·because all contradictions boil down to something of the form ‘P and not-P’, which contains a negation·). So God must be possible, from which it follows that God exists—giving us an •a priori proof of his existence. In 43 I also •proved it a priori in a different way, through the reality of eternal truths, ·which can contain reality only if the ideas they involve are in God’s understanding·. But what I have just said •proves God’s existence a posteriori, from the premise that contingent things exist, for their ultimate or sufficient reason could only be found in the necessary being which contains within itself the reason for its own existence.

46. Descartes seems to have imagined....that since eternal truths depend on God, they must be arbitrary and depend on his •will; but we shouldn’t follow him in this. What depend on his will are only contingent truths, which are governed by suitability or the choice of the best; whereas necessary truths depend solely on God’s •understanding, of which they are the internal object.

47. Thus God alone is the basic unitary thing, the original simple substance. All created or derivative monads are produced by him. They are generated by the continual flashes of silent lightning (so to speak) that God gives off from moment to moment—flashes that are limited ·in what they can give only· by the essential limits on what the created things can take in.

48. In God there is

(i) power, which is the source of everything, then

(ii) knowledge, which contains every single idea, and then finally

(iii) will, which produces changes in accordance with the principle of what is best.

And these are what correspond, respectively, to what in created monads constitute

(i) the subject, or base, ·or basic nature of the monad itself·,

(ii) the faculty of perception, and

(iii) the appetitive faculty.

But in God these attributes are absolutely infinite or perfect, whereas in created monads....they are only imitations ·of the divine attributes·, imitations that are more or less close depending on how much perfection they possess.

49. A created thing is said to •act on something else in so far as it has perfection, and to •be acted on by something else in so far as it is imperfect. Thus, •activity is attributed

7

Monadology G. W. Leibniz

to a monad in so far as it has distinct perceptions, and passivity is attributed to the monad in so far as it has confused perceptions. ·Why do I say ‘Thus,... ’, implying that the second of the above two sentences follows from the first? It is because of a link between being perfect and having distinct perceptions—a link I now explain·.

50. ·To the extent that one monad has distinct perceptions and another has confused ones, the former’s states can explain the latter’s, and not vice versa. And· one created thing is more perfect than another to the extent that what happens in it serves to explain a priori what happens in the other; and that is what makes us say that it ‘acted on’ the other.

51. How can the states of monad x explain the states of monad y? Not by x’s having a •real influence on y, for that is impossible. All that x has with respect to y is an •ideal influence, which works through the intervention of God. When God is setting things up at the outset, monad x reasonably demands, in God’s mind, that God take account of x in designing y. That is how x’s states explain y’s: it has nothing to do with real causal influence of x over y, which is something a created monad could never exert.

52. And here is how monad x can be both active and passive with respect to monad y—acting on y and being acted on by it. God, in comparing the two simple substances, finds in each reasons that oblige him to adapt the other to it; so that x can differ from y in some ways that make it active, and in others that make it passive, with respect to y. It is active to the extent that what can be clearly understood in it serves to explain what happens in y, and passive to the extent that what happens in it is explained by distinct perceptions in y.

53. Now, since in the ideas of God there is an infinity of possible universes, and since only one can exist, there must be a sufficient reason for God’s choice of that one—a reason that leads him to choose •one rather than •some other of the possible universes.

54. And this reason can only be found in the suitability or degrees of perfection that these worlds contain, with each possible world’s right to claim existence being proportional to the perfection it contains.

55. And that is the reason for the existence of the best, which God’s wisdom brings him to know, his goodness brings him to choose, and his power brings him to produce.

56. Now, this interconnection, or this adapting of all created things to each one, and of each one to all the others, brings it about that each simple substance has relational properties that express all the others, so that each monad is a perpetual living mirror of the universe.

57. And just as the same town when seen from different sides will seem quite different—as though it were multiplied perspectivally—the same thing happens here: because of the infinite multitude of simple substances it’s as though there were that many different universes; but they are all perspectives on the same one, differing according to the different points of view of the monads.

58. And that is the way to get the greatest possible •variety, but with all the •order there could be; i.e. it is the way to get as much perfection as there could be.

59. This theory (which I venture to say I have now demonstrated) is the only one that properly displays God’s greatness. Bayle recognised this when he raised objections to it in his Dictionary (the article on Rorarius), where he was even tempted to say that I had attributed to God too much—more than is possible ·even for God·. But he couldn’t adduce any reason why this universal harmony, which makes every substance exactly express every other through its relations with them, should be impossible.

8

Monadology G. W. Leibniz

60. Anyway, what I have just been saying yields reasons why things couldn’t have gone otherwise. ·Here they are·. In regulating the whole universe God had regard to each part, and especially to each monad; ·so each monad has features that are given to it in the light of the features of every other monad—it won’t be restricted to having correspondences with only a part of the universe·. And since a monad is by nature representative, ·so that all its features are representations·, nothing could restrict it to representing only a part of the universe. ·I am not saying that each monad is omniscient, or anything like that!· A created monad’s representation of the details of the whole universe is confused; it can be distinct only with respect to a small part of things, namely things that are either closest or largest in relation to it. Otherwise every monad would be divine! Monads are limited not in how widely their knowledge spreads, but in what kind of knowledge it is. They all reach confusedly to infinity, to everything; but they are limited and differentiated by their different levels of distinct perception.

61. And in this respect composite things are analogous to simple ones. ·In the world of composites, the world of matter·, everything is full, which means that all matter is interlinked. ·If there were empty space, a body might move in it without affecting any other body; but that is not how things stand·. In a plenum [= ‘world that is full’], any movement must have an effect on distant bodies, the greater the distance the smaller the effect, ·but always some effect. Here is why·. Each body is affected by •the bodies that touch it, and feels some effects of everything that happens to •them; but also through •them it also feels the effects of all the bodies that touch •them, and so on, so that such communication extends indefinitely. As a result, each body feels the effects of everything that happens in the universe, so that he who sees everything could read off from each body what is happening everywhere; and, indeed, because he could see in its present state what is distant both in space and in time, he could read also what has happened and what will happen.... But a soul can read within itself only what is represented there distinctly; it could never bring out all at once everything that is folded into it, because its folds go on to infinity.

62. Thus, although each created monad represents the whole universe, it represents more distinctly the body that is exclusively assigned to it, and of which it forms the entelechy [see note in 18]. And just as that •body expresses the whole universe through the interconnection of all matter in the plenum, the •soul also represents the entire universe by representing its particular body.

63. What we call a ‘living thing’ is

a body that has a monad as its entelechy or its soul,

together with

that entelechy or soul.

And we call a living thing ‘an animal’ if its entelechy or central monad is a soul [see 19]. Now this body of a living thing or animal is always highly organized. ·Here is why·:

•The universe is regulated in a perfectly orderly manner; and

•every monad is a mirror of the universe in its own way; so

•the representing monad must itself be orderly; so

•the body that it represents (thereby representing the universe) must be orderly.

64. Thus every organized body of a living thing is a kind of divine machine or natural automaton. It infinitely surpasses any artificial automaton, because a man-made machine isn’t a machine in every one of its parts. For example, a cog on a brass wheel has parts or fragments which to us are no longer anything artificial, and bear no signs of their relation to the

9

Monadology G. W. Leibniz

intended use of the wheel, signs that would mark them out as parts of a machine. But Nature’s machines—living bodies, that is—are machines even in their smallest parts, right down to infinity. That is what makes the difference between •nature and •artifice, that is, between •divine artifice and •our artifice.

65. And ·God·, the author of Nature, was able to carry out this divine and infinitely marvellous artifice because every portion of matter is not only

divisible to infinity,

as the ancients realised, but is

actually sub-divided without end,

every part divided into smaller parts, each one of which has some motion of its own ·rather than having only such motion as it gets from the motion of some larger lump of which it is a part·. Without this ·infinite dividedness· it would be impossible for each portion of matter to express the whole universe.

66. And from this we can see that there is a world of creatures—of living things and animals, entelechies and souls—in the smallest fragment of matter.

67. Every portion of matter can be thought of as a garden full of plants or a pond full of fish. But every branch of the plant, every part of the animal (every drop of its vital fluids, even) is another such garden or pond.

68. And although the earth and air separating the plants in the garden and the water separating the fish in the pond are not themselves plants or fish, they contain other ·organisms·, but usually ones that are too small for us to perceive them.

69. Thus there is nothing barren, sterile, dead in the universe; nothing chaotic, nothing confused except in appearance. ·Here is an example of that·. If you see a pond from a certain distance, you may see the swirling of the fish without being able to pick out any individual fish; it may seem to you that you are seeing confused movements of the fish, ·but really nothing is confused in itself—what’s happening here is that you are perceiving confusedly·.

70. We can see from this that every living body has one dominant entelechy, which in an animal is its soul; but the parts of that living body are full of other living things, plants, animals, each of which also has its entelechy or dominant soul.

71. Some people who have misunderstood my ideas have thought ·me to have implied· that

every soul has a mass or portion of matter which is its own and is assigned to it for ever, and therefore every soul has other living things that are inferior to it, destined always to be in its service.

That doesn’t follow; and it isn’t true, because all bodies are in a perpetual state of flux, like rivers, with parts constantly coming into them and going out.

72. Thus the soul changes its body only gradually, a bit at a time, and is never suddenly stripped of all its organs. So animals undergo a great deal of change of form [French metamorphose] but they never undergo the transmigration of souls from one body to another [metempsychose]. And no souls are completely separated from matter—there are no spirits without bodies. Only God is completely detached from matter.

73. Another upshot of all this is that there is never either •complete generation ·in which a living thing comes into existence· or •complete death, which (taking ‘death’ in its strict sense) consists in the soul’s becoming detached ·from its body·. What we call generation is development and growth; just as what we call death is envelopment and shrinking.

10

Monadology G. W. Leibniz

74. Philosophers [here = ‘philosophers and scientists’] have been at a loss regarding the origin of forms, entelechies, or souls, ·but not any longer·. Careful investigations into plants, insects and animals have shown that Nature’s organic bodies are never produced from chaos or from putrefaction, but always from seeds, in which there is without doubt already some preformation. ·Rather than something formed being generated from something formless, it has turned out that what is formed always comes from something that was already formed·. So these days we think that before conception there is an organized body there, and that this has a soul; which is to say that before conception there is already an animal there. What conception does is to launch that animal into a great transformation that will turn it into an animal of a different kind. We even have examples of something like this ·great transformation· apart from generation, as when maggots turn into flies and caterpillars into butterflies.

75. ·The account that is generally accepted these days goes as follows·. Tiny animals that could get raised to the level of larger animals through the process of conception we can call ‘spermatic animals’. The majority of them don’t go through that process; they remain within their own kind, and are born, reproduce themselves and are destroyed, just like the larger animals. Only the select few move up onto a larger stage.

76. But that is only half right. I came to realize that an animal that has no natural way of starting can’t naturally end either, and thus that not only will there be no generation but also no complete destruction, no death in the strict sense of that word. This a posteriori line of thought based on observation fits perfectly with the a priori principles that I deduced above.

77. So it can be said that not only is the soul—the mirror of an indestructible universe—indestructible, but so too is the animal; though its mechanism may often come to an end in part, and throw off or take on organic coating.

78. These principles gave me a natural way of explaining the union of the soul with the organic body, or rather their conformity with one another. Soul and body each follow their own laws; and are in agreement in virtue of the fact that, since they all represent the same universe. there is a pre-established harmony among all substances.

79. Souls act according to •the laws of final causes, through appetition, ends and means. Bodies act according to •the laws of efficient causes, i.e. the laws of motion. And these two realms, that of efficient causes and that of final causes, harmonize with one another.

80. Descartes recognised that souls can’t impart force to bodies, because there is always the same amount of •force in matter. He believed, though, that the soul could change the directions of bodies. But that was because in his day the law of Nature which maintains the conservation of the same total •direction in matter was unknown. If he had been aware of it he would have ended up with my system of preestablished harmony.

81. This system maintains that bodies act as if there were no souls (though there couldn’t be no souls); and souls act as if there were no bodies. And both act as if one of them influenced the other.

82. As for minds, or rational souls [see 29]: I stand by my view, just expressed, that

basically there is the same thing in all living things and animals, so that both the soul and the animal begin only when the world begins, and never come to an end, any more than the world does;

11

Monadology G. W. Leibniz

but I maintain that there is something special to be said about rational animals, as follows. Their little spermatic animals, to the extent that they are no more than that, have only ordinary souls, ones that can feel; but when the select few come, through an act of conception, to have the nature of a human being, their feeling souls are raised to the level of reason, and to the privileges of minds.

83. I have noted some differences between ordinary souls and minds. Here is another. •Souls in general are living mirrors or images [here = ‘likenesses’] of the universe of •created things, but •minds are also images of •the Divinity himself, i.e. of ·God·, the author of Nature. They are capable of knowing the system of the universe, and of imitating aspects of it through sketchy constructions of their own, each mind being like a little divinity within its own sphere.

84. That is what enables minds to enter into a kind of community with God, so that he relates to them not only (as he does to all his other creatures) •as an inventor relates to his machine, but also •as a prince does to his subjects, and indeed •as a father does to his children.

85. From this it is easy to conclude that the totality of all minds must make up the City of God, i.e. the most perfect possible state under the most perfect of monarchs.

86. This City of God, this truly universal monarchy, is a moral world within the natural world, and it is the noblest and the most divine of God’s creations. And it is in this moral world that the glory of God truly consists, since there would be no such glory if God’s greatness and goodness were not known and admired by minds. Furthermore, although his •wisdom and •power can be seen in everything ·he does·, strictly speaking it is only in relation to this divine city that God has •goodness.

87. Just as I earlier established that there is a perfect harmony between two natural realms,

one of •efficient causes and the other of •final causes,

so I should point out here another harmony, between

the •physical realm of Nature and the •moral realm of grace;

that is, between God considered as •designer of the machine of the universe and God considered as •monarch of the divine city of minds.

88. This ·second· harmony ensures that things lead towards grace through the paths of Nature itself. For example, the ·divine· government of minds ·in the City of God· requires that at certain times the planet earth be destroyed and then restored, so as to punish some people and reward others; and ·because of the harmony· this ·moral requirement· will be brought about through purely natural processes.

89. We can also say •that God the designer satisfies the wishes of God the legislator in every respect, and •that sins must therefore bring their own punishment through the natural order—indeed through the mechanical structure of things; and similarly •that fine actions will draw their reward through the mechanical doings of bodies, even though that reward can’t and shouldn’t always arrive right away.

90. Finally, under this perfect government there will be no unrewarded good actions and no unpunished bad ones; and everything must work out for the benefit of •the good, i.e. of those in this great state •who are not discontented, •who trust in providence when they have done their duty, and •who love and model themselves (as they should) on the author of all good—getting delight from contemplating his perfections (which is what genuinely pure love involves, getting pleasure from the happiness of the beloved). That is what gets wise and virtuous people •to work at everything

12

Monadology G. W. Leibniz

that seems to conform to what God can be presumed in advance to want, and what gets them •to be content nevertheless with what God brings about through what—it turns out later—he actually does want. [Leibniz expresses this contrast through technical terms derived from Thomas Aquinas.] They are content with this because they recognise that if we could understand the order of the universe well enough we would find that it surpasses all the hopes of the wisest people, and that it is impossible to make it better than it is. Not only could the universe not be better as a whole, but—wise and virtuous people recognize—it couldn’t be better for us in particular, as long as we are properly dedicated to ·God·, the creator of everything; not only as the designer and efficient cause of our being, but also as our master and final cause, who should be the entire goal of our wills, and who alone can make us happy.

13

Second Treatise of Government

John Locke

Copyright © 2010–2015 All rights reserved. Jonathan Bennett
[Brackets] enclose editorial explanations. Small ·dots· enclose material that has been added, but can be read as though it were part of the original text. Occasional •bullets, and also indenting of passages that are not quotations, are meant as aids to grasping the structure of a sentence or a thought. Every four-point ellipsis .... indicates the omission of a brief passage that seems to present more difficulty than it is worth.—-The division into numbered sections is Locke’s.
First launched: January 2005 Last amended: March 2008
[This single-column (but otherwise unrevised) version by Philosophy Ink derives from the original two-column PDF version at http://www.earlymoderntexts.com. Even Bennett's pagination has been retained since he sometimes makes in-text references to his own page numbers.]

Contents

Preface 1
Chapter 1 2
Chapter 2: The state of nature 3
Chapter 3: The state of war 7
Chapter 4: Slavery 9
Chapter 5: Property 10
Chapter 6: Paternal power 19
Chapter 7: Political or Civil Society 26

Second Treatise John Locke

Chapter 8: The beginning of political societies 32
Chapter 9: The purposes of political society and government 40
Chapter 10: The forms of a commonwealth 42
Chapter 11: The extent of the legislative power 43
Chapter 12: The legislative, executive, and federative powers of the commonwealth 46
Chapter 13: The subordination of the powers of the commonwealth 48
Chapter 14: Prerogative 53
Chapter 15: Paternal, political, and despotic power, considered together 56
Chapter 16: Conquest 58
Chapter 17: Usurpation 65
Chapter 18: Tyranny 65
Chapter 19: The dissolution of government 70
Locke on children 80

Second Treatise John Locke Preface

Preface to the two Treatises

Reader, you have here the beginning and the end of a ·two-part· treatise about government. It isn’t worthwhile to go into what happened to the pages that should have come in between (they were more than half the work). [The missing pages, that were to have been included in the Second Treatise, i.e. the second part of the two-part treatise, were simply lost. They contained an extended attack on Sir Robert Filmer’s Patriarcha, a defence of the divine right of kings, published in 1680 (Filmer had died in 1653). The lost pages presumably overlapped the attack on the same target that filled Locke’s First Treatise of Government and also occupy a good deal of space in the Second.] These surviving pages, I hope, are sufficient •to establish the throne of our great restorer, our present King William; •to justify his title ·to the throne· on the basis of the consent of the people, which is the only lawful basis for government, and which he possesses more fully and clearly than any other ruler in the Christian world; and to •justify to the world the people of England, whose love of their just and natural rights, and their resolve to preserve them, saved this nation when it was on the brink of slavery and ruin ·under King James II·. If these pages are as convincing as I flatter myself that they are, the missing pages will be no great loss, and my reader can be satisfied without them. ·I certainly hope so, because· I don’t expect to have either the time of the inclination to take all that trouble again, filling up the gap in my answer by again tracking Sir Robert ·Filmer· through all the windings and obscurities of his amazing system. The king and the nation as a whole have since so thoroughly refuted his hypothesis that I don’t think anyone ever again will be •bold enough to speak up against our common safety, and be an advocate for slavery, or •weak enough to be deceived by contradictions dressed up in elegant language. If you take the trouble to tackle the parts of Sir Robert’s discourses that are not dealt with here, stripping off the flourish of dubious expressions and trying to turn his words into direct, positive, intelligible propositions, and if you then compare these propositions with one another, you will soon be satisfied that there was never so much glib nonsense put together in fine-sounding English. If you don’t think it worthwhile to look through all his work, just try the part where he discusses usurpation, and see whether all your skill is enough to make Sir Robert intelligible and consistent with himself and with common sense. I wouldn’t speak so plainly of a gentleman who is no longer in a position to answer, if it weren’t that in recent years preachers have been espousing his doctrine and making it the current orthodoxy of our times.... I wouldn’t have written against Sir Robert, labouring to show his mistakes, inconsistencies, and lack of the biblical proofs that he boasts of having as his only foundation, if there weren’t men among us who, by praising his books and accepting his doctrine, clear me of the charge of writing only against a dead adversary. They have been so zealous about this that if I have done him any wrong I can’t hope they will show me any mercy. I wish that where they have done wrong to the truth and to the public, they would •be as ready to correct it ·as I am to admit errors proved against me·, and that they •would give due weight to the thought that the greatest harm one can do to the monarch and the people is to spread wrong notions about government. If they did, it might for ever put an end to our having reason to complain of thunderings from the pulpit! If anyone who is really concerned about truth tries to refute my hypothesis, I promise him either to admit any mistake he fairly convicts

1

Second Treatise John Locke Chapter 1

me of or to answer his difficulties. But he must remember two things: •That picking holes in my discourse—objecting to this turn of phrase or that little incident—is not the same as answering my book. •That I shan’t let scolding pass as argument....

Chapter 1

1. In my First Treatise of Government I showed these four things: (1) That Adam did not have, whether by natural right as a father or through a •positive gift from God, any such authority over his children or over the world as has been claimed. (2) That if even he had, his heirs would not have the same right. (3) That if the right were to be passed on to his heirs, it would be indeterminate who were his heirs, because there is no law of nature or •positive law of God that settles this question in every possible case; so it wouldn’t be determinate who inherited the right and thus was entitled to rule. (4) Even if all that had been ·theoretically· determined, ·it would be useless in practice·: the knowledge of the chain of heirs running back to Adam has been utterly lost, so that nobody in all the races of mankind and families of the world would have the slightest claim to have that ·supposed· right of inheritance. All these premises having, as I think, been clearly established, no rulers now on earth can derive the faintest shadow of authority from the supposed source of all ·human political· power, Adam’s private dominion and paternal rule. So if you don’t want to •give reason to think that all government in the world is the product purely of force and violence, and men live together only by the same rules as the lower animals, where strength settles every issue, and so •lay a foundation for perpetual disorder and mischief, riots, sedition and rebellion (things that the followers of that ·‘force and violence’· hypothesis so loudly cry out against), you will have to find another account of the beginnings of government, another source for political power, and another way of settling who the people are who ·ought to· have it—other, that is, than what Sir Robert Filmer has taught us.

[The word •‘positive’, used in section 1 and again in 13 and elsewhere, is a technical term. A positive law is one that some legislator imposes; it comes from the decision of some law-making authority. The contrast is with a natural law, which isn’t •laid down by anyone but simply •arises out of the natures of things. So a positive gift from God would be simply a gift as ordinarily understood; Locke throws in ‘positive’, presumably, because even a natural right that Adam had would in a sense be a gift from God, because God gave Adam his nature; but it wouldn’t be a positive gift, arising from an explicit gift-giving action on God’s part. Similarly with the notion of a positive law of God’s.].

2. For this purpose, I think it may be worthwhile to state what I think political power is; so that the power of a •government official over a subject can be distinguished from that of a •father over his children, a •master over his servant, a •husband over his wife, and a •lord over his slave. Because it sometimes happens that one man has all these

2

Second Treatise John Locke 2: The state of nature

different powers, we can get clearer about how the powers differ by looking at the different relationships in which the man stands: as ruler of a commonwealth, father of a family, and captain of a galley.

3. So: I take political power to be a right to •make laws—with the death penalty and consequently all lesser penalties—for regulating and preserving property, and to •employ the force of the community in enforcing such laws and defending the commonwealth from external attack; all this being only for the public good.

Chapter 2: The state of nature

4. To understand political power correctly and derive it from its proper source, we must consider what state all men are naturally in. In this state men are perfectly free to order their actions, and dispose of their possessions and themselves, in any way they like, without asking anyone’s permission—subject only to limits set by the law of nature.

It is also a state of equality, in which no-one has more power and authority than anyone else; because it is simply obvious that creatures of the same species and status, all born to all the same advantages of nature and to the use of the same abilities, should also be equal ·in other ways·, with no-one being subjected to or subordinate to anyone else, unless ·God·, the lord and master of them all, were to declare clearly and explicitly his wish that some one person be raised above the others and given an undoubted right to dominion and sovereignty

5. The judicious ·Richard· Hooker regards this natural equality of men as so obvious and unquestionable that he bases on it men’s •obligation to love one another, on which he builds their •duties towards each other, from which ·in turn· he derives the great •maxims of justice and charity. Here are his words:

A similar natural inducement has led men to realize that they have as much duty to love others as to love themselves. Things that are equal must be measured by a single standard; so if I inevitably want to receive some good—indeed as much good from every man as any man can want for himself—how could I expect to have any part of my desire satisfied if I am not careful to satisfy the similar desires that other men, being all of the same nature, are bound to have? To offer them anything inconsistent with their desire will be to grieve them as much as ·it would grieve· me; so that if I do harm I must expect to suffer, because there is no reason why others should show more love to me than I have shown to them. Thus, my desire to be loved as much as possible by my natural equals gives me a natural duty to act towards them with the same love. Everyone knows the rules and canons natural reason has laid down for the guidance of our lives on the basis of this relation of equality between ourselves and those who are like us.

3

Second Treatise John Locke 2: The state of nature

6. But though this is a state of •liberty, it isn’t a state of •licence ·in which there are no constraints on how people behave·. A man in that state is absolutely free to dispose of himself or his possessions, but he isn’t at liberty to destroy himself, or even to destroy any created thing in his possession unless something nobler than its mere preservation is at stake. The state of nature is governed by a law that creates obligations for everyone. And reason, which is that law, teaches anyone who takes the trouble to consult it, that because we are all equal and independent, no-one ought to harm anyone else in his life, health, liberty, or possessions. This is because

•we are all the work of one omnipotent and infinitely wise maker;

•we are all the servants of one sovereign master, sent into the world by his order to do his business;

•we are all the property of him who made us, and he made us to last as long as he chooses, not as long as we choose;

•we have the same abilities, and share in one common nature, so there can’t be any rank-ordering that would authorize some of us to destroy others, as if we were made to be used by one another, as the lower kinds of creatures are made to be used by us.

Everyone is obliged to preserve himself and not opt out of life willfully, so for the same reason everyone ought, when his own survival isn’t at stake, to do as much as he can to preserve the rest of mankind; and except when it’s a matter of punishing an offender, no-one may take away or damage anything that contributes to the preservation of someone else’s life, liberty, health, limb, or goods.

7. So that •all men may be held back from invading the rights of others and from harming one another, and so that •the law of nature that aims at the peace and preservation of all mankind may be obeyed, the enforcement of that law of nature (in the state of nature) is in every man’s hands, so that everyone has a right to punish law-breakers as severely as is needed to hinder the violation of the law. For the law of nature, like every law concerning men in this world, would be futile if no-one had power to enforce it and thereby preserve the innocent and restrain offenders. And in the state of nature if anyone may punish someone for something bad that he has done, then everyone may do so....

8. That is how in a state of nature one man comes to have a ·legitimate· power over another. It isn’t an unconditional power, allowing him to use a captured criminal according to the hot frenzy or unbridled extremes of his own will; but only a power to punish him so far as calm reason and conscience say is proportionate to his crime, namely as much punishment as may serve for •reparation and •restraint—for •those two are the only reasons why one man may lawfully harm another, which is what we call ‘punishment’. By breaking the law of nature, the offender declares himself to live by some rule other than that of reason and common fairness (which is the standard that God has set for the actions of men, for their mutual security); and so he becomes dangerous to mankind because he has disregarded and broken the tie that is meant to secure them from injury and violence. This is an offence against the whole ·human· species, and against the peace and safety that the law of nature provides for the species. Now, every man, by the right he has to preserve mankind in general, may restrain and if necessary destroy things that are noxious to mankind; and so he can do to anyone who has transgressed that law as much harm as may make him repent having done it, and thereby deter him—and by his example deter others—from doing the same. So for this reason every man has a right to enforce the law of nature and punish offenders.

4

Second Treatise John Locke 2: The state of nature

9. No doubt this will seem a very strange doctrine to some people; but before they condemn it, I challenge them to explain what right any king or state has to put to death or ·otherwise· punish a foreigner for a crime he commits in their country. The right is certainly not based on their laws, through any permission they get from the announced will of the legislature; for such announcements don’t get through to a foreigner: they aren’t addressed to him, and even if they were, he isn’t obliged to listen.... Those who have the supreme power of making laws in England, France or Holland are to an Indian merely like the rest of the world, men without authority. So if the law of nature didn’t give every man a power to punish offences against it as he soberly judges the case to require, I don’t see how the judiciary of any community can punish someone from another country; because they can’t have any more power over him than every man can naturally have over another.

10. As well as •the crime that consists in violating the law and departing from the right rule of reason—crime through which man becomes so degenerate that he declares that he is deserting the principles of human nature and becoming vermin—there is often •transgression through which someone does harm to someone else. In the latter case, the person who has been harmed has, in addition to the general right of punishment that he shares with everyone else, a particular right to seek reparation from the person who harmed him; and anyone else who thinks this just may also join with the injured party and help him to recover from the offender such damages as may make satisfaction for the harm he has suffered.

11. So there are two distinct rights: (i) the right that everyone has, to punish the criminal so as to restrain him and prevent such offences in future; (ii) the right that an injured party has to get reparation. Now, a magistrate, who by being magistrate has the common right of punishing put into his hands, can by his own authority (i) cancel the punishment of a criminal offence in a case where the public good doesn’t demand that the law be enforced; but he can’t (ii) cancel the satisfaction due to any private man for the damage he has received. The only one who can do that is the person who has been harmed. The injured party has the power of taking for himself the goods or service of the offender, by right of •self-preservation; and everyone has a power to punish the crime to prevent its being committed again, by the right he has of preserving •all mankind, and doing everything reasonable that he can to that end. And so it is that in the state of nature everyone has a power to kill a murderer, both •to deter others from this crime that no reparation can make up for, by the example of the punishment that everyone inflicts for it, and also •to secure men from future crimes by this criminal; he has renounced reason, the common rule and standard God has given to mankind, and by the unjust violence and slaughter he has committed on one person he has declared war against all mankind, so that he can be destroyed as though he were a lion or a tiger.... This is the basis for the great law of nature, Whoever sheds man’s blood, by man shall his blood be shed. Cain was so fully convinced that everyone had a right to destroy such a criminal that after murdering his brother he cried out ‘Anyone who finds me will slay me’—so plainly was this law written in the hearts of all mankind.

12. For the same reason a man in the state of nature may punish lesser breaches of the law of nature. ‘By death?’ you may ask. I answer that each offence may be punished severely enough to make it a bad bargain for the offender, to give him reason to repent, and to terrify others from offending in the same way. Every offence that can be •committed in

5

Second Treatise John Locke 2: The state of nature

the state of nature may also be •punished in the state of nature—and punished in the same way (as far as possible) as it would be in a commonwealth. I don’t want to go into the details of the law of nature or of its punitive measures, ·but I will say this much·:- It is certain that there is a •law of nature, which is as intelligible and plain to a reasonable person who studies it as are the •positive laws of commonwealths. [See the explanation of ‘positive’ after section 1.] It may even be plainer—as much plainer as •reason is ·plainer·, easier to understand, than the fancies and intricate ·theoretical· contrivances of men who have tried to find words that will further their conflicting hidden interests. For that is what has gone into the devising of most of the legislated laws of countries. Really, such laws are right only to the extent that they are founded on the law of nature, which is the standard by which they should be applied and interpreted.

13. To this strange doctrine ·of mine·, namely that in the state of nature everyone has the power to enforce the law of nature, I expect this objection to be raised:

It is unreasonable for men to be judges in their own cases, because self-love will bias men in favour of themselves and their friends. And on the other side, hostility, passion and revenge will lead them to punish others too severely. So nothing but confusion and disorder will follow, and that is why God has—as he certainly has—established government to restrain the partiality and violence of men.

I freely allow that civil government is the proper remedy for the drawbacks of the state of nature. There must certainly be great disadvantages in a state where men may be judges in their own case; someone who was so •unjust as to do his brother an injury will (we may well suppose) hardly be so •just as to condemn himself for it! But I respond to the objector as follows [the answer runs to the end of the section]:- If the state of nature is intolerable because of the evils that are bound to follow from men’s being judges in their own cases, and government is to be the remedy for this, ·let us do a comparison·. On the one side there is the •state of nature; on the other there is

•government where one man—and remember that absolute monarchs are only men!—commands a multitude, is free to be the judge in his own case, and can do what he likes to all his subjects, with no-one being allowed to question or control those who carry out his wishes, and everyone having to put up with whatever he does, whether he is led by reason, mistake or passion.

How much better it is in the state of nature, where no man is obliged to submit to the unjust will of someone else, and someone who judges wrongly (whether or not it is in his own case) is answerable for that to the rest of mankind!

14. It is often asked, as though this were a mighty objection: ‘Where are there—where ever were there—any men in such a state of nature?’ Here is an answer that may suffice in the mean time:- The world always did and always will have many men in the state of nature, because all monarchs and rulers of independent governments throughout the world are in that state. I include in this all who govern independent communities, whether or not they are in league with others; for the state of nature between men isn’t ended just by their making a pact with one another. The only pact that ends the state of nature is one in which men agree together mutually to enter into one community and make one body politic.... The promises and bargains involved in bartering between two men on a desert island,....or between a Swiss and an Indian in the woods of America, are binding on them even though they are perfectly in a state of nature in relation to one another; for truth and promise-keeping belongs to men

6

Second Treatise John Locke 3: The state of war

•as men, not •as members of society—·i.e. as a matter of natural law, not positive law·.

15. To those who deny that anyone was ever in the state of nature, I oppose the authority of the judicious Hooker, who writes:

The laws....of nature bind men absolutely, just as men, even if they have no settled fellowship, no solemn agreement among themselves about what to do and what not to do. What naturally leads us to seek communion and fellowship with other people is the fact that on our own we haven’t the means to provide ourselves with an adequate store of things that we need for the kind of life our nature desires, a life fit for the dignity of man. It was to make up for those defects and imperfections of the solitary life that men first united themselves in politic societies. (The Laws of Ecclesiastical Polity, Bk 1, sect. 10)

And I also affirm that all men are naturally in the state of nature, and remain so until they consent to make themselves members of some political society. I expect to make all this very clear in later parts of this discourse.

Chapter 3: The state of war

16. The state of war is a state of enmity and destruction. So when someone declares by word or action—not in a sudden outburst of rage, but as a matter of calm settled design—that he intends to end another man’s life, he puts himself into a state of war against the other person; and he thereby exposes his life to the risk of falling to the power of the •other person or anyone that joins with •him in his defence and takes up his quarrel. For it is reasonable and just that I should have a right to destroy anything that threatens me with destruction, because the fundamental law of nature says that men are to be preserved as much as possible, and that when not everyone can be preserved the safety of the innocent is to be preferred. ·In line with this·, I may destroy a man who makes war on me or has revealed himself as an enemy to my life, for the same reason that I may kill a wolf or a lion; because such men are not under the ties of the common law of reason, have no rule except that of force and violence, and so may be treated as beasts of prey—dangerous creatures that will certainly destroy me if I fall into their power.

17. So it comes about that someone who tries to get another man into his absolute power thereby puts himself into a state of war with the other, for such an attempt amounts to a declaration of a plan against the life of the other man. If someone wants to get me •into his power without my consent, I have reason to conclude that would use me as he pleased when he had got me •there, and would destroy me if he wanted to; for no-one can want to have me in his absolute power unless it’s to compel me by force to something that is against the right of my freedom, i.e. to make me a slave. To be sure of my own survival I must be free from such force; and reason tells me to look on him—the person who wants

7

Second Treatise John Locke 3: The state of war

me in his power—as an enemy to my survival, wanting to take away the freedom that is the fence to it. So someone who tries to enslave me thereby puts himself into a state of war with me. Someone wants to take away •the freedom of someone else must be supposed to have a plan to take away •everything else from the person, because freedom is the foundation of all the rest; and that holds in a commonwealth as well as in the state of nature.

18. This makes it lawful for me to kill a thief who hasn’t done me any harm or declared any plan against my life, other than using force to get me in his power so as to take away my money or whatever else he wants. No matter what he claims he is up to, he is using force without right, to get me into his power; so I have no reason to think that he won’t, when he has me in his power, take everything else away from me as well as my liberty. So it is lawful for me to treat him as someone who has put himself into a state of war with me, i.e. to kill him if I can; for that is the risk he ran when he started a war in which he is the aggressor.

19. This is the plain difference between the state of •nature and the state of •war. Some men—·notably Hobbes·—have treated them as the same; but in fact they are as distant from one another as a state of •peace, good will, mutual assistance and preservation is distant from a state of •enmity, malice, violence and mutual destruction. A state of nature, properly understood, involves

men living together according to reason, with no-one on earth who stands above them both and has authority to judge between them.

Whereas in a state of war

a man uses or declares his intention to use force against another man, with no-one on earth to whom the other can appeal for relief.

It is the lack of such an appeal that gives a man the right of war against an aggressor, ·not only in a state of nature but· even if they are both subjects in a single society. [The rest of this section expands on Locke’s version in ways that ·dots· can’t easily indicate.] If a thief has already stolen all that I am worth and is not a continuing threat to me, I may not harm him except through an appeal to the law. But if he is now setting on me to rob me—even if it’s just my horse or my coat that he is after—I may kill him. There is the law, which was made for my protection, but there is no time for it to intervene to save me from losing my goods and perhaps losing my life (and if I lose that there is no reparation). Furthermore, it is the thief’s fault that there is no time for an appeal to the judge that stands over him and me—namely, the law—and so I am allowed to make my own defence, and to be at war with the thief and to kill him if I can. What puts men into a state of nature is the lack of a common judge who has authority; the use of unlawful force against a man’s person creates a state of war, whether or not there is a common judge and (therefore) whether or not they are in a state of nature.

20. But for men who are in a society ·under a government·, the state of war ends when the actual force ends; and then those on each side ·of the trouble· should equally submit to the fair determination of the law.... But in the state of nature, where there are no positive laws or judges with authority to appeal to, once a state of war has begun it continues—with the innocent party having a right to destroy the other if he can—until the aggressor offers peace, and seeks reconciliation on terms that will make up for any wrongs he has done and will give the innocent person security from then on. What if the situation is like this?

There is time and opportunity for an appeal to the law, and to legally constituted judges, but the remedy is not available because of a manifest perverting

8

Second Treatise John Locke 4: Slavery

of justice, a barefaced twisting of the laws so that they protect or even reward the violence or injuries perpetrated by some men or some party of men.

In such a case it is hard to think we have anything but a state of war. For wherever violence is used and injury done, even if it is done by people appointed to administer justice and is dressed up in the name, claims, or forms of law, it is still violence and injury. The purpose of the law is to protect and get compensation for the innocent, by an unbiased treatment of all who come under it; and when this is not genuinely done, war is made upon the sufferers, and they—having nowhere on earth to appeal to for justice—are left to the only remedy in such cases, an appeal to heaven.

21. ·In a state of nature· where there is no authority to decide between contenders, and the only appeal is to heaven, every little difference is apt to end up in war; and that is one great reason for men to put themselves into society, and leave the state of nature. For where there is an authority, a power on earth from which relief can be had by appeal, the controversy is decided by that power and the state of war is blocked. [The remainder of the section discusses, in the light of this, a passage in the Old Testament, Judges xi.]

Chapter 4: Slavery

22. The •natural liberty of man is

to be free from any superior power on earth, and not to be under the will or legislative authority of men but to be ruled only by the law of nature.

The liberty of man •in society is

to be under no legislative power except the one established by consent in the commonwealth; and not under the power of any will or under restraint from any law except what is enacted by the legislature in accordance with its mandate.

Freedom then is not what Sir Robert Filmer tells us (Observations on Hobbes, Milton, etc., page 55), namely a liberty for everyone to do what he wants, live as he pleases, and not be tied by any laws. Rather, ·freedom is one of two things·. •Freedom of nature is being under no restraint except the law of nature. •Freedom of men under government is having a standing rule to live by, common to everyone in the society in question, and made by the legislative power that has been set up in it; a liberty to follow one’s own will in anything that isn’t forbidden by the rule, and not to be subject to the inconstant, uncertain, unknown, arbitrary will of another man. [Here and elsewhere, Locke uses ‘arbitrary’ not in our current sense of something like •‘decided for no reason’ or ‘decided on a whim’ or the like; but rather in a broader sense, current in his day, as meaning merely •‘decided’ or ‘depending upon someone’s choice’. In that older and weaker sense of the word, the fear of being under someone’s ‘arbitrary will’ is just a fear of being at the mercy of whatever he chooses to do to you, whether or not his choice is ‘arbitrary’ in the now-current sense.]

23. [In this section Locke writes that a man doesn’t have the power to take his own life. He presumably means that a man

9

Second Treatise John Locke 5: Property

may not rightly take his own life because the fundamental law of nature says that men are to be preserved as much as possible (section 16). He continues:] This freedom from absolute, arbitrary power, is so necessary to a man’s survival, so tightly tied to it, that losing it involves losing ·all control over· his own life. ·That’s why no-one can voluntarily enter into slavery·. A man doesn’t have the power to take his own life, so he can’t voluntarily enslave himself to anyone, or put himself under the absolute, arbitrary power of •someone else to take away his life whenever •he pleases. Nobody can give more power than he has; so someone who cannot take away his own life cannot give someone else such a power over it. If someone performs an act that deserves death, he has by his own fault forfeited his own life; the person to whom he has forfeited it may (when he has him in his power) delay taking it and instead make use of the offending man for his own purposes; and this isn’t doing him any wrong, because whenever he finds the hardship of his slavery to outweigh the value of his life, he has the power to resist the will of his master, thus bringing the death that he wants.

24. What I have been discussing is the condition of complete slavery, which is just a continuation of the state of war between a lawful conqueror and a captive. If they enter into any kind of pact—agreeing to limited power on the one side and obedience on the other—the state of war and slavery ceases for as long as the pact is in effect. For, as I have said, no man can by an agreement pass over to someone else something that he doesn’t himself have, namely a power over his own life.

I admit that we find among the Jews, as well as other nations, cases where men sold themselves; but clearly they sold themselves only into drudgery, not slavery. It is evident that the person who was sold wasn’t thereby put at the mercy of an absolute, arbitrary, despotic power; for the master was obliged at a certain time to let the other go free from his service, and so he couldn’t at any time have the power to kill him. Indeed the master of this kind of servant was so far from having an arbitrary power over his •life that he couldn’t arbitrarily even •maim him: the loss of an eye or a tooth set him free (Exodus xxi).

Chapter 5: Property

25. God, as King David says (Psalms cxv.16), has given the earth to the children of men—given it to mankind in common. This is clear, whether we consider •natural reason, which tells us that men, once they are born, have a right to survive and thus a right to food and drink and such other things as nature provides for their subsistence, or •revelation, which gives us an account of the grants that God made of the world to Adam and to Noah and his sons. Some people think that this creates a great difficulty about how anyone should ever come to own anything. I might answer ·that difficulty with another difficulty, saying· that if the supposition that

God gave the world to Adam and his posterity in common

makes it hard to see how •there can be any individual

10

Second Treatise John Locke 5: Property

ownership, the supposition that

God gave the world to Adam and his successive heirs, excluding all the rest of his posterity

makes it hard to see how •anything can be owned except by one universal monarch. But I shan’t rest content with that, and will try to show ·in a positive way· how men could come to own various particular parts of something that God gave to mankind in common, and how this could come about without any explicit agreement among men in general. [Here and throughout this chapter, ‘own’ will often replace Locke’s ‘have a property in’.]

26. God, who has given the world to men in common, has also given them reason to make use of it to the best advantage of life and convenience. The earth and everything in it is given to men for the support and comfort of their existence. All the fruits it naturally produces and animals that it feeds, as produced by the spontaneous hand of nature, belong to mankind in common; nobody has a basic right—a private right that excludes the rest of mankind—over any of them as they are in their natural state. But they were given for the use of men; and before they can be useful or beneficial to any particular man there must be some way for a particular man to appropriate them [= ‘come to own them’]. The wild Indians ·in north America· don’t have fences or boundaries, and are still joint tenants ·of their territory·; but if any one of them is to get any benefit from fruit or venison, the food in question must be his—and his (i.e. a part of him) in such a way that no-one else retains any right to it. [The last clause of that is puzzling. Does Locke mean that the Indian can’t directly get benefit from the venison except by eating it? That seems to be the only way to make sense of ‘part of him’; but it doesn’t fit well with the paragraph as a whole.]

27. Though •men as a whole own the earth and all inferior creatures, every •·individual· man has a property in his own person [= ‘owns himself’]; this is something that nobody else has any right to. The labour of his body and the work of his hands, we may say, are strictly his. So when he takes something from the state that nature has provided and left it in, he mixes his labour with it, thus joining to it something that is his own; and in that way he makes it his property. He has removed the item from the common state that nature has placed it in, and through this labour the item has had annexed to it something that excludes the common right of other men: for this labour is unquestionably the property of the labourer, so no other man can have a right to anything the labour is joined to—at least where there is enough, and as good, left in common for others. [Note Locke’s statement that every man ‘has a property in his own person’. He often says that the whole point of political structures is to protect ‘property’; which might be sordidly mercantile if he weren’t talking about the protection not just of man’s physical possessions but also of his life and liberty.]

28. Someone who eats the acorns he picked up under an oak, or the apples he gathered from the trees in the forest, has certainly appropriated them to himself! Nobody can deny that the nourishment is his. Well, then, when did they begin to be his?

when he digested them?
when he cooked them?
when he brought them home?
when he picked them up ·under the tree·?

It is obvious that if his first gathering didn’t make them his, nothing else could do so. That labour •marked those things off from the rest of the world’s contents; it •added something to them beyond what they had been given by nature, the common mother of all; and so they became his private right.

11

Second Treatise John Locke 5: Property

Suppose we denied this, and said instead:

He had no right to the acorns or apples that he thus appropriated, because he didn’t have the consent of all mankind to make them his. It was robbery on his part to take for himself something that belonged to all men in common.

If such a consent as that was necessary, men in general would have starved, notwithstanding the plenty God had provided them with. We see ·the thesis I am defending at work in our own society·. When there is some land that has the status of a common—being held in common by the community by agreement among them—taking any part of what is common and removing it from the state nature leaves it in creates ownership; and if it didn’t, the common would be of no use. And the taking of this or that part doesn’t depend on the express consent of all the commoners [= ‘all those who share in the common ownership of the land’]. Thus when my horse bites off some grass, my servant cuts turf, or I dig up ore, in any place where I have a right to these in common with others, the grass or turf or ore becomes my property, without anyone’s giving it to me or consenting to my having it. My labour in removing it out of the common state it was in has established me as its owner.

29. If the explicit consent of every commoner was needed for anyone to appropriate to himself any part of what is given in common, children couldn’t cut into the meat their father had provided for them in common without saying which child was to have which portion. The water running in the fountain is everyone’s, but who would doubt that the water in the pitcher belongs to the person who drew it out?....

30. Thus this law of reason makes it the case that the Indian who kills a deer owns it; it is agreed to belong to the person who put his labour into it, even though until then it was the common right of everyone. Those who are counted as the civilized part of mankind have made and multiplied positive laws to settle property rights; but ·even· among us this original law of nature—the law governing how property starts when everything is held in common—still applies. [Locke concludes the section with examples: catching a fish, gathering ambergris, shooting a hare.]

31. You may object that if gathering the acorns etc. creates a right to them, then anyone may hoard as much as he likes. I answer: Not so. The very law of nature that in this way •gives us property also •sets limits to that property. God has given us all things richly.... But how far has he given them to us? To enjoy [= ‘to use, to get benefit from’; this what ‘enjoy(ment)’ usually means in this work]. Anyone can through his labour come to own as much as he can use in a beneficial way before it spoils; anything beyond this is more than his share and belongs to others. Nothing was made by God for man to spoil or destroy. For a long time •there could be little room for quarrels or contentions about property established on this basis: •there was an abundance of natural provisions and few users of them; and •only a small part of that abundance could be marked off by the industry of one man and hoarded up to the disadvantage of others—especially keeping within the bounds (set by reason) of what he could actually use.

32. But these days the chief issue about property concerns the earth itself rather than the plants and animals that live on it, because when you own some of the earth you own what lives on it as well. I think it is clear that ownership of land is acquired in the same way that I have been describing. A man owns whatever land he tills, plants, improves, cultivates, and can use the products of. By his labour he as it were fences off that land from all that is held in common. Suppose someone objected:

12

Second Treatise John Locke 5: Property

He has no valid right to the land, because everyone else has an equal title to it. So he can’t appropriate it, he can’t ‘fence it off’, without the consent of all his fellow-commoners, all mankind.

That is wrong. When God gave the world in common to all mankind, he •commanded man to work, and •man needed to work in order to survive. So •God and •his reason commanded man to subdue the earth, i.e. to improve it for the benefit of life; and in doing that he expended something that was his own, namely •his labour. A man who in obedience to this command of God subdued, tilled and sowed any part of the earth’s surface thereby joined to that land something that was •his property, something that no-one else had any title to or could rightfully take from him.

33. This appropriation of a plot of land by improving it wasn’t done at the expense of any other man, because there was still enough (and as good) left for others—more than enough for the use of the people who weren’t yet provided for. In effect, the man who ·by his labour· ‘fenced off’ some land didn’t reduce the amount of land that was left for everyone else: someone who leaves as much as anyone else can make use of does as good as take nothing at all. Nobody could think he had been harmed by someone else’s taking a long drink of water, if there was the whole river of the same water left for him to quench his thirst; and the ·ownership issues concerning· land and water, where there is enough of both, are exactly the same.

34. God gave the world to men in common; but since he gave it them for their benefit and for the greatest conveniences of life they could get from it, he can’t have meant it always to remain common and uncultivated. He gave it for the use of the reasonable and hard-working man (and labour was to be his title to it), not to the whims or the greed of the man who is quarrelsome and contentious. Someone who had land left for his improvement—land as good as what had already been taken up—had no need to complain and ought not to concern himself with what had already been improved by someone else’s labour. If he did, it would be obvious that he wanted the benefit of someone else’s work, to which he had no right, rather than the ground that God had given him in common with others to labour on....

35. In countries such as England ·now·, where there are many people living under a government, and where there is money and commerce, no-one can enclose or appropriate any part of any common land without the consent of all his fellow-commoners. That is because land that is held in common has that status by compact, i.e. by the law of the land, which is not to be violated. Also, although such land is held in common by some men, it isn’t held by all mankind; rather, it is the joint property of this county or this village. Furthermore, after such an enclosure—·such a ‘fencing off’·—what was left would not, from the point of view of the rest of the commoners, be ‘as good’ as the whole was when they could all make use of the whole. This is quite unlike how things stood when that great common, the world, was just starting and being populated. The law that man was under at that time was in favour of appropriating. God ordered man to work, and his wants forced him to do so. That was his property, which couldn’t be taken from him wherever he had fixed it [those five words are Locke’s]. And so we see that •subduing or cultivating the earth and •having dominion [here = ‘rightful control’] are joined together, the former creating the right to the latter....

36. Nature did well in setting limits to private property through limits to how much men can work and limits to how much they need. No man’s labour could tame or appropriate

13

Second Treatise John Locke 5: Property

all the land; no man’s enjoyment could consume more than a small part; so that it was impossible for any man in this way to infringe on the right of another, or acquire a property to the disadvantage of his neighbour.... This measure confined every man’s possessions to a very moderate proportion, such as he might make his own without harming anyone else, in the first ages of the world when men were more in danger of •getting lost by wandering off on their own in the vast wilderness of the earth as it was then than of •being squeezed for lack of land to cultivate. And, full as the world now seems, the rule for land-ownership can still be adopted without harm to anyone. Suppose a family in the state people were in when the world was first being populated by the children of Adam, or of Noah: let them plant on some vacant land in the interior of America. We’ll find that the possessions they could acquire, by the rule I have given, would not be very large, and even today they wouldn’t adversely affect the rest of mankind, or give them reason to complain or think themselves harmed by this family’s encroachment. I maintain this despite the fact that the human race has spread itself to all the corners of the world, and infinitely outnumbers those who were here at the beginning. Indeed, the extent of ground is of so little value when not worked on that I have been told that in Spain a man may be permitted to plough, sow and reap on land to which his only title is that he is making use of it.... Be this as it may (and I don’t insist on it), I venture to assert boldly that if it weren’t for just one thing the same rule of ownership—namely that every man is to own as much as he could make use of—would still hold in the world, without inconveniencing anybody, because there is land enough in the world to suffice twice as many people as there are. The ‘one thing’ that blocks this is the invention of money, and men’s tacit agreement to put a value on it; this made it possible, with men’s consent, to have larger possessions and to have a right to them. I now proceed to show how this has come about.

37. Men came to want more than they needed, and this altered the intrinsic value of things: a thing’s value originally depended only on its usefulness to the life of man; but men came to agree that a little piece of yellow metal—which wouldn’t fade or rot or rust—should be worth a great lump of flesh or a whole heap of corn. Before all that happened, each man could appropriate by his labour as much of the things of nature as he could use, without detriment to others, because an equal abundance was still left to those who would work as hard on it. ·Locke now moves away from the just-announced topic of money, and won’t return to it until section 46.· To which let me add that someone who comes to own land through his labour doesn’t •lessen the common stock of mankind but •increases it. That’s because the life-support provisions produced by one acre of enclosed and cultivated land, are (to put it very mildly) ten times more than what would come from an acre of equally rich land that was helkd in common and not cultivated. So he who encloses land, and gets more of the conveniences of life from ten ·cultivated· acres than he could have had from a hundred left to nature, can truly be said to give ninety acres to mankind. For his labour now supplies him with provisions out of ten acres that would have needed a hundred ·uncultivated· acres lying in common. I have here greatly understated the productivity of improved land, setting it at ten to one when really it is much nearer a hundred to one. [Locke defends this by comparing a thousand acres of ‘the wild woods and uncultivated waste of America’ with ‘ten acres of equally fertile land in Devonshire, where they are well cultivated’.]

[He then starts a fresh point: before land was owned, someone could by gathering fruit or hunting animals come to own those things, because of the labour he had put into them.

14

Second Treatise John Locke 5: Property

But] if they perished in his possession without having been properly used—if the fruits rotted or the venison putrified before he could use it—he offended against the common law of nature, and was liable to be punished. For he had encroached on his neighbour’s share, because he had no right to these things beyond what use they could be to him to afford him conveniences of life.

38. The same rule governed the possession of land too: he had his own particular right to whatever grass etc. that he sowed, reaped, stored, and made use of before it spoiled; and to whatever animals he enclosed, fed, and made use of. But if the grass of his enclosure rotted on the ground, or the fruit of his planting perished without being harvested and stored, this part of the earth was still to be looked on as waste-land that might be owned by anyone else—despite the fact that he had enclosed it. Thus, at the beginning, Cain might take as much ground as he could cultivate and make it his own land, still leaving enough for Abel’s sheep to feed on; a few acres would serve for both. But as families increased and by hard work enlarged their stocks, their possessions enlarged correspondingly; but this commonly happened without any fixed ownership of the land they made use of. In due course they formed into groups, settled themselves together, and built cities; and then eventually they set out the bounds of their distinct territories, agreed on boundaries between them and their neighbours, and established laws of their own to settle property-rights within the society. ·These land-ownership developments came relatively late·. For we see that in the part of the world that was first inhabited and was therefore probably the most densely populated, even as late as Abraham’s time they wandered freely up and down with the flocks and herds that they lived on; and Abraham did this ·even· in a country where he was a foreigner. This shows clearly that a great part of the land, at least, lay in common; that the inhabitants didn’t value it or claim ownership of it beyond making use of it. But when there came to be insufficient grazing land in the same place, they separated and enlarged their pasture where it best suited them (as Abraham and Lot did, Genesis xiii. 5)....

39. The supposition that Adam had all to himself authority over and ownership of all the world, to the exclusion of all other men, can’t be proved, and anyway couldn’t be the basis for anyone’s property-rights ·today·. And we don’t need it. Supposing the world to have been given (as it was) to the children of men in common, we see how men’s labour could give them separate titles to different parts of it, for their private uses; with no doubts about who has what rights, and no room for quarrelling.

40. It isn’t as strange as it may seem at first glance that the •property of •labour should be able to outweigh the •community of •land. For labour affects the value of everything. Think of how an acre of land planted with tobacco or sugar, sown with wheat or barley, differs from an acre of the same land lying in common without being cultivated; you will see the improvement brought about by labour creates most of the ·extra· value ·of the former·. It would be a very conservative estimate to say that of the products of the earth that are useful to the life of man nine tenths are the effects of labour. Indeed, if we rightly estimate the various expenses that have been involved in things as they come to our use, sorting out what in them is purely due to nature and what to labour, we’ll find that in most of them ninety-nine hundredths ·of their value· should go in the ‘labour’ column.

41. [Locke here contrasts various ‘nations of the Americans’ with England; they have equally good soil, but an American ‘king’ lives worse than an English ‘day-labourer’, because the Americans don’t improve their land by labour.]

15

Second Treatise John Locke 5: Property

42. This will become clearer if we simply track some of the ordinary provisions of life through their various stages up to becoming useful to us, and see how much of their value comes from human industry. •Bread, wine and cloth are things we use daily, and we have plenty of them; but if it weren’t for the labour that is put into these more useful commodities we would have to settle for •acorns, water and leaves or skins as our food, drink and clothing. What makes

bread more valuable than acorns,

wine more valuable than water, and

cloth or silk more valuable than leaves, skins or moss,

is wholly due to labour and industry.... ·One upshot of this is that· the ground that produces the materials provides only a very small part of the final value. So small a part that even here in England land that is left wholly to nature, with no improvement through cultivation....is rightly called ‘waste’, and we shall find the benefit of it amount to little more than nothing.

This shows how much better it is to have a large population than to have a large country; and shows that the great art of government is to have the land used well, and that any ruler will quickly be safe against his neighbours if he has the wisdom—the godlike wisdom—to establish laws of liberty to protect and encourage the honest industry of his people against the oppression of power and narrowness of party. But that is by the way; I return now to the argument in hand.

43. [Locke again compares uncultivated American land with cultivated land in England, this time putting the value ratio at one to a thousand. He continues:] It is labour, then, that puts the greatest part of value upon land, without which it would scarcely be worth anything. We owe to labour the greatest part of all the land’s useful products; it is labour that makes the straw, bran, and bread of an acre of wheat more valuable than the product of an acre of equally good land that lies waste. The labour that goes into the bread we eat is not just

the ploughman’s efforts, the work of the reaper and the thresher, and the baker’s sweat,

but also

the labour of those who domesticated the oxen, who dug and shaped the iron and stones, who felled and framed the timber used in the plough, the mill, the oven, or any of the vast number of other utensils that are needed to get this corn from •sowable seed to •edible bread.

All this should be attributed to labour; as for nature and the land—they provided only the materials, which were almost worthless in their raw condition. Imagine what it would be like if every loaf of bread came to us along with a catalogue of all the contributions that labour had made to its existence! It would have to include the labour components in relevant pieces of

iron, wood, leather, bark, timber, stone, bricks, coals, lime, cloth, dyes, pitch, tar, masts, ropes, and all the materials used in the ship that brought any of the commodities used by any of the workmen in any part of the work.

It would take far too long to make such a list, if indeed it was even possible.

44. All this makes it clear that •though the things of nature are given in common, man had in himself the great foundation for ownership—namely his being master of himself, and owner of his own person and of the actions or work done by it; and that •most of what he applied to the support or comfort of his being, when invention and skills had made life more comfortable, was entirely his own and didn’t belong in common to others.

16

Second Treatise John Locke 5: Property

45. Thus labour in the beginning gave a right of ownership wherever anyone chose to employ his labour on what was held in common. For a long time the common holdings were much greater than what was individually owned, and even now they are greater than what mankind makes use of. At first, men were mainly contented with what unassisted nature offered to meet their needs, but then:

In some parts of the world (where the increase of people and animals, and the use of money, had made land scarce and thus of some value) various communities settled the bounds of their separate territories, and by laws within themselves regulated the properties of the private men in their society, and in this way by compact and agreement they settled the property rights that labour and industry had begun. And the leagues that have been made between different states and kingdoms, either explicitly or tacitly disowning all claim to one anothers’ land, have by common consent given up their claims to their natural common right in ·undeveloped· land in one anothers’ domains, and so have by positive agreement settled who owns what in various parts and parcels of the earth, ·so that, for instance, no Englishman can claim to own an acre of France because (i) it was uncultivated until he worked on it and (ii) he was not a party to ‘internal’ French laws giving its ownership to someone else·.

Even after all this, however, there are great tracts of ground that still lie in common ·and so could legitimately be claimed on the basis of labour·. These are in territories whose inhabitants haven’t joined with the rest of mankind in the consent of the use of their common money [Locke’s exact words, starting with ‘joined’], and are lands that exceed what the inhabitants do or can make use of. Though this can hardly happen among people who have agreed to use money.

46. Most of the things useful to the life of man—things that the world’s first commoners, like the Americans even now, were forced to seek for their sheer survival—are things of short duration, things that will decay and perish if they are not consumed soon. ·The much more durable· gold, silver and diamonds are things that have value by agreement rather than because there is a real use for them in sustaining life. ·I shall now explain how those two kinds of value came to be linked·. Of the good things that nature has provided in common, everyone had a right (as I have said) to as much as he could use. Each man owned everything that •he could bring about with his labour, everything that •his industry could alter from the state nature had put it in. He who gathered a hundred bushels of acorns or apples thereby owned them; as soon as he had gathered them, they were his. His only obligation was to be sure that he used them before they spoiled, for otherwise he took more than his share, and robbed others. And indeed it was foolish as well as dishonest to hoard up more than he could use. ·Now consider a graded trio of cases·. (i) If he gave away some to someone else, so that it didn’t perish uselessly in his possession, that was one way of using it. (ii) And if he traded plums that would have rotted in a week for nuts that would remain eatable for a year, he wasn’t harming anyone. As long as nothing perished uselessly in his hands, he wasn’t wasting the common stock, destroying goods that belonged to others. (iii) If he traded his store of nuts for a piece of metal that had a pleasing colour, or exchanged his sheep for shells, or his wool for a sparkling pebble or a diamond, and kept those—·the metal, shells, pebbles, diamonds·—in his possession all his life, this wasn’t encroaching on anyone else’s rights.... What would take him beyond the bounds of his rightful property was not having a great deal but letting something spoil instead of being used.

17

Second Treatise John Locke 6: Paternal power

47. That is how money came into use—as a durable thing that men could keep without its spoiling, and that by mutual consent men would take in exchange for the truly useful but perishable supports of life.

48. And as differences in how hard men worked were apt to make differences in how much they owned, so this invention of money gave them the opportunity to continue and enlarge their possessions. Consider this possibility:

An island separated from any possibility of trade with the rest of the world; only a hundred families on the island; but enough sheep, horses and cows and other useful animals, enough wholesome fruits, and enough land for corn, for a hundred thousand times as many; but nothing on the island that is rare and durable enough to serve as money.

On such an island, what reason could anyone have to enlarge his possessions beyond the needs of his household, these being met by his own industry and/or trade with other households for similarly perishable and useful commodities? Men won’t be apt to enlarge their possessions of land—however rich and available extra land may be—if there isn’t something durable and scarce and ·counted as· valuable to store up. Suppose someone has the opportunity to come to own ten thousand (or a hundred thousand) acres of excellent land, already cultivated and well stocked with cattle, in the middle of the interior of America where he has no hopes of commerce with other parts of the world through which to get money through the sale of the product. What value will he attach to this estate? It wouldn’t be worth his while to mark its boundaries; he will hand it back to the wild common of nature, apart from what it would supply for the conveniences of life to be had there for him and his family.

49. Thus in the beginning all the world was America—even more so than America is now, because in the beginning no such thing as money was known anywhere. Find out something that has the use and value of money among a man’s neighbours and you’ll see him start to enlarge his possessions.

50. [In this section Locke goes over it again: by tacitly agreeing to attach value to gold, silver or other money, men have found a way for someone to own more than he can use. He concludes with the remark that ‘in governments, the laws regulate the right of property, and the possession of land is determined by positive constitutions’ (see note on ‘positive’ at the end of section 1).

51. It is easy to conceive, then, how labour could at first create ownership of some of the common things of nature, and how uses we could make of those things set limits to what could be owned ·by any individual·. So there couldn’t be any reason for quarrelling about title, or any doubt about how much could be owned. •Right and •convenience went together; for as a man had a •right to all he could employ his labour upon, so he had •no temptation to labour for more than he could use. This left no room for controversy about the title, or for encroachment on the rights of others: what portion a man carved out for himself was easily seen; and it was useless as well as dishonest for him to carve out too much or take more than he needed.

18

Second Treatise John Locke 6: Paternal power

Chapter 6: Paternal power

52. You may think that a work like the present one is not the place for complaints about words and names that have become current; but I think it won’t be amiss to offer new words when the old ones are apt to lead men into mistakes. The phrase ‘paternal power’ is probably an example of this. It seems so to place the power of parents over their children wholly in the father, as though the mother had no share in it; whereas •reason and •revelation both tell us that she has an equal title. Might it not be better to call it ‘parental power’? Whatever obligations are laid on children by •nature and the right of generation must certainly bind them equally to each of the joint causes of their being generated. And accordingly we see the •positive law of God everywhere joins the parents together, without distinction, when it commands the obedience of children. [Locke gives four examples, from the old and new testaments.]

53. Had just this one thing been thought about properly, even without going any deeper, it might have kept men from running into the gross mistakes they have made about this power of parents. When under the label ‘paternal power’ it seemed to belong only to the father, it could be described as ‘absolute dominion’ and as ‘regal authority’ without seeming ridiculous; but those phrases would have sounded strange, and in the very name shown the absurdity ·of the doctrine in question·, if this supposed absolute power over children had been called ‘parental’, for that would have given away the fact that it belonged to the mother too. Those who contend so much for ‘the absolute power and authority of fatherhood’, as they call it, will be in difficulties if the mother is given any share in it. The monarchy they contend for wouldn’t be well supported if the very name showed that the fundamental authority from which they want to derive their government by only a single person belonged not to one person but to two! But no more about names.

54. I said in Chapter 2 that all men are by nature equal, but of course I didn’t mean equality in all respects. •Age or virtue may put some men above others; •excellence of ability and merit may raise others above the common level; •some may naturally owe deference to others because of their birth, or from gratitude because of benefits they have received, or for other reasons. But all this is consistent with the equality that all men have in respect of jurisdiction or dominion over one another. That was the equality I spoke of in Chapter 2—the equality that is relevant to the business in hand, namely the equal right that every man has to his natural freedom,without being subjected to the will or authority of any other man.

55. I acknowledge that children are not born in this state of full equality, though they are born to it. Their parents have a sort of rule and jurisdiction over them when they come into the world and for some time after that, but it’s only a temporary one. The bonds of this subjection are like the swaddling clothes they are wrapped up in and supported by in the weakness of their infancy; as the child grows up, age and reason loosen the ties, until at last they drop off altogether and leave a man to his own devices.

56. Adam was created as a complete man, his body and mind in full possession of their strength and reason; so he was able, from the first instant of his coming into existence, to provide for his own support and survival, and to govern his actions according to the dictates of the law of reason that God had implanted in him. The world has been populated

19

Second Treatise John Locke 6: Paternal power

with his descendants, who are all born infants, weak and helpless, without knowledge or understanding. To make up for the defects of this imperfect [here = ‘incomplete’] state until till the improvement of growth and age has removed them, Adam and Eve and all parents after them were obliged by the law of nature to preserve, nourish, and bring up the children they had begotten—not as their own workmanship, but as the workmanship of their own maker, the almighty ·God·, to whom they were to be accountable for them.

57. The law that was to govern Adam was the very one that was to govern all his posterity, namely the law of reason. But his offspring entered the world differently from him, namely by natural birth, which brought them out ignorant and without the use of reason. So they were not immediately under the law of reason, because nobody can be under a law that hasn’t been made known to him; and this law is made known only by reason, so that someone who hasn’t come to the use of his reason can’t be said to be under it. Adam’s children, not being under this law at birth, were not free at that time; for law, properly understood, is not so much the •limitation as the •direction of a free and intelligent agent to his proper interest, and doesn’t prescribe anything that isn’t for the general good of those under that law. If men could be happier without it, the law would be a useless thing and would inevitably vanish. ·Don’t think of the law as confining·: it is wrong to label as ‘confinement’ something that hedges us in only from bogs and precipices! So, however much people may get this wrong, what law is for is not to abolish or restrain freedom but to preserve and enlarge it; for in all the states of created beings who are capable of laws, where there is no law there is no freedom. Liberty is freedom from restraint and violence by others; and this can’t be had where there is no law. This freedom is not—as some say it is—a freedom for every man to do whatever he wants to do (for who could be free if every other man’s whims might dominate him?); rather, it is a freedom to dispose in any way he wants of his person, his actions, his possessions, and his whole property—not to be subject in any of this to the arbitrary will of anyone else but freely to follow his own will, all within whatever limits are set by the laws that he is under.

58. So the •power that parents have over their children arises from their •duty to take care of their offspring during the imperfect state of childhood. What the children need, and what the parents are obliged to provide, is the forming of their minds and the governing of their actions; that is while the children are still young and ignorant; when reason comes into play the parents are released from that trouble. God gave man an understanding to direct his actions, and (fitting in with that) allowed him a freedom of will and of acting within the limits set by the law he is under. But while he is in a condition in which he hasn’t enough understanding of his own to direct his will, he isn’t to have any will of his own to follow. The person who •understands for him must •will for him too; that person must prescribe to his will and regulate his actions; but when he reaches the condition that made his father a freeman, the son is a freeman too.

59. This holds in all the laws a man is under, whether •natural or •civil. ·Let us look at these separately·. •If a man is under the law of nature, what made him free under that law? What gave him freedom to dispose of his property according to his own will, within the limits set by that law? I answer, a state of maturity in which he might be supposed to be capable of knowing that law so that he could keep his actions within the limits set by it. When he has entered that state, he is presumed to know how far that law is to be his guide, and how far he may make use of his freedom; and so he comes to have that freedom. Until then, he must be

20

Second Treatise John Locke 6: Paternal power

guided by somebody else who is presumed to know how far the law allows a liberty. If such a state of reason, such an age of discretion, made him free, the same state will make his son free too. •If a man is under the law of England, what made him free under that law? That is, what gave him the liberty to dispose of his actions and possessions as he wishes, within the limits of what that law allows? ·I answer·, a capacity for knowing that law—a capacity which the law itself supposes to be present at the age of twenty-one and in some cases sooner. If this made the father free, it will make the son free too. Till then we see the law allows the son to have no will: he is to be guided by the will of his father or guardian, who is to do his understanding for him. And if the father dies and fails to substitute a deputy in his place, or if he doesn’t provide a tutor to govern his son while he is a minor who lacks understanding, the law takes care to do it. Someone else must govern him and be a will to him until he has reached a state of freedom, and his understanding has become fit to take over the government of his will. But after that the father and son are equally free, as are a tutor and his pupil after the pupil has grown up. They are equally subjects of the same law together, and the father has no remaining dominion over the life, liberty, or estate of his son. This holds, whether they are only in the state of nature and under its law or are under the positive laws of an established government.

60. But if, through defects that happen out of the ordinary course of nature, someone never achieves a degree of reason that would make him capable of knowing the law and so living within the rules of it, he is never capable of being a free man, he is never allowed freely to follow his own will (because he knows no bounds to it, doesn’t have the understanding that is the will’s proper guide), but continues under the tuition and government of others for as long as his own understanding is incapable of taking over. And so lunatics and idiots are never freed from the government of their parents. [The section continues with a quotation from Hooker, saying the same thing, and the remark that all this comes from a duty—given by nature and by God—to preserve one’s offspring, and hardly gives proof that parents have ‘regal authority’.]

61. Thus we are born •free, as we are born •rational; not that we as newborn babies actually have the use of either: age that brings •reason brings •freedom with it. So we see how •natural •freedom is consistent with •subjection to parents, both being based on the same principle. A child is free by his father’s title, by his father’s understanding, which is to govern him till he has understanding of his own. The •freedom of a mature man and the •subjection of a not yet mature child to his parents are so consistent with one another, and so distinguishable, that the most blinded contenders for monarchy-by-right-of-fatherhood can’t miss this difference; the most obstinate of them can’t maintain that the two are inconsistent. ·I now show their consistency with one another within the context of Filmer’s theory of monarchy·. Suppose their doctrine ·of monarchy· were all true, and the right ·contemporary· heir of Adam were now known and by that title settled as a monarch on his throne, invested with all the absolute unlimited power that Sir Robert Filmer talks of. If this monarch were to die just after his heir was born, wouldn’t the child—however free and sovereign he was—be subject to his mother and nurse, to tutors and governors, till age and education brought him reason and the ability to govern himself and others? The necessities of his life, the health of his body, and the forming of his mind, would all require that he be directed by the will of others and not by his own will. But will anyone think that this restraint and subjection would be inconsistent with (or deprived him

21

Second Treatise John Locke 6: Paternal power

of) the liberty or sovereignty that he had a right to, or gave away his empire to those who had the government of him in his youth? This government over him would only prepare him the better and sooner for being a governor of others. If anybody should ask me when my son is of age to be free, I would answer: Just when his monarch is of age to govern! As for determining when a man can be said to have achieved enough use of reason to be capable of ·understanding and obeying· those laws whereby he is then bound: this, says the judicious Hooker (Ecclesiastical Polity, Book 1, section 6), is a great deal easier for sense to discern than for anyone by skill and learning to determine [= roughly ‘easier to tell by experience of particular cases than to lay down in general theoretical terms’].

62. Commonwealths themselves allow that there is an age at which men are to begin to act like free men, so that before that age they aren’t required to take oaths of allegiance or in any other way to declare the authority of the government of their countries.

63. So a man’s freedom—his liberty of acting according to his own will—is based on his having reason, which can instruct him in the law he is to govern himself by, and make him know to what extent he is left to the freedom of his own will. To turn him loose and give him complete liberty before he has reason to guide him is not allowing him his natural privilege of being free; rather, it is pushing him out among the lower animals and abandoning him to a state as wretched and sub-human as theirs is. This is what gives parents the authority to govern their children while they are minors. God has made it their business to take this care of their offspring, and has built into them tendencies to gentleness and concern so as to moderate this power, so that they will use the power, for as long as the children need to be under it, for the children’s good.

64. But what reason can there be to expand the care that parents owe to their offspring into an absolute arbitrary command of the father? In fact, a father’s power reaches only far enough to •impose the discipline that he finds effective in giving his children the strong and healthy bodies and vigorous and right-thinking minds that will best fit them to be most useful to themselves and others; and, if it is necessary in the family’s circumstances, •to make them work, when they are able, for their own livelihood. But in this power the mother too has her share with the father.

65. Indeed, this power is so far from being something that the father has by a special right of nature, rather than having it in his role as the guardian of his children, that when his care of them comes to an end so does his power over them. That power is inseparably tied to their nourishment and upbringing; and it belongs as much to the foster-father of an abandoned baby as to the natural father of another child. That’s how little power the bare act of begetting gives a man over his offspring: if all his care ends there, and his only claim on the name and authority of a father is that he begot the child, ·his power comes to nothing·. And what will become of this paternal power in places where one woman has more than one husband at a time? or in the parts of America where when the husband and wife separate (which happens frequently) the children all stay with the mother and are wholly cared for and provided for by her? If a father dies while the children are young, don’t they naturally everywhere owe the same obedience to their mother, during their minority, as they would to their father if he were still alive? ·Obviously they do! And then, with ‘paternal power’ replaced by ‘maternal power’, the idea that governmental power comes from this source becomes even more clearly

22

Second Treatise John Locke 6: Paternal power

incredible. For consider·: Will anyone say that the ·widowed· mother has a legislative power over her children? that she can make laws that will oblige the children throughout their lives, regulating all matters having to do with property and freedom of action? and that she can enforce the observation of these laws with capital punishments? All of that lies within the legitimate scope of the law-giver, and the father doesn’t have even the shadow of it!. His command over his children is only temporary, and doesn’t affect their life or property. [Locke continues in this vein, repeating points already made.]

66. But though in due course a child comes to be as free from subjection to the will and command of his father as the father himself is free from subjection to the will of anyone else, and each of them is under only the restraints that also bind the other—from the law of nature and from the civil law of their country—this freedom that the son has doesn’t exempt him from honouring his parents as he is required to do by the law of God and nature. God having •made the parents through their having children serve as instruments in his great design of continuing the race of mankind, •laid on them an obligation to nourish, preserve, and bring up their offspring, and also •laid on children a perpetual obligation to honour their parents. This honour involves an inward esteem and reverence to be shown by all outward expressions, so it holds the child back from anything that might ever injure or offend, disturb or endanger, the happiness or life of those from whom he received his own life; and draws him into doing all he can for the defence, relief, assistance and comfort of those by whose means he came into existence and has been made capable of enjoying life. No state—and no kind of freedom—can free children from this obligation. But this is very far from giving parents a power of command over their children, or an authority to make laws and dispose as they please of the children’s lives or liberties. It is one thing to be owed honour, respect, gratitude and assistance; another to require absolute obedience and submission. A monarch on his throne owes his mother the honour any son owes his parents, but this doesn’t lessen his authority or entitle her to govern him.

67. Consider these two facts: (1) While a child is a minor, its father is temporarily in the position of a governor—a position that ends when the child becomes an adult. (2) The child’s duty of honour gives the parents a perpetual right to respect, reverence, support and compliance too, in proportion to how much care, cost, and kindness the father has put into the child’s upbringing. This doesn’t end with minority, but holds throughout a man’s life. The failure to distinguish these two powers, namely

•the father’s right of upbringing during minority, and •the parent’s right to be honoured, throughout his life,

may have caused a great part of the mistakes about this matter. ·But they are utterly different from one another·. Strictly speaking, the first of them is not really a •right of parental power but rather a privilege of children and a •duty of parents. The nourishment and education of their children is so much a duty of parents that nothing can absolve them from performing it; and though the power of commanding and punishing children goes along with the duty, God has woven into the forces at work in human nature such a tenderness for offspring that there is little risk of parents using their power too severely.... [Sections 68–71 repeat and decorate the main themes of the chapter up to here, without adding significant content.]

72. ·In addition to the powers of privileges discussed above·, there is another power that a father ordinarily has, which

23

Second Treatise John Locke 6: Paternal power

gives him a hold on the obedience of his children. Although men in general have this power, the occasions for using it are nearly always within the private lives of families; it seldom shows up anywhere else, and when it does it isn’t much noticed, which is why it is generally taken to be a part of paternal jurisdiction. What I am talking about is the power men generally have to leave their estates to those who please them best. Children can expect to inherit from their father, usually in certain proportions according to the law and custom of the country; but the father commonly has the power to make bequests with a more or less generous hand depending on how much each child has behaved in ways that he has agreed with and liked.

73. This gives a considerable hold on the obedience of children, ·and it connects with something that has been a main topic of this treatise, namely the place of consent in government. I shall explain·. The enjoyment of land always involves submitting to the government of the country where the land is. Now, it has commonly been supposed that a father could give his offspring a binding obligation to submit to the government of which he himself was a subject, ·but this is wrong·. The obligation to submit to a government is only a condition of owning the land; and the inheritance of an estate that is under that government reaches only those who will accept the estate when it has that condition attached to it. So it is not a natural tie or obligation, but a voluntary submission. Every man’s children are by nature as free as the man himself or any of his ancestors ever were, and while they are in that freedom they may choose what society they will join themselves to, what commonwealth they will submit to. But if they want to enjoy the inheritance of their ancestors, they must take it on the terms on which their ancestors had it, and submit to all the conditions tied to such ownership. So this power does indeed enable fathers to •oblige their children to obedience to themselves even when they are adults, and most commonly to •subject their children to this or that political power. But neither of these comes from any special right of fatherhood, but rather from owning the means to enforce and reward such compliance ·with the father’s wishes or with the laws of the commonwealth·. It is just the power that a Frenchman has over an Englishman who hopes to inherit his estate: that hope certainly creates a strong tie on his obedience ·to the Frenchman·; and if the estate is left to him, he can enjoy it only on the conditions attached to the possession of land in the country that contains it, whether it be France or England.

74..... ·Despite all this·, we can see how easy it was, at certain times and places, for the father of the family to become its monarch. This would be so when the world was young, and also today in some places where the low population makes it possible for ·the· families ·of the next generation· to spread out into the surrounding countryside and make homes for themselves in unoccupied territory. ·That creates a situation in which a considerable number of people, in a line of descent from a single living person, ‘the father’, are spread out across a considerable territory·. Without some government it would be hard for them to live together, and their common father had been a ruler from the beginning of the infancy of his children; so the adult children were most likely—whether explicitly or by tacit consent—to have him continue as ruler. The only change from the earlier state of affairs is that they •permitted the father (and no-one else in his family) to have the executive power of the law of nature, a power that every free man naturally has, and by that •permission giving him a monarchical power while they remained in it [= ‘remained in that family’?]. But this ·monarchical power within the extended family· didn’t come

24

Second Treatise John Locke 6: Paternal power

from any paternal right but purely from the consent of the adult offspring. Suppose that a foreigner comes into the family’s territory by chance or on business and, while there, kills a member of the family.... No-one doubts that in such a case the father may condemn the foreigner and punish him, with death or in some other way. just as he could punish an offence by one of his children. Now, in punishing the foreigner he can’t be exercising any paternal authority, because the foreigner is not his child; so he must be acting by virtue of the executive power of the law of nature, which he had a right to ·not as a •father but· just as a •man. Any of his adult children would also have had such a natural right if they hadn’t laid it aside and chosen to allow this dignity and authority to belong to the father and to no-one else in the family.

75. Thus it was easy, almost natural, and virtually inevitable, for children to give their tacit consent to the father’s having authority and government. They had been accustomed in their childhood to follow his direction, and to refer their little differences to him; when they were grown up, who would be fitter to rule them? They hadn’t much property, or much envy of one anothers’ goods, so their ‘little differences’ hadn’t become much bigger! Where could they find a fitter umpire than he by whose care they had all been sustained and brought up, and who had a tenderness for them all?....

76. Thus the natural fathers of families gradually became their politic monarchs as well. And when they happened to live long and to have able and worthy heirs, they laid the foundations for kingdoms—whether hereditary or elective—with various different kinds of constitutions and procedures, shaped by the effects of chance, contrivance, and particular events. But if •monarchs are entitled to their thrones because of their rights as fathers, and if •the natural right of fathers to political authority is shown by the mere fact that government has commonly been exercised by fathers, then by the very same inference we can ‘prove’ that all monarchs—and indeed only monarchs—should be priests, since it is as certain •that in the beginning the father of the family was his household’s priest as •that he was its ruler. [In a footnote to section 74 Locke quotes a long passage from Hooker, saying things similar to what Locke says in that section, and referring to ‘the ancient custom’ whereby fathers became kings and also came ‘to exercise the office of priests’.]

25

Second Treatise John Locke 7: Political or Civil Society

Chapter 7: Political or Civil Society

··CONJUGAL SOCIETY··
77. God having made man as a creature who, in God’s own judgment, ought not to be alone, •drew him strongly—by need, convenience, and inclination—into society, and •equipped him with understanding and language to keep society going and to enjoy it. The first society was between man and wife, which gave rise to the society between parents and children; to which in time the society between master and servant came to be added. All these could and often did meet together, and constitute a single family in which the master or mistress had some appropriate sort of authority. [In Locke’s day ‘family’ commonly meant ‘household’, i.e. including the servants.] Each of these smaller societies, like the larger one of the entire household, fell short of being a political society, as we shall see if we consider the different ends, ties, and bounds of each of them.

78. Conjugal society is made by a voluntary compact between man and woman. It mainly consists in the togetherness of bodies and right of access to one another’s bodies that is needed for procreation, which is its main purpose; but it brings with it mutual support and assistance, and a togetherness of interests too, this being needed to unite their care and affection and also needed by their offspring, who have a right to be nourished and maintained by them till they are old enough to provide for themselves.

79. The purpose of bonding between male and female is not just •procreation but •the continuation of the species; ·meaning that it’s not just to have children but to bring them up·; so this link between male and female ought to last beyond procreation, so long as is needed for the nourishment and support of the young ones.... This rule that our infinite wise maker has imposed on his creatures can be seen to be regularly obeyed by the lower animals. In viviparous animals that feed on grass, the bonding of male with female lasts no longer than the mere act of copulation; because the female’s teat is sufficient to nourish the young until they can feed on grass, all the male has to do is to beget [= ‘to impregnate the female’], and doesn’t concern himself with the female or with the young, to whose nourishment he can’t contribute anything. But in beasts of prey the conjunction lasts longer, because the dam isn’t able to survive and to nourish her numerous offspring by her own prey alone, this being a more laborious way of living than feeding on grass, as well as a more dangerous one. So the male has to help to maintain their common family, which can’t survive unaided until the young are able to prey for themselves. This can be seen also with birds, whose young need food in the nest, so that the cock and the hen continue as mates until the young can fly, and can provide for themselves. (The only exception is some domestic birds; the cock needn’t feed and take care of the young brood because there is plenty of food.)

80. This brings us to what I think is the chief if not the only reason why the human male and female are bonded together for longer than other creatures. It is this:- Long before a human child is able to shift for itself without help from his parents, its mother can again conceive and bear another child; so that the father, who is bound to take care for those he has fathered, is obliged to continue in conjugal society with the same woman for longer than some other creatures. With creatures whose young can make their own way the time of procreation comes around again, the conjugal bond automatically dissolves and the parents are at liberty, till

26

Second Treatise John Locke 7: Political or Civil Society

Hymen [the god of marriage] at his usual anniversary season summons them again to choose new mates. We have to admire the wisdom of the great creator, who •gave man foresight and an ability to make preparations for the future as well dealing with present needs, •made it necessary that the society of man and wife should be more lasting than that of male and female among other creatures; so that their industry might be encouraged and their interests better united to make provision and lay up goods for their shared offspring—an arrangement that would be mightily disturbed if the offspring had an uncertain mixture of parentage or if conjugal society were often and easily dissolved.

81. But though there are these ties that make conjugal bonds firmer and more lasting in humans than in the other species of animals, it is still reasonable to ask:

Once procreation and upbringing have been secured, and inheritance arranged for, why shouldn’t this compact ·between man and wife· be like any other voluntary compact? That is, why shouldn’t its continuance depend on the consent of the parties, or on the elapsing of a certain period of time, or on some other condition?

·It is a reasonable question because· neither the compact itself or the purposes for which it was undertaken require that it should always be for life. (Unless of course there is a positive law ordaining that all such contracts be perpetual. [See the explanation of ‘positive’ on page 3.]

82. Though the husband and wife have a single common concern, they have different •views about things and so inevitably they will sometimes differ in what they •want to be done. The final decision on any practical question has to rest with someone, and it naturally falls to the man’s share, because he is the abler [Locke’s word] and the stronger of the two. But this applies only to things in which they have a common interest or ownership; it leaves the wife in the full and free possession of what by contract is her special right, and gives the husband no more power over her life than she has over his! The husband’s power is so far from that of an absolute monarch that the wife is in many cases free to separate from him, where natural right or their contract allows it—whether that contract is made by themselves in the state of nature, or made by the customs or laws of the country they live in. When such a separation occurs, the children go to the father or to the mother, depending on what their contract says.

83. All the •purposes of marriage can be achieved under political government as well as in the state of nature, so the civil magistrate doesn’t interfere with any of the husband’s or wife’s rights or powers that are naturally necessary for those •purposes, namely procreation and mutual support and assistance while they are together. He comes into the picture only when called upon to decide any controversy that may arise between man and wife about the purposes in question. [Locke goes on to say that ‘absolute sovereignty and power of life and death’ doesn’t naturally belong to the husband, because this isn’t needed for the purposes for which marriage exists; and that if it were needed for that, matrimony would be impossible in countries whose laws forbid any private citizen to have such authority.]

84. As for the society between parents and children, and the distinct rights and powers belonging to each: I discussed this fully enough in chapter 6, and needn’t say more about it here. I think it is obvious that conjugal society is far different from politic society.

·DOMESTIC GOVERNANCE GENERALLY·
85. ‘Master’ and ‘servant’ are names as old as history, but very different relationships can be characterized by them.

27

Second Treatise John Locke 7: Political or Civil Society

•A free man may make himself a servant to someone else by selling to him for a specified time the service that he undertakes to do, in exchange for wages he is to receive. This often puts him into the household of his master, and under its ordinary discipline, but it gives the master a power over him that is temporary and is no greater than what is contained in the contract between them. •But there is another sort of servant to which we give the special name ‘slave’. A slave is someone who, being a captive taken in a just war, is by the right of nature subjected to the absolute command and arbitrary power of his master. A slave has forfeited his life and with it his liberty; he has lost all his goods, and as a slave he is not capable of having any property; so he can’t in his condition of slavery be considered as any part of civil society, the chief purpose of which is the preservation of property.

86. Let us then consider a master of a family [= ‘household’] with all these subordinate relations of wife, children, servants, and slaves, all brought together under the ·general label of· ‘the domestic rule of a family’. This may look like a little commonwealth in its structure and rules, but it is really far from that in its constitution, its power and its purpose. [Locke goes on by saying that if it were a monarchy, it would be an extraordinarily limited one. Then:] But how a family or any other society of men differs from a political society, properly so-called, we shall best see by considering what political society is.

·POLITICAL SOCIETY·
87. As I have shown, man was born with a right to perfect freedom, and with an uncontrolled enjoyment of all the rights and privileges of the law of nature, equally with any other man or men in the world. So he has by nature a power not only •to preserve

•his property,

that is,

•his life, liberty and possessions,

against harm from other men, but •to judge and punish breaches of the law of nature by others—punishing in the manner he thinks the offence deserves, even punishing with death crimes that he thinks are so dreadful as to deserve it. But no political society can exist or survive without having in itself the power to preserve the property—and therefore to punish the offences—of all the members of that society; and so there can’t be a political society except where every one of the members has given up this natural power, passing it into the hands of the community in all cases.... With all private judgments of every particular member of the society being excluded, the community comes to be the umpire. It acts in this role •according to settled standing rules, impartially, the same to all parties; acting •through men who have authority from the community to apply those rules. This ‘umpire’ settles all the disputes that may arise between members of the society concerning any matter of right, and punishes offences that any member has committed against the society, with penalties that the law has established. This makes it easy to tell who are and who aren’t members of a political society. Those who

are united into one body with a common established law and judiciary to appeal to, with authority to decide controversies and punish offenders,

are in •civil society with one another; whereas those who

have no such common appeal (I mean: no such appeal here on earth)

are still in •the state of nature, each having to judge and to carry out the sentence, because there isn’t anyone else to do those things for him.

28

Second Treatise John Locke 7: Political or Civil Society

88. That’s how it comes about that the commonwealth has

•the power of making laws: that is, the power to set down what punishments are appropriate for what crimes that members of the society commit; and

•the power of war and peace: that is, the power to punish any harm done to any of its members by anyone who isn’t a member;

all this being done for the preservation of the property of all the members of the society, as far as is possible. [Note the broad meaning given to ‘property’ near the start of section 87.] Every man who has entered into civil society has thereby relinquished his power to punish offences against the law of nature on the basis of his own private judgment, •giving it to the legislature in all cases; and along with that he has also •given to the commonwealth a right to call on him to employ his force for the carrying out of its judgments (which are really his own judgments, for they are made by himself or by his representative). So we have the distinction between the •legislative and •executive powers of civil society. The former are used to

judge, by •standing laws, how far offences committed within the commonwealth are to be punished;

the latter are used to

determine, by •occasional judgments based on particular circumstances, how far harms from outside the commonwealth are to be vindicated.

Each ·branch of a commonwealth’s power· can employ all the force of all its members, when there is a need for it.

89. Thus, there is a political (or civil) society when and only when a number of men are united into one society in such a way that each of them forgoes his executive power of the law of nature, giving it over to the public. And this comes about wherever a number of men in the state of nature enter into society to make one people, one body politic, under one supreme government. (·A man can become a member of a commonwealth without being in on its creation, namely· when someone joins himself to a commonwealth that is already in existence. In doing this he authorizes the society—i.e. authorizes it legislature—to make laws for him as the public good of the society shall require....) This takes men out of a state of nature into the state of a commonwealth, by setting up a judge on earth with authority to settle all the controversies and redress the harms that are done to any member of the commonwealth.... Any group of men who have no such decisive power to appeal to are still in the state of nature, no matter what other kind of association they have with one another.

·ABSOLUTE MONARCHY·
90. This makes it evident that absolute monarchy, which some people regard as the only ·genuine· government in the world, is actually inconsistent with civil society and so can’t be a form of civil government at all! Consider what civil society is for. It is set up

to avoid and remedy the drawbacks of the state of nature that inevitably follow from every man’s being judge in his own case, by setting up a known authority to which every member of that society can appeal when he has been harmed or is involved in a dispute—an authority that everyone in the society ought to obey.

So any people who don’t have such an authority to appeal to for the settlement of their disputes are still in the state of nature. Thus, every absolute monarch is in the state of nature with respect to those who are under his dominion. [Locke has a footnote quoting a confirmatory passage from Hooker. Another such is attached to the next section, and two to section 94.]

29

Second Treatise John Locke 7: Political or Civil Society

91. For an absolute monarch is supposed to have both legislative and executive power in himself alone; so there is no judge or court of appeal that can fairly, impartially, and authoritatively make decisions that could provide relief and compensation for any harm that may be inflicted by the monarch or on his orders. So such a man—call him Czar or Grand Seignior or what you will—is as much in the state of nature with respect to his subjects as he is with respect to the rest of mankind. ·This is a special case of the state of nature, because between it and the ordinary state of nature there is· this difference, a woeful one for the subject (really, the slave) of an absolute monarch: •in the ordinary state of nature a man is free to judge what he has a right to, and to use the best of his power to maintain his rights; whereas •in an absolute monarchy, when his property is invaded by the will of his monarch, he not only has no-one to appeal to but he isn’t even free to judge what his rights are or to defend them (as though he were a cat or a dog, that can’t think for itself). He is, in short, exposed to all the misery and inconveniences that a man can fear from someone who is in the unrestrained state of nature and is also corrupted with flattery and armed with power.

92. If you think that absolute power purifies men’s blood and corrects the baseness of human nature, read history—of this or any other age—and you’ll be convinced of the contrary. A man who would have been insolent and injurious in the forests of America isn’t likely to be much better on a throne! ·Possibly even worse·, because as an absolute monarch he may have •access to learning and religion that will ‘justify’ everything he does to his subjects, and •the power of arms to silence immediately all those who dare question his actions....

93. In absolute monarchies, as well in other governments in the world, the subjects can appeal to the law and have judges to decide disputes and restrain violence among the subjects. Everyone thinks this to be necessary, and believes that anyone who threatens it should be thought a declared enemy to society and mankind. But does this come from a true love of mankind and society, and from the charity that we all owe to one another? There is reason to think that it doesn’t. There is really no more to it than what any man who loves his own power, profit, or greatness will naturally to do to prevent fights among animals that labour and drudge purely for his pleasure and advantage, and so are taken care of not out of any love the master has for them but out love for himself and for the profit they bring him. If we ask ‘What security, what fence, do we have to protect us from the violence and oppression of this absolute ruler?’, the very question is ·found to be· almost intolerable. They are ready to tell you that even to ask about safety ·from the monarch· is an offence that deserves to be punished by death. Between •subjects, they will grant, there must be measures, laws and judges to produce mutual peace and security: but •the ruler ought to be absolute, and is above all such considerations; because he has power to do more hurt and wrong, it is right when he does it! To ask how you may be guarded from harm coming from the direction where the strongest hand is available to do it is to use the voice of faction and rebellion; as if when men left the state of nature and entered into society they agreed that all but one of them should be under the restraint of laws, and that that one should keep all the liberty of the state of nature, increased by power, and made licentious by impunity. This implies that men are so foolish that they would take care to avoid harms from polecats or foxes, but think it is safety to be eaten by lions.

30

Second Treatise John Locke 7: Political or Civil Society

94. But whatever may be soothingly said to confuse people’s •understandings, it doesn’t stop men from •feeling. And when they see that any man is outside the bounds of the civil society to which they belong, and that they have no appeal on earth against any harm he may do them, they are apt to •think they are in the state of nature with respect to that man, and to •take care as soon possible to regain the safety and security in civil society which was their only reason for entering into it in the first place. This holds for any such man, whatever his station in life—·whether he is a monarch or a street-sweeper·. In the early stages of a commonwealth it may happen (this being something I shall discuss more fully later on) that one good and excellent man comes to be pre- eminent, his goodness and virtue causing the others to defer to him as to a kind of natural authority; so that by everyone’s tacit consent else he comes to be the chief arbitrator of their disputes, with no precautions taken ·against his abusing that power· except their confidence in his uprightness and wisdom. ·The story could unfold from there in the following way·. The careless and unforeseeing innocence of the first years of society—which I have been describing—establish customs ·of deference to one individual·; some of the successors to the first pre-eminent man are much inferior to him; but the passage of time gives authority to customs (some say it makes then sacred), ·and so the custom of deference-to-one stays in place·. Eventually the people find that, although the whole purpose of government is the preservation of property, their property is not safe under this government; and they conclude that the only way for them to be safe and without anxiety—the only way for them to think they are in a civil society—is for the legislative power to be given to a collective body of men, call it ‘senate’, ‘parliament’, or what you will. In this way every single person—from the highest to the lowest—comes to be subject to the laws that he himself, as part of the legislature, has established. No-one has authority to take himself outside the reach of a law once it has been made; nor can anyone by any claim of superiority plead exemption from the laws, so as to license offences against it by himself or his dependents. No man in civil society can be exempted from its laws; for if any man can do what he thinks fit, and there is no appeal on earth for compensation or protection against any harm he may do, isn’t he still perfectly in the state of nature, and so not a part or member of that civil society? The only way to avoid the answer ‘Yes’ is to say that the state of nature and civil society are one and the same thing, and I have never yet found anyone who is such an enthusiast for anarchy that he would affirm that.

31

Second Treatise John Locke 8: The beginning of political societies

Chapter 8: The beginning of political societies

95. Men all being naturally free, equal, and independent, no-one can be deprived of this freedom etc. and subjected to the political power of someone else, without his own consent. The only way anyone can strip off his natural liberty and clothe himself in the bonds of civil society is for him to agree with other men to unite into a community, so as to live together comfortably, safely, and peaceably, in a secure enjoyment of their properties and a greater security against outsiders. Any number of men can do this, because it does no harm to the freedom of the rest; they are left with the liberty of the state of nature, which they had all along. When any number of men have in this way consented to make one community or government, that immediately incorporates them, turns them into a single body politic in which the majority have a right to act on behalf of the rest and to bind them by its decisions. [‘incorporate’ comes from Latin corpus = ‘body’.]

96. [In this section Locke makes the point that a unified single body can move in only one way, and that must be in the direction in which ‘the greater force carries it, which is the consent of the majority’. Majoritarian rule is the only possibility for united action. Locke will discuss one alternative—namely universal agreement—in section 98.]

97. Thus every man, by agreeing with others to make one body politic under one government, puts himself under an obligation to everyone in that society to submit to the decisions of the majority, and to be bound by it. Otherwise—that is, if he were willing to submit himself only to the majority acts that he approved of—the original compact through which he and others incorporated into one society would be meaningless; it wouldn’t be a compact if it left him as free of obligations as he had been in the state of nature....

98. For if the consent of •the majority isn’t accepted as the act of the whole ·body politic· and as binding on every individual, the only basis there could be for something’s counting as an act of the whole would be its having the consent of •every individual. But it is virtually impossible for that ever to be had. Even with an assembly much smaller than that of an entire commonwealth, many will be kept from attending by ill-health or the demands of business. Add to that the variety of opinions and conflicts of interests that inevitably occur in any collection of men, and coming into society upon such terms—i.e. on the basis that the society as a whole does nothing that isn’t assented to by each and every member of it—would be like Cato’s coming into the theatre only to go out again. [This refers to an episode in which the younger Cato conspicuously walked out of a theatrical performance in ancient Rome, to protest what he thought to be indecency in the performance.] Such a constitution as this would give the ·supposedly· mighty Leviathan a shorter life than the feeblest creatures; it wouldn’t live beyond the day it was born. [For ‘Leviathan’, see Job 41. Hobbes had adapted the word as a name for the politically organised sate.] We can’t think that this is what rational creatures would want in setting up political societies....

99. So those who out of a state of nature unite into a community must be understood to give up all the power required to secure its purposes to the majority of the community (unless they explicitly agree on some number greater than the majority). They achieve this simply by agreeing to unite into one political society; that’s all the compact that is needed between the individuals that create or join a commonwealth. Thus, what begins a political society and keeps it in existence

32

Second Treatise John Locke 8: The beginning of political societies

is nothing but the consent of any number of free men capable of a majority [Locke’s phrase] to unite and incorporate into such a society. This is the only thing that did or could give a beginning to any lawful government in the world.

100. To this I find two objections made. First,

History shows no examples of this, no cases where a group of independent and equal men met together and in this way began and set up a government.

Secondly,

It is impossible for men rightly to do this, because all men are born under government, and so they are bound to submit to that government and aren’t at liberty to begin a new one.

·I shall discuss these in turn, giving twelve sections to the first of them·.

·THE ‘HISTORY IS SILENT’ OBJECTION·
101. Here is an answer to the first objection. It is no wonder that history gives us very little account of men living together in the state of nature. As soon as any number of men were brought together by the inconveniences of that state, and by their love of society and their lack of it, they immediately united and incorporated if they planned to continue together. If we can conclude that men never were in the state of nature because we don’t hear not much about them in such a state, we can just as well conclude that the soldiers of Salmanasser or Xerxes were never children because we hear little of them before the time when they were men and became soldiers. In all parts of the world there was government before there were records; writing seldom comes in among a people until a long stretch of civil society has, through other more necessary arts ·such as agriculture and architecture·, provided for their safety, ease, and affluence. When writing does eventually come in, people begin to look into the history of their founders, researching their origins when no memory remains of them; for commonwealths are like individual persons in being, usually, ignorant of their own births and infancies; and when a commonwealth does know something about its origins, they owe that knowledge to the records that others happen to have kept of it. And such records as we have of the beginnings of political states give no support to paternal dominion, except for the Jewish state, where God himself stepped in. They are all either plain instances of the kind of beginning that I have described mentioned or at least show clear signs of it.

102. Rome and Venice had their starts when a number of men, free and independent of one another and with no natural superiority or subjection, came together ·to form a political society·. Anyone who denies this must have a strange inclination to deny any evident matter of fact that doesn’t agree with his hypothesis. [Locke then quotes an historian who reports that in many parts of the American continent people had lived together in ‘troops’ with no government at all, some of them continuing thus into Locke’s time. Then:] You might object: ‘Every man there was born subject to his father, or to the head of his family’; but I have already shown that the subjection a child owes to a father still leaves him free to join in whatever political society he thinks fit. But be that as it may, it is obvious that these men were actually free; and whatever superiority some political theorists would now accord to any of them, they themselves made no such claim; by consent they were all equal until by that same consent they set rulers over themselves. So their political societies all began from a voluntary union, and the mutual agreement of men freely acting in the choice of their governors and forms of government.

33

Second Treatise John Locke 8: The beginning of political societies

103. [Locke gives another example: colonists from ancient Sparta. Then:] Thus I have given several historical examples of free people in the state of nature who met together, incorporated, and began a commonwealth. Anyway, if the lack of such examples were a good argument to show that governments couldn’t have been started in this way, the defenders of the paternal empire ·theory of government· would do better leave it unused rather than urging it against natural liberty ·and thus against my theory·: my advice to them would be not to search too much into the origins of governments, lest they should find at the founding of most of them something very little favourable to the design they support and the governmental power they contend for. We wouldn’t be running much of a risk if we said ‘Find plenty of historical instances of governments begun on the basis of paternal right, and we’ll accept your theory’; though really there is no great force in an argument from what •has been to what •should of right be, ·even if they had the historical premise for the argument·.

104. [This short section repeats the conclusion of the preceding sections.]

105. I don’t deny that if we look back as far as history will take us into the origins of commonwealths, we shall generally find them under the government and administration of one man. Also, I am inclined to believe this:

Where a family was numerous enough to survive on its own without mixing with others (as often happens where there is much land and few people), the government commonly began in the father. By the law of nature he had the power to punish, as he thought fit, any offences against that law; this included punishing his offspring when they offended, even after they had become adults; and it is very likely that each submitted to his own punishment and supported the father in punishing the others when they offended, thereby giving him power to carry out his sentence against any transgression, This would in effect make him the law-maker and governor over everyone who continued to be joined up with his family. He was the most fit to be trusted; paternal affection secured their property and interest under his care; and the childhood custom of obeying him made it easier to submit to him than to anyone else. So if they had to have •one man to rule them (for government can hardly be avoided when men live together), who so likely to be •the man as their common father, unless negligence, cruelty, or some other defect of mind or body made him unfit for it?

But when •the father died and left as his next heir someone who was less fit to rule (because too young, or lacking in wisdom, courage, or the like), or when •several families met and agreed to continue together, it can’t be doubted that then •they used their natural freedom to set up as their ruler the one whom they judged to be the ablest and the most likely to rule well. And so we find the people of America—ones who lived out of the reach of the conquering swords and spreading domination of the two great empires of Peru and Mexico—enjoyed their own natural freedom, ·and made their own choices of ruler·. Other things being equal, they have commonly preferred the heir of their deceased king; but when they find him to be any way weak or uncapable, they pass him over and choose the toughest and bravest man as their ruler.

106. So the prevalence in early times of government by one man doesn’t destroy what I affirm, namely that

the beginning of political society depends upon the individuals’ consenting to create and join into one

34

Second Treatise John Locke 8: The beginning of political societies

society; and when they are thus incorporated they can set up whatever form of government they think fit.

But people have been misled ·by the historical records· into thinking that by nature government is monarchical, and belongs to the father. So perhaps we should consider here why people in the beginning generally chose this ·one-man· form ·of government·. The father’s pre-eminence might explain this in •the first stages of some commonwealths, but obviously the reason why government by a single person •continued through the years was not a respect for paternal authority; since all small monarchies (and most are small in their early years) have at least sometimes been elective.

107. [Locke repeats the reasons given in section 105 for fathers to be accepted as rulers in the early years of a political society. Then:] Add to that a further fact:-

Monarchy would be simple and obvious to men •whose experience hadn’t instructed them in forms of government, and •who hadn’t encountered the ambition or insolence of empire, which might teach them to beware of the....drawbacks of absolute power which a hereditary monarchy was apt to lay claim to.

So it wasn’t at all strange if they didn’t take the trouble to think much about methods of restraining any excesses on the part of those to whom they had given authority over them, and of balancing the power of government by placing different parts of it in different hands.... It is no wonder that they gave themselves a form of government that was not only obvious and simple but also best suited to their present state and condition, in which they needed defence against foreign invasions and injuries more than they needed a multiplicity of laws. [Locke elaborates that last point: ‘the equality of a simple poor way of living’ meant that there would be few internal disputes, whereas there was always a need to be defended against foreign attack.]

108. And thus we see that the kings of the Indians in America are little more than generals of their armies. They command absolutely in war, because there there can’t be a plurality of governors and so, naturally, command is exercised on the king’s sole authority; but at home and in times of peace they exercise very little power, and have only a very moderate kind of sovereignty, the resolutions of peace and war being ordinarily made either by the people as a whole or by a council. ·It is important to keep America in mind, because· America even now is similar to how Asia and Europe were in the early years when there was more land than the people could use, and the lack of people and of money left men with no temptation to enlarge their possessions of land.

109. And thus in Israel itself the chief business of their judges and first kings seems to have been to be leaders of their armies. [This long section backs up that claim with a number of Old Testament references, all from Judges and 1 Samuel.]

110. So there are two ways in which a commonwealth might begin.

•A family gradually grew up into a commonwealth, and the fatherly authority was passed on ·in each generation· to the older son; everyone grew up under this system, and tacitly submitted to it because its easiness and equality didn’t offend anyone; until time seemed to have confirmed it, and made it a rule that the right to governing authority was to be hereditary. •Several families....somehow came to be settled in proximity to one another, and formed a social bond; they needed a general whose conduct might defend them against their enemies in war; and so they made one man their ruler, with no explicit

35

Second Treatise John Locke 8: The beginning of political societies

limitation or restraint except what was implied by the nature of the thing [Locke’s phrase] and the purposes of government. This lack of precautions reflected the great mutual confidence of the men who first started commonwealths—a product of the innocence and sincerity of that poor but virtuous age.

Whichever of those it was that first put the rule into the hands of a single person, it is certain that •when someone was entrusted with the status of rule this was for the public good and safety, and that •in the infancies of commonwealths those who had that status usually used it for those ends. If they hadn’t, young societies could not have survived....

111. That was in the golden age, before vain ambition and wicked greed had corrupted men’s minds into misunderstanding the nature of true power and honour. That age had more virtue, and consequently better governors and less vicious subjects, ·than we do now·; so there was (on one side) •no stretching of powers to oppress the people, and consequently (on the other side) •no disputatious attempts to lessen or restrict the power of the government, and therefore •no contest between rulers and people about governors or government. In later ages, however, ambition and luxury led monarchs to retain and increase their power without doing the work for which they were given it; and led them also (with the help of flattery) to have distinct and separate interests from their people. So men found it necessary to examine more carefully the origin and rights of government; and to discover ways to restrain the excesses and prevent the abuses of the power they had put into someone’s hands only for their own good, finding that in fact it was being used to hurt them. [This section has another footnote quoting Hooker.]

112. This shows us how probable it is •that people who were naturally free, and who by their own consent created a government in either of the ways I have described, generally put the rule into one man’s hands and chose to be under the conduct of a single person, without explicitly limiting or regulating his power, which they entrusted to his honesty and prudence. And •that they did this without having dreamed of monarchy being ‘by divine right’ (which indeed no-one heard of until it was revealed to us by the theological writers of recent years!), and without treating paternal power as the foundation of all government. What I have said ·from section 101 up to here· may suffice to show that as far as we have any light from history we have reason to conclude that all peaceful beginnings of government have been laid in the consent of the people. I say ‘peaceful’ because I shall have to deal later with conquest, which some regard as a way for governments to begin.

·THE ‘BORN UNDER GOVERNMENT’ OBJECTION·
113. The other objection I find urged against my account of how political societies begin—·see section 100·—is this:

All men are born under some government or other, so it is impossible for anyone to be at liberty to unite with others to begin a new government; impossible, anyway, to do this lawfully.

If this argument is sound, how did there come to be so many lawful monarchies in the world? To someone who accepts the argument I say: Show me any one man in any age of the world who was free to begin a lawful monarchy, and I’ll show you ten other free men who were at liberty, at that time, to unite and begin a new government of some form or other. For it can be demonstrated that if someone who was born under the dominion of someone else can be free enough to ·come to· have a right to command others in a new and distinct empire,

36

Second Treatise John Locke 8: The beginning of political societies

everyone who is born under the dominion of someone else can have that same freedom to become a ruler, or subject, of a distinct separate government. And so according to this line of thought, either •all men, however born, are free, or •there is only one lawful monarch, one lawful government, in the world. In the latter case, all that remains for my opponents to do is to point him out; and when they have done that I’m sure that all mankind will easily agree to obey him!

114. This is a sufficient answer to their objection; it shows that the objection makes as much trouble for their position as it does for the one they are opposing. Still, I shall try to reveal the weakness of their argument a little further. They say:

All men are born under some government and therefore can’t be at liberty to begin a new one. Everyone is born a subject to his father, or his king, and is therefore perpetually a subject who owes allegiance to someone.

It is obvious mankind has never admitted or believed that any natural subjection that they were born into without their own consent, whether to father or to king, made them subjects ·for the rest of their lives· and did the same to their heirs.

115. For history, both religious and secular, is full of examples of men removing themselves and their obedience from the jurisdiction they were born under and from the family or community they grew up in, and setting up new governments in other places. That was the source of all the numerous little commonwealths in the early years: they went on multiplying as long as there was room enough for them, until the stronger or luckier swallowed the weaker; and then those large ones in turn broke into pieces which became smaller dominions. Thus history is full of testimonies against paternal sovereignty, plainly proving that what made governments in the beginning was not a natural right of the father being passed on to his heirs. If that had been the basis of government, there couldn’t possibly have been so many little kingdoms. There could only have been one universal monarchy unless men had been free to choose to separate themselves from their families and whatever kind of government their families had set up for themselves, and to go and make distinct commonwealths and other governments.

116. This has been the practice of the world from its first beginning to the present day. Men who are now born under constituted and long-standing political states, with established laws and set forms of government, are no more restricted in their freedom by that fact about their birth than they would be if they had been born in the forests among the ungoverned inhabitants who run loose there. Those who want to persuade us that by being born under a government we are naturally subject to it....have only one argument for their position (setting aside the argument from paternal power, which I have already answered), namely: our fathers or ancestors gave up their natural liberty, and thereby bound up themselves and their posterity to perpetual subjection to the government to which they themselves submitted.... But no-one can by any compact whatever bind his children or posterity; for when his son becomes an adult he is altogether as free as the father, so an act of the father can no more give away the liberty of the son than it can give away anyone else‘s liberty. A father can indeed attach conditions to the inheritance of his land, so that the son can’t have possession and enjoyment of possessions that used to be his fathers unless he becomes ·or continues to be· a subject of the commonwealth to which the father used to belong. Because that estate is the father’s property, he can dispose of it in any way he likes.

37

Second Treatise John Locke 8: The beginning of political societies

117. This has led to a widespread mistake ·concerning political subjection·. Commonwealths don’t permit any part of their land to be dismembered, or to be enjoyed by any but their own members; so a son can’t ordinarily enjoy the possessions—·mainly consisting of land·—of his father except on the terms on which his father did, namely becoming ·by his own consent· a member of that society; and that immediately subjects him to the government he finds established there, just as much as any other subject of that commonwealth. So free men who are born under government do give their consent to it, ·doing this through the inheritance of land·; but they do this one by one, as each reaches the age ·at which he can inherit·, rather than doing it as group, all together; so people don’t notice this, and think that consent isn’t given at all or isn’t necessary; from which they infer that they are naturally subjects just as they are naturally men.

118. But clearly that isn’t how governments themselves understand the matter: they don’t claim that the power they had over the father gives them power over the son, regarding children as being their subjects just because their fathers were so. If a subject of England has a child by an English woman in France, whose subject is the child? Not the king of England’s; for he must apply to be accounted an Englishman. And not the king of France’s; for •his father is at liberty to bring him out of France and bring him up anywhere he likes; and anyway •who ever was judged as a traitor (or deserter) because he left (or fought against) a country in which he was born to parents who were foreigners there? It is clear, then, from the practice of governments themselves as well as from the law of right reason, that a child at birth is not a subject of any country or government. He is under his father’s tuition and authority until he reaches the age of discretion; and then he is free to choose what government he will put himself under, what body politic he will unite himself to....

119. I have shown that every man is naturally free, and that nothing can make him subject to any earthly power except his own consent. That raises the question: What are we to understand as a sufficient declaration of a man’s consent—·sufficient, that is·, to make him subject to the laws of some government? The common distinction between explicit and tacit consent is relevant here. Nobody doubts that an •explicit consent of a man entering into a society makes him perfectly a member of that society, a subject of that government. Our remaining question concerns •tacit consent: What counts as tacit consent, and how far does it bind? That is: What does a man have to do to be taken to have consented to be subject of a given government, when he hasn’t explicitly given such consent? I answer:

If a man owns or enjoys some part of the land under a given government, while that enjoyment lasts he gives his tacit consent to the laws of that government and is obliged to obey them. [See the explanation of ‘enjoyment’ in section 31.] This holds, whether •the land is the owned property of himself and his heirs for ever, or •he only lodges on it for a week. It holds indeed if •he is only travelling freely on the highway; and in effect it holds as long as •he is merely in the territories of the government in question.

120. To understand this better, consider how •land comes within the reach of governments. When a man first incorporates •himself into any commonwealth he automatically brings with him and submits to the community •the possessions that he does or will have (if they don’t already belong to some other government). ·Why? Well·, suppose it is wrong, and that

38

Second Treatise John Locke 8: The beginning of political societies

someone could enter with others into society for securing and regulating property, while assuming that his land, his ownership of which is to be regulated by the laws of the society, should be exempt from the jurisdiction of the government to which he himself is subject.

This is an outright contradiction! So the act through which a person unites •himself—his previously free self—to any commonwealth also unites •his possessions—his previously free possessions—to that commonwealth. Both of them, the person and his possessions, are subject to the government and dominion of that commonwealth for as long as it exists. From that time on, therefore, anyone who comes to enjoy that land—whether through inheritance, purchase, permission, or whatever—must take it with the condition it is already under, namely, submission to the government of the commonwealth under whose jurisdiction it falls.

121. ·So much for •land; now for •the users of land·. If a land-owner hasn’t actually incorporated himself in the society ·of the commonwealth whose domain includes the land in question·, the government ·of that commonwealth· has direct jurisdiction only over the land; its jurisdiction reaches as far as the land-owner only when and to the extent that he lives on his land and enjoys it. The political obligation that someone is under by virtue of his enjoyment of his land begins and ends with the enjoyment. So •if a land-owner who has given only this sort of tacit consent to the government wants to give, sell, or otherwise get rid of his land, he is at liberty to go and incorporate himself into some other commonwealth, or to agree with others to begin a new one in any part of the world that they can find free and unpossessed. In contrast with that, if •someone has once by actual agreement and an explicit declaration given his consent to belonging to some commonwealth, he is perpetually and irrevocably obliged to continue as its subject; he can never be again in the liberty of the state of nature—unless through some calamity the government in question •comes to be dissolved, or by some public act •cuts him off from being any longer a member of that commonwealth.

122. But submitting to the laws of a country, living quietly and enjoying privileges and protection under them, doesn’t make a man a member of that society; all it does is to give him local protection from, and oblige him to pay local homage to, the government of that country. This doesn’t make him a member of that society, a perpetual subject of that commonwealth, any more than you would become subject to me because you found it convenient to live for a time in my household (though while you were there you would be obliged to comply with the laws and submit to the government that you found there). And so we see that foreigners who live all their lives under another government, enjoying the privileges and protection of it, don’t automatically come to be subjects or members of that commonwealth (though they are bound, ·by positive law and· even in conscience, to submit to its administration, just as its subjects or members are). Nothing can make a man a subject except his actually entering into the commonwealth by positive engagement, and explicit promise and compact.—-That is what I think regarding the beginning of political societies, and the consent that makes one a member of a commonwealth.

39

Second Treatise John Locke 9: Purposes of society and government

Chapter 9: The purposes of political society and government

123. If man in the state of nature is as free as I have said he is—if he is absolute lord of his own person and possessions, equal to the greatest and subject to nobody—why will he part with his freedom? Why will he give up this lordly status and subject himself to the control of someone else’s power? The answer is obvious:

Though in the state of nature he has an unrestricted right to his possessions, he is far from assured that he will be able to get the use of them, because they are constantly exposed to invasion by others. All men are kings as much as he is, every man is his equal, and most men are not strict observers of fairness and justice; so his hold on the property he has in this state is very unsafe, very insecure. This makes him willing to leave a state in which he is very free, but which is full of fears and continual dangers; and not unreasonably he looks for others with whom he can enter into a society for the mutual preservation of their •lives, •liberties and •estates, which I call by the general name •‘property’. (The others may be ones who are already united in such a society, or ones who would like to be so united.)

124. So the great and chief purpose of men’s uniting into commonwealths and putting themselves under government is the preservation of their property. The state of nature lacks many things that are needed for this; ·I shall discuss three of them·. First, The state of nature lacks •an established, settled, known law, received and accepted by common consent as the standard of right and wrong and as the common measure to decide all controversies. What about the law of nature? Well, it is plain and intelligible to all reasonable creatures; but men are biased by self-interest, as well as ignorant about the law of nature because they don’t study it; and so they aren’t apt to accept it as a law that will bind them if it is applied to their particular cases.

125. Secondly, the state of nature lacks •a known and impartial judge, with authority to settle all differences according to the established law. In that state everyone is both judge and enforcer of the law of nature, ·and few men will play either role well·. Men are partial to themselves, so that passion and revenge are very apt to carry them too far, and with too much heat, in their own cases; and their negligence and lack of concern will make them remiss in other men’s cases.

126. Thirdly, the state of nature often lacks •a power to back up and support a correct sentence, and to enforce it properly. People who have committed crimes will usually, if they can, resort to force to retain the benefits of their crime; ·this includes using force to resist punishment·; and such resistance often makes the punishment dangerous, even destructive, to those who try to inflict it.

127. Thus mankind are in poor shape while they remain in the state of nature—despite all their privileges there—so that they are quickly driven into society. That is why we seldom find any number of men living together for long in this state. The drawbacks it exposes them to....make them take refuge under the established laws of government, and seek there to preserve their property. This is what makes each one of them so willingly give up his power of punishing, a power then to be exercised only by whoever is appointed to that role, this being done by whatever rules are agreed on by the community or by those whom they have authorized to draw

40

Second Treatise John Locke 9: Purposes of society and government

up the rules for them. This is the basic cause, as well as the basic justification, for the legislative and executive powers ·within a government· as well as for the governments and societies themselves.

128. For in the state of nature a man has, along with his liberty to enjoy innocent delights, two powers. The first is to do whatever he thinks fit for the preservation of himself and of others, so far as the law of nature permits. This law makes him and all the rest of mankind into one community, one society, distinct from all other creatures. And if it weren’t for the corruption and viciousness of degenerate men, there would be no need for any other law—no need for men to separate from this great •natural community and by •positive agreements combine into separate smaller associations. [See the explanation of ‘positive’ on page 3.] The other power a man has in the state of nature is the power to punish crimes committed against the law of nature. He gives up both these powers when he joins in a particular politic society—a private one, so to speak—and brings himself into any commonwealth, separate from the rest of mankind.

129. The first power....he gives up to be regulated by laws made by the society, so far as is required for the preservation of himself and the rest of the society. Such laws greatly restrict the liberty he had under the law of nature.

130. Secondly, he wholly gives up the power of punishing; the natural force that he could use for punishment in the state of nature he now puts at the disposal of the executive power of the society. Now that he is in a new state, in which

he will enjoy many advantages from the labour, assistance, and society of others in the same community, as well as protection from the strength of the community as a whole,

he must also ·give up something. For·

he will have to part with as much of his natural freedom to provide for himself as is required for the welfare, prosperity, and safety of the society.

As well as being necessary, this is fair, because the other members of the society are doing the same thing.

131. But though men who enter into society give up the equality, liberty, and executive power they had in the state of nature....each of them does this only with the intention of better preserving himself, his liberty and property (for no rational creature can be thought to change his condition intending to make it worse). So the power of the society or legislature that they create can never be supposed to extend further than the common good. It is obliged to secure everyone’s property by providing against the three defects mentioned above ·in sections 124-6·, the ones that made the state of nature so unsafe and uneasy. Whoever has the legislative or supreme power in any commonwealth, therefore, is bound (1) to govern by established standing laws, promulgated and known to the people (and not by on-the-spot decrees), with unbiased and upright judges appointed to apply those laws in deciding controversies; and (2) to employ the force of the community •at home only in the enforcement of such laws, or •abroad to prevent or correct foreign injuries and secure the community from attack. And all this is to be directed to the peace, safety, and public good of the people, and to nothing else.

41

Second Treatise John Locke 10: Forms of commonwealth

Chapter 10: The forms of a commonwealth

132. When men first unite into a society, a majority of them naturally have (as I have shown) the whole power of the community, and may employ all that power in making laws for the community from time to time, and enforcing those laws through officials whom they have appointed. When that happens, the form of the government is a thorough democracy. Or they may put the law-making power into the hands of a select few, and their heirs or successors; and then the government is an oligarchy. If they put the power into the hands of one man, their government is a monarchy. (If the power is given to that man and his heirs, it is an hereditary monarchy: if to him only for life, with them retaining the power to nominate a successor, it is an elective monarchy.) Out of these ·possibilities· a community may make compounded and mixed forms of government if they see fit to do so. And if the majority first give the legislative power to one or more persons for their lifetimes or for some stipulated period, taking the supreme power back after that time has elapsed, then the community may dispose of it in any way they please, and so set up a new form of government. For the form of government depends on where the supreme power is placed; and the supreme power is the legislative power. (If it weren’t, legislation would be in the hands of some less-than-supreme power, which as a legislator would be in a position to prescribe to whoever had the supreme power; and that doesn’t make sense.)

133. I use ‘commonwealth’ throughout this work to mean (not a democracy or any other specific form of government, but ·more generally·) any •independent community—·that is, any community •that is not part of a larger political community·. The Latin word for this was civitas, for which the best English translation is ‘commonwealth’. Used correctly, it expresses such a society of men, which ‘community’ and ‘city’ in English do not—for there may be subordinate communities under a ·single· government, and we use ‘city’ to mean something quite different from ‘commonwealth’. So please let me avoid ambiguity by using the word ‘commonwealth’ in the sense I have explained, the sense in which I find it used by King James I—what I think to be its genuine sense. If you don’t like it, feel free to substitute something else.

42

Second Treatise John Locke 11: Extent of legislative power

Chapter 11: The extent of the legislative power

[Locke’s usual meaning for the word ‘arbitrary’, explained at the end of section 22, is at work in this and the next few chapters; but sometimes he seems rather to use the word in its now-current stronger sense of ‘decided for no reason’ or ‘decided on a whim’ or the like. The older, weaker sense is at work in section 135; the stronger sense seems to be involved in section 136, at least at its start. Sometimes, as at the start of section 137, it isn’t clear which sense is involved.]

134. The great •purpose for which men enter into society is •to be safe and at peace in their use of their property; and the great •instrument by which this is to be achieved is •the laws established in that society. So the first and fundamental positive law of any commonwealth is the establishing of the legislative power; and the first and fundamental natural law—which should govern even the legislature itself—is the preservation of the society and (as far as the public good allows it) the preservation of every person in it.

This legislature is not only the supreme power of the commonwealth, but is sacred and unalterable in the hands in which the community have placed it; and no other person or organisation, whatever its form and whatever power it has behind it, can make edicts that have the force of law and create obligations as a law does unless they have been permitted to do this by the legislature that the public has chosen and appointed.

Without this, the law would lack something that it absolutely must have if it is to be a law, namely the consent of the society. Nobody has power to subject a society to laws except with the society’s consent and by their authority; and therefore all the obedience that anyone can owe, even under the most solemn obligations, ultimately terminates in [Locke’s three words] this supreme power—·the legislature of the commonwealth·—and is governed by the laws it enacts. No oaths to any foreign power, or any subordinate power in a man’s own commonwealth, can free him from his obedience to the legislature.... [This section has a long footnote, quoting two confirmatory passages from Hooker. The next two sections have one such footnote each.]

135. Though the legislature (whether one person or more, whether functioning intermittently or continuously at work) is the supreme power in every commonwealth, ·there are four important things to be said about what it may not do. I shall present one right away, the second in sections 136-7, the third in 138-40, the fourth in 141·.

First, it doesn’t and can’t possibly have absolutely arbitrary power over the lives and fortunes of the people. For the legislative power is simply the combined power of every member of the society, which has been handed over to the person or persons constituting the legislature; there can’t be more of this power than those people had in the state of nature before they entered into society and gave their power to the community. Nobody can transfer to someone else more power than he has himself; and nobody has an absolute arbitrary power to destroy his own life, or take away someone else’s life or property.... A man in the state of nature has no arbitrary power over the life, liberty, or possessions of someone else; he has only as much ·freedom or moral power· as the law of nature gave him for the preservation of himself and everyone else; this is all ·the power· he has, so it is all he can give up to the commonwealth and thus to the legislature; so the legislature can’t have more than this. The outer limit of its power is set by the good of the society as a whole. It is a power whose only purpose is preservation, and therefore

43

Second Treatise John Locke 11: Extent of legislative power

the legislature can never have a right to destroy, enslave, or deliberately impoverish the subjects. The obligations of the law of nature don’t cease in society; in many cases indeed they pull in tighter there, with human laws enforcing them and punishing breaches of them. Thus the law of nature stands as an eternal rule to all men, legislators as well as others. The rules that legislators make for other men’s actions....must conform to the law of nature, which is a declaration of the will of God. The fundamental law of nature enjoins the preservation of mankind, and no human sanction can be valid against it.

136. Secondly, the legislature or supreme authority cannot give itself a power to rule by sudden, arbitrary decrees. It is bound to dispense justice and decide the rights of the subject by published standing laws, and known authorized judges. The law of nature is unwritten, and thus can be found only in the minds of men; so when people mis-state or mis-apply it (whether through passion or through self-interest) it is hard to convince them they are wrong when there isn’t an established judge ·to appeal to·. For this reason, the law of nature doesn’t serve as well as it should to determine the rights and protect the properties of those who live under it, especially where everyone is judge, interpreter, and enforcer of it too, even in his own case.... To avoid these drawbacks which disorder men’s property in the state of nature, men unite into societies so as to have •the united strength of the whole society to secure and defend their properties, and have •standing rules to hold the society together, rules that let everyone know what is his....

137. Absolute arbitrary power [section 135] and governing without settled standing laws [section 136] are both inconsistent with the purposes of society and government. Men wouldn’t quit the freedom of the state of nature for a governed society, and tie themselves up under it, if it weren’t to preserve their lives, liberties and fortunes with help from stated rules of right and property. It can’t be thought that they should intend to give to anyone an absolute arbitrary power over their persons and estates, and strengthen the law-officer’s hand so that he could do anything he liked with them. This would be putting themselves into a condition worse than the state of nature, in which they were free to defend their right against harm from others, and [now Locke’s exact words to the end of the sentence] were upon equal terms of force to maintain it, whether invaded by a single man or by many in combination. In contrast with that, if they gave themselves up to the absolute arbitrary power and will of a legislator, they would be disarming themselves and arming someone else to prey on them as he chose. It is much worse to be exposed to the arbitrary power of one man who has the command of 100,000 than to be exposed to the arbitrary power of 100,000 single men; because someone’s having 100,000 men under his command is no guarantee that his will, as distinct from his force, is any better than anyone else’s. And therefore, whatever the form of the commonwealth, its ruling power ought to govern by laws that have been published and taken in, and not by spur-of-the-moment dictates and frivolous decisions.... This achieves two things. (1) The people know their duty, and are safe and secure within the limits of the law. (2) The rulers are kept within their bounds, and are not tempted by their power to misuse it, using it for purposes and by means that they •don’t want the public to know and •wouldn’t willingly own up to.

138. Thirdly, the supreme power can’t take from any man any part of his property without his consent. What men enter into societies with governments for is the •preservation of their property; so it would be a gross absurdity to have a government that •deprived them of that very property! So

44

Second Treatise John Locke 11: Extent of legislative power

men in society

have property,

which means that

•they have such a right to the goods that are theirs according to the law of the community, and •nobody has a right to take any part of those goods from them without their own consent.

Without that second clause they would have no property at all; for something isn’t really my property if someone else can rightfully take it from me against my will, whenever he pleases. Hence it is a mistake to think that the supreme (or legislative) power of a commonwealth can do what it likes, and dispose of the estates of a subject arbitrarily, or take any part of them that it fancies. There is not much fear of this with governments where the legislature involves •assemblies whose membership varies—ones whose members, when the assembly disbands, are subjects under the common laws of their country, on a par with everyone else. But in governments where the legislature is •one lasting assembly that is always in existence, or •one man (as in absolute monarchies), there is a danger that they will think they have interests different from those of the rest of the community, and so will be apt to increase their own riches and power by taking whatever they want from the people. ·This would obviously be a terrible situation·, for a man’s property is not at all secure, even if there are fair laws protecting the property from the man’s fellow subjects, if they who command those subjects have the power to take from any one of them any part of his property that they want, and use and dispose of it as they choose.

139.....Sometimes it is necessary for power to be absolute, but that doesn’t mean that it is arbitrary; even absolute power, ·when it is legitimate·, is restricted to the purposes that required it to be absolute. To see that this is so, we need only to look at the usual form of military discipline. The preservation of the army, and through that the preservation of the whole commonwealth, requires absolute obedience to the command of every superior officer; and ·even· when a command is dangerous or unreasonable, disobedience to it is rightly punished with death. And yet a sergeant who could command a soldier to march up to the mouth of a cannon, or stand in a breach ·in the defensive walls· where he is almost sure to be killed, may not command that same soldier to give him one penny of his money. A general who can condemn the soldier to death for deserting his post or for not obeying the most desperate orders may not, for all his absolute power of life and death, help himself to the least little thing among that soldier’s possessions. ·The reason for the difference is clear·. The commander has his power for a •purpose, namely the preservation of all the people; for that •purpose blind obedience is necessary; and that is why the general can command anything and hang men for the least disobedience. Whereas taking a soldier’s goods has nothing to do with that •purpose.

140. It is true that governments need a great deal of money for their support, and it is appropriate that each person who enjoys his share of the protection should pay his proportion of the cost. But it must be with his consent, i.e. the consent of the majority, given either ·directly· by themselves or through representatives they have chosen; for if anyone claims a power to impose taxes on the people by his own authority and without such consent of the people, he is invading the fundamental law of property and subverting the purpose of government....

141. Fourthly, the legislature cannot transfer the power of making laws to any other hands. It was delegated to them from the people, and they aren’t free to pass it on

45

Second Treatise John Locke 12: Three kinds of power

to others. Only the people can decide the form of the commonwealth, which they do by instituting a legislature and deciding whose hands to put it into.... The power of the legislature, being derived from the people by a positive voluntary grant and institution, can’t be anything different from what that positive grant conveyed; and what it conveyed was the power •to make laws, not •to make legislators; so the legislature can have no power to transfer to anyone else their authority to make laws.

142. The legislative power of every commonwealth, in every form of government, is subject to the following limits to the trust that is put in them by the society and by the law of God and the law of nature. First, they are to govern by published established laws, not to be varied in particular cases, but to have one rule for rich and poor, for the favourite at court and the peasant at his plough. Secondly, these laws ought to be designed for no other ultimate purpose than the good of the people. Thirdly, they must not raise taxes on people’s property without their consent, whether given directly or through deputies. This is relevant only for governments where the legislature is always in existence, or at least where the people haven’t made any provision for some part of the legislature to be chosen, from time to time, by themselves. Fourthly, the legislature must not transfer the power of making laws to anyone else, or place it anywhere but where the people have placed it.

Chapter 12: The legislative, executive, and federative powers of the commonwealth

143. It is the legislative power that has a right to direct how the force of the commonwealth shall be employed for preserving the community and its individual members. But laws that are to be continuously in force and constantly enforced don’t take much time to make; so there is no need for the legislature to be always in existence because it doesn’t always have business to do. In well ordered commonwealths, where the good of the whole is properly taken into account, the legislative power is put into the hands of a number of people who have when assembled a power to make laws, after which they are to separate again and are to be subject to the laws they have made. This arrangement helps to keep a rein on them, so that they will be careful to legislate for the public good. ·An alternative would be for the legislators to be continuously in government service, filling the times between legislative sessions by acting as executors of the law. But this is rightly rejected in well ordered commonwealths· because it may be too great a temptation to human power-seeking frailty for the very people who have the power to make laws also to have the power to enforce them; for if they did, they might come to •exempt themselves from obedience to the laws they had made, and to •adapt the law—both in making and in enforcing it—to their own private advantage. That would separate their interests from those of the rest of the community, which would be contrary to the purpose of society and government.

46

Second Treatise John Locke 12: Three kinds of power

144. But once a law has been swiftly made, it has a constant and lasting force and needs to be enforced all the time, or at least there must always be someone on duty to enforce it when there is need for that. So there must be a power that—unlike the legislature—is always in existence, a power that will see to the enforcement of the laws that have been made and not repealed. That is how the legislative and executive powers come to be separated in many commonwealths. [Here and elsewhere, ‘enforce’ is used in place of Locke’s ‘execute’. The latter remains in the adjective ‘executive’ and the noun ‘executor’; but ‘execute’ and ‘executioner’ too easily suggest to modern ears that the topic is specifically capital punishment, which it isn’t.]

145. In every commonwealth there is another power that one may call ‘natural’, because it corresponds to the power every man naturally had before he entered into society. The members of a commonwealth are •distinct persons in relation to one another, and as such are governed by the laws of the society; but in relation to the rest of mankind they constitute •one body, which relates to the rest of mankind in the way the individual members related to one another in the state of nature. And so when any member of the society gets into a controversy with someone from outside it, the affair is managed by the public; and if a member of the ·political· body is harmed ·by an outsider·, the whole body is engaged in getting reparation....

146. This ·whole body· therefore has the power of •war and peace, •leagues and alliances, and •all transactions with individuals and communities outside the commonwealth. This power might be called ‘federative’. As long as the thing is understood, I don’t care about the name.

147. These two powers, •executive and •federative, are distinct from one another: one involves •the enforcement of the society’s laws upon all its members, while the other involves •the management of the security and interest of the public externally, in relation to those ·outsiders· from whom it may receive benefit or damage. Although this federative power is of great importance to the commonwealth, it is much less capable than the executive power of being directed by antecedent, standing, positive laws; and so it must necessarily be left to the prudence and wisdom of those who have the power to exercise it for the public good. ·The reason for this difference is as follows·. The laws concerning how subjects relate to one another are meant to •direct their actions, and so need to •precede them. But the function of the federative power is ·not to direct the actions of citizens but rather· to respond to the actions of foreigners, and the plans and interests of foreigners vary so greatly that ·they can’t be anticipated by a set of standing laws for each eventuality; and so· the federative power must be left in great part to the prudence of those who have it, trusting them to do their best for the advantage of the commonwealth.

148. Though the executive and federative powers of every community are really distinct in themselves, they are hardly to be separated and put into the hands of distinct sets of people. For they both require the force of the society for their exercise, and it is hardly practicable to place the force of the commonwealth in distinct hands, neither subordinate to the other. If the executive and federative powers were given to different ·groups of· people, they might act separately, thus putting the force of the public under different commands—and that would be apt sooner or later to cause disorder and ruin.

47

Second Treatise John Locke 13: Subordination of powers

Chapter 13: The subordination of the powers of the commonwealth

149. In a constituted commonwealth, standing on its own basis and acting according to its own nature (i.e. acting for the preservation of the community), there can be only be one supreme power, the legislative power, to which all the rest are and must be subordinate. But this is only a fiduciary [= •‘entrusted’] power to act for certain ends, so that the people retain a supreme power to remove or alter the legislature when they find it acting contrary to the •trust that had been placed in it. [The root of ‘fiduciary’ is the Latin fide = ‘trust’.] All power that is given with •trust for attaining a certain end is limited by that purpose; when the purpose is obviously neglected or opposed ·by the legislature·, the trust is automatically forfeited and the power returns into the hands of those who gave it. They may then make a new assignment of it, to whomever they think best for their safety and security. And thus the community never loses its supreme power of saving itself from the attempts and plans of anybody, even of their own legislators if they are so foolish or so wicked as to develop and carry out plans against the liberties and properties of the subject. No man or society of men has a power to hand over their preservation (or, therefore, the means to it) to the absolute will and arbitrary dominion of someone else; so when someone tries to bring them into that slavish condition, they will always have a right to •preserve ·the liberty that· they don’t have the power to part with, and to •rid themselves of those who invade this fundamental, sacred, and unalterable law of self-preservation, which was their reason for entering into society in the first place. In this respect the community may be said to be always the supreme power; but not as considered under any ·particular· form of government, because this power of the people can never be exercised until the government is dissolved.

150. [This section repeats the reason, given at the end of section 132, why the legislature must be the supreme power in the commonwealth.]

151. In some commonwealths, where the legislature is not always in existence, and the executive power is given to a single person who also has a share in the legislative power, that single person can in a reasonable sense be called ‘supreme’. Not because •he has all the supreme power (·which he doesn’t, because· that is the power of law-making, ·in which he has only a share·), but because •he has the supreme executive power, from which all the lower law-officers derive all or most of their various subordinate powers, and •he has no legislature superior to him. That is because no law can be made without his consent, and he can’t be expected to consent to any that would make him subject to the other part of the legislature. [Interruption: Locke has laid no basis for saying that the executive’s ‘consent’ is needed for any new law. This entire chapter, though mostly written in the language of general political theory, is aimed at the specific situation of England in the early 1680s, when Locke was writing. In that situation, the ‘executive’ was the king, and his consent was constitutionally required for any legislation. Here and at one point in section 152 Locke seems to have slid into thinking in terms of the English politics of his time at the expense of coherence with the political theory he has been building, and also drifting away from his immediate framework, which is the status of the executive at times when the legislature is not in existence. In contrast with this, sections 154-6, concerning the executive’s power to call the legislature into session, are thoroughly grounded in what Locke has said up there while also being sharply relevant to the English situation, in which Charles II had announced his right to rule without parliament.

48

Second Treatise John Locke 13: Subordination of powers

England’s troubles come to the fore again at section 213, but this time by open stipulation rather than a silent slide.] But notice that although oaths of allegiance and loyalty are taken to him, it is to him not as supreme legislator but as supreme executor of the law that he and others jointly made; for •allegiance is nothing but •obedience according to law. ·This distinction is important, because· if this supreme executor violates the law he then has no right to obedience; he can claim obedience ·not as a private person but· only as the public person vested with the power of the law; he is to be considered as the image or representative of the commonwealth, empowered by the will of the society as declared in its laws; and thus he has no will, no power, other than that of the law. If he leaves this representative function, this public will, and acts by his own private will, he demotes himself and becomes again a single private person, with no power or will that has any right to obedience....

152. When the executive power is placed anywhere other than in a person who also has a share in the legislature, it is visibly subordinate and accountable to the legislature, which can place it elsewhere if it chooses. So what is exempt from subordination—·i.e. isn’t subordinate to anyone or anything·—isn’t simply

•the supreme executive power

that but rather

•the supreme executive power when held by someone who has a share in the legislature.

The latter has no distinct superior legislature to be subordinate and accountable to, except in ways that he will consent to, so that he is only as subordinate as he himself thinks he should be, which certainly won’t be much. I needn’t discuss •other delegated and subordinate powers in a commonwealth; they are so many and so infinitely various across the different customs and constitutions of distinct commonwealths that it’s impossible to describe them all in detail. All I need for my purposes is to point out that none of •them has any authority beyond what is delegated to it by positive grant and commission, and are all of them are accountable to some other power in the commonwealth.

153. It isn’t necessary—it isn’t even advisable—that the legislature should be in existence all the time; but it’s absolutely necessary that the executive power be. There isn’t always a need for new laws to be made, but there is always a need for laws that have been made to be enforced. When the •legislature puts the enforcement of the laws they make into hands of a separate •executive power, they retain the power to take it back again if they find cause to do so, and to punish ·the executive· for any conduct that goes against the laws. The same holds for the •federative power, because it and the executive are both powers that have been delegated by the legislature and are subordinate to it—the legislature being supreme in a constituted commonwealth, as I have shown. The legislature may assemble and exercise their legislative power at the times specified by their original constitution or at their adjournment—or, if no time has been specified by either of these, and no other procedure is prescribed for convoking them, they may meet at any time they please. For the supreme power, having been placed in them by the people, is always in them, and they may exercise it when they please unless by their original constitution they are limited to certain seasons or by an act of their supreme power they have adjourned to a certain time.... ·In writing about when the legislature may ‘assemble’· I have been assuming that it consists of several persons. If it is a single person, it can’t help being always in existence, and will naturally have the supreme executive power as well as the supreme legislative power. ·It may delegate executive power, perhaps to one person, but he won’t ever have supreme executive

49

Second Treatise John Locke 13: Subordination of powers

power because it isn’t ever true of him (see section 151) that ‘he has no legislature superior to him’·.

154. If the legislature or any part of it is made up of representatives chosen by the people for a specified period of time, after which they are to return to the ordinary condition of subjects and to have no ·further· share in the legislature unless they are chosen again, this power of choosing again must also be exercised by the people either at certain appointed times or else when they are called to it. In the latter case, the power of convoking the legislature ·by calling for a general election· is ordinarily given to the executive, and is to be exercised in one of these two ways. (1) If the original constitution lays down the intervals at which the legislature is to assemble and act, all the executive power has to do is dutifully to issue directions for the proper conduct of the election and the assembly. (2) Otherwise, it is left to the executive’s prudence to call for new elections, when the benefits or needs of the public require the amendment of old laws or the making of new ones, or the correction or prevention of any misfortunes that have occurred or are threatening the people.

155. You may want to ask: ‘What if the executive power, having control of the force of the commonwealth, makes use of that force to prevent the legislature from meeting and acting at a time when its original constitution specifies that it should meet or the needs of the commonwealth require that it do so?’ I reply: Someone who uses force against the people, without authority and contrary to the trust they had given him, puts himself into a state of war with the people. They have a right to ·oppose this executive and· reinstate their legislature in the exercise of its power. They have set up a legislature intending it to exercise the power of making laws—either at certain set times or when there is need of it—and when the legislature is hindered by •any force from doing what is needed by the society for the safety and preservation of the people, the people have a right to remove •that force by force. In all states and conditions, the true remedy for unauthorized force is to oppose it with force....

156. The executive’s power of assembling and dismissing the legislature doesn’t make him superior to it. This power has been entrusted to him for the safety of the people, in a case where the assembling and disbanding of the legislature couldn’t be settled in advance by a fixed rule because human affairs were too uncertain and variable for that. Those who first set up the government couldn’t possibly see into the future well enough to know in advance exactly what timetable for the legislature would—for all time to come!—meet the needs of the commonwealth....

•Constant frequent meetings of the legislature, and long continuations of their assemblies when there was no need, would be burdensome to the people and would be bound eventually to produce more dangerous drawbacks. •Affairs might sometimes develop so fast that the legislature’s help was needed immediately, so that any delay in their convening might endanger the public. •Sometimes too their business might be so great that a time-limited sitting would be too short for their work, and rob the public of the benefit that could be had only from their mature deliberation.

To save the community from being exposed at some time or other to serious danger by having a legislature that met and acted only at fixed intervals and for fixed periods, what could be done other than entrusting it—·i.e. the power to call the legislative assembly into session·—to the prudence of someone who was ·always· present, was acquainted with the

50

Second Treatise John Locke 13: Subordination of powers

state of public affairs, and could use this prerogative for the public good? and where better to place this prerogative than in the hands of him who was entrusted with the enforcement of the laws, also for the public good? So, given that the regulation of times for the assembling and sitting of the legislature was not settled by the original constitution, it naturally fell into the hands of the executive, not •as an arbitrary power for him to exercise however he chose, but •as something he was entrusted with to use for the public good as changing circumstances might require. It is not my business to consider which is the least inconvenient—

settled periods for the legislature to convene,

the monarch left free to convoke the legislature, or

a mixture of those two systems.

All I have wanted is to show that though the executive power may have the prerogative of convoking and dissolving such assemblies of the legislature, that doesn’t make it superior to the legislature. [This is the first time in this work that Locke has explicitly allowed that the holder of the delegated executive power might be a monarch (his word is ‘prince’).]

157. Things in this world are in such a constant flux that nothing remains for long in the same state. Thus people, riches, trade, power, change their positions, flourishing mighty cities come to ruin and end up as neglected desolate corners, while other empty places grow into populous regions, filled with wealth and inhabitants. But things don’t always change equally, and the reasons for various customs and privileges may cease to apply, though people for their own purposes keep the customs and privileges in place. So it often happens in governments where part of the legislature consists of representatives chosen by the people that in the course of time this representation becomes very unequal and disproportionate to the reasons that first supported it. We can see what gross absurdities can come from following a custom when there is no longer reason for it when we see that the mere name of a town, with not even the ruins of the actual town remaining—with virtually no housing beyond a sheep-pen and no inhabitants beyond a single shepherd—may send as many representatives to the grand assembly of law-makers as a whole rich and populous county. Foreigners stand amazed at this, and everyone must admit that it needs to be remedied; but most people think it is hard to find a remedy, and here is why. The setting up of the legislature was •the original and supreme act of the society, •coming before any of the positive laws that it passed, and •depending wholly on the people; so no inferior power can alter it. Thus, once the legislature has been set up (in the kind of government I have been speaking of), the people have no power to act as long as the government stands; and this inconvenience is thought ·by some to be· incapable of a remedy.

158. The welfare of the people is the supreme law [Locke gives it in Latin] is certainly so just and fundamental a rule that no-one who sincerely follows it can dangerously err. So it is open to the executive, who has the power of convoking the legislature, to do this:

Regulate the number of members of the legislature that each place has a right to have as its representatives, basing this not on precedent but on facts about population, not on custom but on true reason....

If the executive does this, it can’t be judged to have set up a new legislature, but only to have restored the old and true one, and to have rectified the disorders that the passage of time had gradually and inevitably introduced. For it is the interest as well as the intention of the people to have fair and equal representation; so whoever brings it nearest to that is an undoubted friend to....government, and must have the consent and approval of the community. For a

51

Second Treatise John Locke 13: Subordination of powers

monarch’s prerogative is nothing but his power to provide for the public good in cases where, because of unforeseen and uncertain events, certain and unalterable laws could not safely be relied on. Any exercise of the prerogative does and always will count as just if it is done manifestly for the good of the people and for establishing the government on its true foundations. The power of establishing new municipalities and thus new representatives carries with it a supposition that in time the proportions of representation might vary: places might come to have a just right to be represented, though they before had none; and places that had previously been represented might cease to have that right and be regarded as too inconsiderable for such a privilege. What tends to subvert government is not mere change from the present state....but the tendency of change to injure or oppress the people and unfairly to subject one part of the populace to the rest. Whatever is obviously of advantage to the society and to people in general, upon just and lasting measures, will always justify itself; and whenever the people choose their representatives upon just and undeniably equal measures that are suitable to the original scheme of the government, it must be agreed to be the will and act of the society, whoever permitted or caused them so to do. [The two ‘upon just... measures’ phrases are in Locke’s exact words.]

52

Second Treatise John Locke 14: Prerogative

Chapter 14: Prerogative

159. When the legislative and executive powers are in distinct hands (as they are in all moderated monarchies and well-formed governments), the good of the society requires that various things should be left to the discretion of the executive. The legislators can’t foresee and make legal provision for everything that may in future be useful to the community, so the executor of the laws—having the power in his hands—has by the common law of nature a right to make use of it for the good of the society in many cases ·of difficulty· where the existing law •doesn’t deal with the difficulty—until the legislature can conveniently be assembled to make laws that •do. There are many things that the law can’t possibly provide for, and those must be left to the discretion of him who has the executive power in his hands.... Indeed, it is appropriate that the laws themselves should in some cases give way to the executive power, or rather to the fundamental law of nature and government that

All the members of the society are to be preserved as much as may be [here = ‘as far as is reasonably possible’].

Many events may occur in which a strict and rigid adherence to the laws may do harm; for example, a house is burning and the fire can be stopped from spreading by pulling down the house next door, which is against the law. Again, a man may come within the ·punitive· reach of the law (which doesn’t distinguish one person from another) through an ·illegal· action that deserves reward and pardon; so the ruler should have a power to mitigate the severity of the law and pardon some offenders. Since the purpose of government is the preservation of all as much as may be, even the guilty should be spared when this will do no harm to the innocent. [Since ‘executive power’ was introduced at the start of Chapter 12, this is the first time the executive has been referred to as ‘the ruler’.]

160. The word ‘prerogative’ is the name for

this power to act according to discretion, for the public good, without the support of the law and sometimes even against it.

[The remainder of this short section re-states section 159’s reason for giving such a prerogative to the holder(s) of executive power.]

161. This power, while employed for the benefit of the community and in accordance with the trust and purposes of the government, is an undoubted prerogative ·that the executive has·, and it is never called into question. The people seldom if ever think with careful precision about the executive’s prerogative. They are far from examining it as long as it is used to some extent for and not obviously against the good of the people. If a question does arise between the executive power and the people about something claimed as a prerogative, the dispute is easily decided by considering whether the disputed exercise of the prerogative tends to the good or to the harm of the people.

162. It is easy to conceive that in the early days of governments, when commonwealths were not much bigger than families, they had very few laws; their governors were like fathers watching over them for their good, and the government was almost all prerogative. A few established laws were all that was needed, and the ruler’s discretion and care supplied the rest. But when weak monarchs were led to use this power for their own private ends and not for the public good (being led to this by their own mistakes, or

53

Second Treatise John Locke 14: Prerogative

by the flattery of others), the people had to have laws that explicitly set limits to the prerogative with respect to matters in which they had found it working to their disadvantage. Thus the people found that they had to declare limitations of prerogative, where previously they and their ancestors had given the utmost latitude to monarchs who used the latitude only in the right way, namely for the good of their people.

163. When the people have established positive laws setting limits to the executive’s prerogative, some have said that in doing this they have encroached upon the prerogative. But those who say this have a very wrong notion of government. The people in such a case haven’t taken from the monarch anything that rightly belonged to him. All they have done is to declare that the power which they indefinitely left in his or his ancestors’ hands, to be exercised •for their good, wasn’t something they intended him to have if he used it •otherwise.... Alterations in government that tend to the good of the community can’t be an encroachment upon anybody, since nobody in government can have a right tending to any other purpose. Nothing is an encroachment unless it prejudices or hinders the public good. Those who say otherwise speak as if the monarch had interests other than the good of the community, and was not given the executive power for the good of the community—which ·attitude· is the source of almost all the evils and disorders that happen in kingly governments. And indeed if that is so—·i.e. if in some commonwealth the monarch does have interests separate from those of the people·—then the people under his government are not •a society of rational creatures who created a community for their mutual good; they are not •people who have set rulers over themselves to guard and promote that good; rather, they are to be looked on as •a herd of inferior creatures under the command of a master who keeps them and uses them for his own pleasure or profit. If men were so devoid of reason—so like the lower animals—as to enter into society upon such terms, then prerogative might indeed be what some men think it is, namely an arbitrary power to do things that are harmful to the people.

164. But a rational creature can’t be supposed voluntarily to subject himself to someone else for his own harm (though someone who finds a good and wise ruler may not think it either necessary or useful to set precise bounds to the ruler’s power in all things). So prerogative can be nothing but •the people’s permitting their rulers to choose freely to do for the public good various things on which the law is silent or even against the direct letter of the law; and •their accepting such choices when they have been made. A •good monarch—one mindful of the trust put into his hands, and careful about the good of his people—can’t have too much prerogative, i.e. power to do good. Whereas a •weak and poorly performing monarch—

one who would claim that the power his predecessors exercised without the direction of the law is a prerogative belonging to him by the right of his position, a right that he may exercise as he wishes, to make or promote interests distinct from those of the public

- causes the people to claim their right, and to limit the power that they had been content to tacitly allow while it was exercised for their good.

165. Look into the history of England and you will find that prerogative was always largest in the hands of our wisest and best monarchs, because the people, seeing the over-all tendency of their actions to be for the public good, didn’t object to what was done outside the law for that purpose. (·I speak of ‘the over-all tendency’ of the monarch’s conduct, because even a good monarch· may have a frailty or make

54

Second Treatise John Locke 14: Prerogative

a mistake leading to small failures to achieve the public good. Monarchs are only men, made like other men.) So the people, finding reason to be satisfied with these monarchs whenever they acted outside or contrary to the letter of the law, accepted what they did and uncomplainingly allowed the monarchs to enlarge their prerogative as they wished. In this the people rightly judged that the monarchs weren’t doing anything that would harm their laws, because they were acting consistently with the foundation and purpose of all laws, namely the public good.

166. Some people argue that absolute monarchy is the best government because it is what God himself governs the universe by; and that line of thought would give these God-like monarchs ·I have been discussing· some right to arbitrary power on the grounds that such kings partake of God’s wisdom and goodness. This is the basis for the saying, The reigns of good monarchs have been always most dangerous to the liberties of their people. ·Here is why there is truth in that·. Good monarchs may have successors who •have different ideas about how to manage the government, and who •take actions of their good predecessors as precedents and make them the standard of their own prerogative—as though what had been done purely for the •good of the people they had a right to do for the •harm of the people, if they so pleased. When this has happened it has often led to disputes and sometimes to public disorders, before the people could recover their original right and get something that never was a prerogative to be openly declared not to be a prerogative.... A ·genuine· prerogative is nothing but the power of doing public good without a rule.

167. The power of calling parliaments in England—settling their precise time, place, and duration—is certainly a prerogative of the king, but one that is entrusted to him to be used for the good of the nation.... [Locke then re-states the reasons for allowing such a prerogative to the holder of the executive power.]

168. On the matter of prerogative, there is an old question: Who is to judge whether this power is being used rightly? I answer: between

•an executive power that is in existence and has such a prerogative, and •a legislature that can’t convene without the executive’s calling them together,

there can be no judge on earth. Just as there can be none between •the legislature and •the people in a situation where either the executive or the legislature, having got the power in their hands, plan or begin to enslave or destroy the people. In this case, as in all other cases where they have no judge on earth, the people’s only other remedy is to appeal to heaven. In such cases the rulers, exercising a power that the people never put into their hands,....do what they have no right to do. And when the people as a whole (or any individual man) are deprived of their right or are subject to an exercise of power without right, and have no appeal on earth, then they are free to appeal to heaven if they judge the issue to be important enough for that. And therefore, although •the constitution of the society in question doesn’t give the people any superior power to act as judge, making and enforcing a decision in the case, they have, by •a law antecedent and to (and outranking) all positive laws of men, reserved to themselves a final decision. It is the one that is open to all mankind when no appeal can be made on earth, namely the judgment as to whether they have just cause to make their appeal to heaven.... Don’t think that this lays a perpetual foundation for disorder; for the appeal to heaven comes into play only when the trouble is so great that the majority feel it, are weary of it, and see that it must be amended. But the executive power, or wise monarchs, need never come into danger of this; and it is the thing above all others that they need to avoid, because it is dangerous above all others.

55

Second Treatise John Locke 15: Paternal, political, and despotic power

Chapter 15: Paternal, political, and despotic power, considered together

169. I have had occasion in earlier chapters to speak of these separately, but it may be worthwhile to consider them together, as the great mistakes about government that have recently been made have (I think) arisen from confusing these distinct powers with one another.

170. First, then, paternal or parental power is simply what parents have over their children to govern them for their own good until they come to the use of reason, or to a state of knowledge that should make them capable of understanding the rules—whether the law of nature or the civic law of their country—that they are to govern themselves by. I say ‘capable’ of this, meaning: as capable as the general run of people who live as freemen under that law. The affection and tenderness that God has planted in the hearts of parents towards their children shows that this isn’t meant to be a severe arbitrary government, but only for the help, instruction, and preservation of the children. But happen it as it will [= ‘whatever the details of how this is handled in individual families’], I have shown that •there is no reason why parental power should be thought ever to extend to life and death over the children any more than over anyone else; and that there is no basis on which to claim that parental power should keep the adult offspring in subjection to the will of his parents, though his having received life and upbringing from his parents obliges him to give respect, honour, gratitude, assistance and support, all his life, to both father and mother. So paternal government is indeed a natural government, but its purposes don’t stretch out to those of political government, nor does its scope.... [Something connected with this section is attached to the end of the whole work.]

171. Secondly, political power is the power that every man has in the state of nature and gives up into the hands of the society, and within the society to the governors whom the society has set over itself on the explicitly stated or tacitly understood condition that the power in question shall be employed for their good and for the preservation of their property. so this power....is to •preserve his property by whatever means he thinks good and ·the law of· nature allows him, and to •punish breaches of the law of nature by others, doing this in ways that (according to his best judgment) are most likely to favour the preservation of himself and of the rest of mankind. Thus, •as possessed by each man in the state of nature, this power has as its purpose and scope the preservation of all of the man’s society (i.e. of all mankind); so •as power in the hands of the magistrate it can’t have any purpose or scope other than that; and so it can’t be an absolute arbitrary power over their lives and fortunes, which are to be preserved as much as possible. ·It is indeed a power sometimes to deprive people of their freedom, or even of their lives, but only under strictly set conditions·. It is a power to make laws and to attach such penalties to them as may help the preservation of the whole community by cutting off the parts that are so gangrenous that they threaten the sound and healthy parts. Those parts and only those parts; no severity of punishment is lawful unless it tends to preserve the life and health of the community. And this power stems purely from compact and agreement—from the mutual consent of those who make up the community.

172. Thirdly, despotic power is an absolute, arbitrary power that one man has over another to take away his life whenever

56

Second Treatise John Locke 15: Paternal, political, and despotic power

he pleases. •Nature doesn’t give this power, for it doesn’t distinguish one man from another; and it can’t be given to someone by •agreement ·with the other man·, for no man has such an arbitrary power over his own life, and therefore can’t give it to someone else. Despotic power can only come from an aggressor’s giving up his right to his own life by putting himself into a state of war with someone else. The aggressor has

•deserted reason, which God gave us to be the rule between man and man, and the common bond whereby mankind is united into one fellowship and society;

•renounced the way of peace that reason teaches, and used the force of war to achieve his unjust purposes against someone else; and so has •walked out on his own kind and joined the wild animals, by adopting for his own conduct their rule of right, namely force.

In this way he has rendered himself liable to be destroyed by the injured person or by anyone else who is willing to join with the victim in carrying out justice, as we would against any other wild beast or noxious brute with which mankind can’t associate and from which it can’t be secure. Thus, the only people who are subject to a despotic power are captives taken in a just and lawful war—·captives, that is, who were fighting on the unjust and unlawful side in such a war·. This power is just a continuation of the state of war; it doesn’t come from any agreement, and couldn’t do so, for what agreement can be made with a man who is not master of his own life? What condition can he perform? And once he is allowed to be master of his own life, the despotic and arbitrary power of his master ceases. Someone who is master of himself and of his own life also has a right to the means of preserving it; so that as soon as any agreement is made, slavery ceases; and so anyone who bargains over conditions with his captive has thereby given up his absolute power and put an end to the state of war.

173. •Nature gives paternal power to parents for the benefit of their children during their minority, to make up for their lack of the skills and knowledge needed to manage their property. (Here and throughout I use ‘property’ to refer to the property that people have in their persons as well as in their goods.) Voluntary •agreement gives political power to governors for the benefit of their subjects, to secure them in the possession and use of their properties. And •forfeiture gives despotic power to lords for their own benefit, over those who have been stripped of all property.

174. If you think about how these kinds of power differ in their origins, scopes, and purposes, you will see clearly that •paternal power comes as far short of •that of the magistrate as •despotic goes beyond it; and that absolute dominion—whoever has it—is so far from being one kind of civil society that it is as inconsistent with such society as slavery is with property. Paternal power occurs when the child’s youth makes him unable to manage his property; political power occurs when men have property at their own disposal; and despotic power occurs over men who have no property at all.

57

Second Treatise John Locke 16: Conquest

Chapter 16: Conquest

175. Though governments can’t arise in any way but the one I have described, and political systems can’t be based on anything but the •consent of the people, ambition has filled the world with such disorders that this •consent is not much noticed in the din of war that makes such a large part of the history of mankind. As a result, many people have mistaken the force of arms for the consent of the people—·or, anyway, have credited armed force with doing things that really only consent can do·—and have counted conquest as one of the sources of government. But •conquest is as far from •setting up any government as •demolishing a house is from •building a new one to replace it. Conquest often makes way for a new form of a commonwealth by destroying one that already exists, but without the people’s consent it can never erect a new one.

176. The aggressor who enters into a state of war with someone else and unjustly invades his victim’s rights can’t in this way come to have a right over whomever he has conquered. You will easily agree with this unless you think that robbers and pirates have a right to govern people they have mastered by force, or that men are bound by promises that were extorted from them by unlawful force. If a robber breaks into my house and with a dagger at my throat makes me sign documents conveying my estate to him, would this give him any title to my estate? ·Obviously not! Well·, that is just the kind of ‘title’ that an unjust conqueror wins through his sword when he forces me into submission. The harm is the same whether committed by the wearer of a crown or by some petty villain, and the crime is the same too. The offender’s status and the number of his followers make no difference to the offence, except perhaps to make it worse. The only difference is this: •little robbers are punished by great robbers who want to keep them obedient, whereas •great robbers are rewarded with laurels and processions because they are too big to be held in the weak hands of justice in this world, and have in their own possession the power that ought to be used to punish them. What is my remedy against a robber who breaks into my house? Appeal to the law for justice. But perhaps •justice is denied, or •I am crippled and cannot move ·so as to go to the law-court·, or •because I have been robbed I don’t have the ·financial· means to go to law. If God has taken away all means for seeking remedy, there is nothing left but patience [= ‘being resigned to what has happened’, ‘putting up with it’]. But my son may become able to seek the relief of the law which is denied to me; he (or his son) may renew his appeal until he recovers what he has a right to. But the conquered and their children have no court, no arbitrator on earth to appeal to. Then they may appeal to heaven, as Jephtha did [Judges 11:30-31], and repeat their appeal until they have recovered the native right of their ancestors—namely, to have over them a legislature that the majority approve and freely accepted. If you object ‘But this would cause endless trouble’, I answer: no more trouble than justice causes when she lies open to all who appeal to her! Someone who troubles his neighbour without a cause is punished for it by the justice of the court he appeals to; and someone who appeals to heaven had better be sure that he has right on his side, and indeed a right that is worth the trouble and cost of the appeal, because he will be confronting a tribunal that can’t be deceived and will be sure to punish everyone according to what harm he has done to his fellow subjects (that is, to any human being). It

58

Second Treatise John Locke 16: Conquest

is clear from this that someone who conquers in an •unjust war can’t get from his conquest any right to the subjection and obedience of the conquered.

177. But supposing victory favours the right side, let us consider a conqueror in a •lawful war, and see what power he gets and over whom. First, it is obvious that his conquest doesn’t give him power over those who conquered with him. Those who fought on his side can’t suffer by the conquest; they must be at least as much freemen ·after the conquest· as they were before. In most cases they serve by agreement, on condition that they will share the spoils with their leader and get other advantages that come with the conquering sword—or at least have a part of the conquered country given to them. I hope that the conquering allies are not to be made slaves by the conquest, wearing their laurels only to show that they are sacrifices to their leaders’ triumph! Those who base absolute monarchy upon the right of the sword imply that their heroes, the founders of such monarchies, are utter Drawcansirs who forget that any officers or soldiers fought on their side in the battles they won, or helped them to subdue and occupy the countries they had conquered. [Drawcansir is a blustering braggart in a 1672 play; he enters a battle and kills all the combatants.] Some say that the English monarchy is based on the Norman conquest, and that our monarchs have thereby a right to absolute rule. History doesn’t support this; but if it were true, and if William ·the Conqueror· had a right to make war on this island, his rule through conquest couldn’t apply to anyone except the Saxons and Britons who were then inhabitants of this country ·and to their descendants·. The Normans who came with him and helped him to conquer, and all their descendants, are freemen; they are not subjects by conquest, whatever powers conquest bestows on the conqueror. And if you or I claim to be free because we are descended from them, it will be very hard to prove that we are not. And the law ·of this country· doesn’t distinguish between the descendants of the Normans and the descendants of the Saxons and Britons, making it clear that the law doesn’t intend that these two groups should differ in their freedom or privileges.

178. Suppose that the conquerors and the conquered don’t incorporate into one people, under the same laws and freedom. In that case (which rarely happens), what power does a lawful conqueror have over those he has subdued? The power he has, I say, is purely despotic. He has an absolute power over the lives of those who have forfeited them by waging an unjust war, but not over the lives or fortunes of those who didn’t take part in the war, and not over the possessions even of those who were actually engaged in it.

179. Secondly, I say then that the conqueror gets power only over those who have actually assisted, allowed, or consented to the unjust force that has been used against him. The people •never had a power to do something unjust, such as to start an unjust war; so they •can’t have given their governors a power to do such a thing; so they •ought not to be charged as guilty of the violence and injustice that is committed in an unjust war except insofar as they actually abet it. (The reasoning behind that also supports this: if our governors use violence or oppression against you, they weren’t empowered to do so by the rest of us, and so we are not guilty of what they have done.) Conquerors seldom trouble themselves to distinguish ·combatants from innocent civilians·, and willingly allow the confusion of war to sweep them all into one heap; but this makes no difference to what is right....

59

Second Treatise John Locke 16: Conquest

180. Thirdly, the power a conqueror gets over those he overcomes in a just war is completely despotic: he has an absolute power over •the lives of those who have forfeited them by putting themselves into a state of war; but this doesn’t give him a right and title to •their possessions. I am sure of this, but at first sight it may seem a strange doctrine, as it is so flatly contrary to the practice of the world. We are all familiar with the way people, speaking of the governing of countries, say of some person and some country that ‘He conquered it’; as if conquest automatically conferred a right of possession. Well, it is one part of the subjection of the conquered not to argue against the conditions cut out to them by the conquering sword; but what the strong and powerful do, however universally they do it, is seldom the rule of right.

181. In most wars force gets tangled up with damage, so that the aggressor harms the estates of those he makes war on; but what puts a man into the state of war is just the use of force, not the use of force to do damage. Whether the aggressor

begins the injury by force,

or else

inflicts the injury quietly, by fraud, and then refuses to make reparation and maintains it by force (which is the same thing as beginning it by force),

either way, it is the unjust use of force that makes the war. Compare someone who •breaks open my house and violently turns me out of doors with someone who •gets into my house peaceably and then by force keeps me out of it. These are in effect doing the same thing. (I am assuming that the intruder and I have no common judge on earth to whom I can appeal and to whom we are both obliged to submit.) It is the unjust use of force, then, that puts a man into a state of war with someone else and leads to his forfeiting his ·right to· life. [Locke then repeats the comparison with wild beasts.]

182. The misdeeds of a father are not faults of his children, who may be rational and peaceable despite their father’s brutishness and injustice. So he by his misdeeds and violence can only forfeit his own life, and doesn’t involve his children in his guilt or his destruction. His goods still continue to belong to his children. (Nature wills the preservation of all mankind as much possible, and makes the goods belong to the children to help them to survive.) Given that they haven’t taken part in the war—whether through infancy, absence, or choice—they have done nothing to forfeit the goods; nor has the conqueror any right to take them away simply on the grounds that he has subdued by force the person who attempted to destroy him. Still, he may have some some right to them, to make good the damages he has sustained by the war and the defence of his own right [Locke’s exact phrase]. We shall see in due course how far this right ·of the conqueror’s· reaches into the possessions of the conquered. Thus, someone who by conquest has a right over a man’s person to destroy him if he pleases doesn’t thereby get a right to possess and use his estate; for the brutal force that the aggressor has used is what gives his ·conquering· adversary a right to take away his life...., but what gives the adversary title to the defeated aggressor’s goods is the damage he has sustained ·through the aggression·. Similarly, I may kill a thief who attacks me on the highway, but I may not take the seemingly less drastic course of taking his money and letting him go, for this would be robbery on my side. His force and the state of war he put himself into made him forfeit his life, but it didn’t give me title to his goods. So: the right of conquest extends only to the •lives of those who took part in the war, and not to their

60

Second Treatise John Locke 16: Conquest

•estates except to make reparation for the damages received and the costs of the war—and even there the rights of the innocent wife and children are to be respected.

183. However much justice the conqueror has on his side, he has no right to seize more than the vanquished could forfeit: the latter’s life is at the victor’s mercy, as are his service and his goods if these are needed for reparation; but the conqueror can’t take the goods of the conquered person’s wife and children—for they too had a title to the goods he had used and shared in the estate he had possessed. Consider an example involving two men in the state of nature (as all commonwealths are in the state of nature relative to one another): suppose that I have injured another man and have refused to make reparations, so it comes to a state of war in which my defending by force what I had unjustly acquired makes me the aggressor. In this war I am conquered; my life then is forfeit, it is at the mercy of the other man, but not the lives of my wife and children! They didn’t make the war or take part in it. I couldn’t forfeit their lives, which were not mine to forfeit. My wife had a share in my estate, and I couldn’t forfeit that either. And my children also, being born of me, had a right to be maintained through my labour or my goods. Here, then, is what it comes down to:- The conqueror has a right to reparation for damages received, and the children have a right to their father’s estate for their survival; as for the wife’s share, it is clear that her husband can’t forfeit what is hers, whether it became hers through her own work or through some agreement. What must be done in the case ·that there is not enough to go around·? I answer that the fundamental law of nature is that as far as possible all should be preserved; from which it follows that if there isn’t enough fully to •recompense the conqueror for his losses and to •provide for the maintenance, he who has enough and to spare must forgo some of his full reparations and give way to the greater right of those who are in danger of perishing without it.

184. Suppose that the rights of the conqueror are so broad that

•the costs and damages of the war are to be reimbursed to the conqueror to the last penny,

and

•the children of the vanquished are to be deprived of all their father’s goods and left to starve and die,

still this won’t give him a title to any country that he conquers. The ·cost of the· damages of war can hardly amount to the value of any considerable tract of land in any part of the world where all the land is possessed and none lies waste. If I haven’t taken away the conqueror’s land (and as the loser how could I?), hardly any damage I have done to him can amount to the value of my land (supposing it to be as much cultivated as his land is, and somewhere near the size of his land that I had overrun). Usually in a war the most harm that is done amounts to the destruction of the crops and other output of a year or two (it seldom reaches four or five). As for money and other riches and treasure that might be taken away, these are not nature’s goods, and have only a notional imaginary value. Nature has put no value on them ·as men do·; they are of no more account by nature’s standard than the wampum of the American Indians is to a European monarch, or the silver money of Europe would formerly have been to an Indian. If we set aside the notional value of money, ·we are left with the value of land and the products of land·. Even if as aggressor I spoiled five years’ worth of product ·of my victim’s land·, that doesn’t add up to the value of ·my· land held in perpetuity; the disproportion is greater than that between five and five hundred. (This

61

Second Treatise John Locke 16: Conquest

is based on the assumption that all land is possessed and none remains waste. If there is more land than people in general can possess and make use of, and anyone has liberty to make use of the waste, the loss of half a year’s product of one’s land is worth more than the inheritance [Locke’s phrase, perhaps meaning ‘the perpetual ownership of some comparable tract of land’; this is the first occurrence of ‘inheritance’ or any cognate of it in this chapter]; but under those circumstances conquerors aren’t much interested in taking the lands of the vanquished.) Thus, no damage that men in the state of nature....suffer from one another can give a conqueror power to dispossess the descendants of the vanquished, and take from them the inheritance that ought to be theirs and their descendants’ through all the generations. The conqueror will indeed be apt to think himself master; and the subdued, just because they are subdued, can’t stand up for their rights. But if that is the whole case for giving the land of the vanquished to the conqueror, this must rest on the ·entirely unacceptable· principle that whoever is strongest has a right to whatever he pleases to take.

185. Thus, the winner in a just war does not get, by winning, any right of dominion over

•those who joined in the war on his side, •those in the subdued country who didn’t oppose him, or •the posterity even of those who did oppose him.

These are all free from any subjection to him, and if their former government is dissolved they are at liberty to start making themselves another.

186. What usually happens in fact is that the conqueror compels them, with a sword at their breasts, to accept his conditions and submit to whatever government he chooses to allow them; but the question is: what right has he to do this? If it be said that in submitting they give their consent to the government in question, this allows that their consent is necessary for the conqueror to have a right to rule over them, and leaves just one question open: Does a person consent when he makes a promise under a threat of unlawful force? how far does such a promise bind him? I reply that it doesn’t bind at all, because when someone gets something from me by force, I still have a right to it, and he is obliged to give it back to me at once. He who takes my horse from me by force ought immediately to give it back, and I have a right to take it back ·if I can·. By the same reasoning, he who forced a promise from me ought immediately to give it back, i.e. to clear me of the obligation of it; and I am entitled to take it back, i.e. choose whether to do what I have promised to do. The law of nature lays obligations on me only by the rules nature prescribes, so it can’t oblige me through a violation of nature’s rules such as extortion through force....

187. It follows from all this that when the conqueror in a just war uses his force to impose a government on the subdued against whom he had no right of war (i.e. who didn’t join in the war against him), they have no obligation to obey this government.

188. But let us suppose that all the men of the community in question, all being members of the same body politic, can be taken to have joined in that unjust war in which they are subdued, so that the lives of all of them are at the mercy of the conqueror.

189. I say that this doesn’t extend to their non-adult children; for since a father doesn’t himself have a power over the life or liberty of his child, no act of his can possibly forfeit the child’s life or liberty. So the children, whatever may happen to the fathers, are freemen; the absolute power of the conqueror reaches no further than the persons of the men who were subdued by him, and it dies when they do.

62

Second Treatise John Locke 16: Conquest

And if he ·spares their lives and· governs them as slaves, subjected to his absolute arbitrary power, he has no such right of dominion over their children. He can have no power over them except by their own consent, whatever he may force them to say or do; and he has no lawful authority when their submission comes from his force rather than their consent.

190. Every man is born with a double right:- •First, a right of freedom to his person; no-one else has any power over this—it is entirely his to use as he wishes. •Secondly, a right before any other man to inherit with his brethren his father’s goods.

191. By the •first of these a man is naturally free from subjection to any government, even if he was born in a place under its jurisdiction. But if he renounces obedience to the lawful government of the country he was born in, he must also give up the rights that he had through its laws, and the possessions that came down to him from his ancestors (if the government was made by their consent).

192. By the •second, the inhabitants of any country, who are descended from those who were subdued and had a government forced upon them against their will, retain a right to the possessions they inherited from their ancestors.... For the original conqueror never had any title to the land of that country, so the descendants and legatees of those who were forced to submit to the yoke of a government by constraint always have a right to shake it off, freeing themselves from the usurpation or tyranny that the sword has brought down on them, until their rulers give them a form of government that they’ll willingly consent to. Who doubts that the Greek Christians, descendants of the ancient possessors of that country, are entitled to throw off the Turkish yoke under which they have groaned for so long, whenever they have an opportunity to do so? For no government can have a right to obedience from a people who haven’t freely consented to it; and they can’t be supposed to have done that until either

•they are put into a full state of liberty to choose their government and governors,

or at least

•(1) they have standing laws to which they have given their free consent directly or through their representatives, and also (2) they are allowed the property to which they are entitled.

Condition (2) means that they are the proprietors of what they have in such a way that nobody can take away any part of it without their own consent. Without that, men under any government are not freemen but slaves under the force of war.

193. Even supposing that the conqueror in a just war does have a right to the estates of the conquered, as well as power over their persons (which he plainly doesn’t), this still doesn’t imply that the continuing government has any kind of absolute power. The descendants of ·those who were conquered· will all be freemen; if the conqueror doesn’t grant them estates and possessions to inhabit his ·newly conquered· country, it won’t be worth anything; and if he does grant them estates and possessions, then they have property, and the nature of property is that without a man’s own consent it can’t be taken from him.

194. Their persons are free by a natural right, and their properties, whether large or small, are their own, to be dealt with by their choice and not by the conqueror’s—otherwise they are not properties. Suppose the conqueror gives one man a thousand acres, for him and his heirs for ever; and to another man he lets a thousand acres for his life, with a rental of £50 or £500. Doesn’t the former man have a right

63

Second Treatise John Locke 16: Conquest

to his thousand acres for ever? and doesn’t the other have a right to his thousand acres for his lifetime, while paying the agreed rent? And doesn’t the tenant for life own all that his labour and industry brings in over and above his rent, even if it is double the rent? Can anyone say that the king (or conqueror), after making a grant, may use his power take away all or part of the land from the heirs of the first man, or from the second man (the tenant) during his lifetime when he is paying the rent? Or can he whenever he pleases take away from either of them the goods or money they have earned through the land in question? If he can, then all free and voluntary contracts are nullified: all it takes to dissolve them at any time is enough power; and all the grants and promises of men in power are nothing but a mockery. Can there be anything more ridiculous than to say ‘I give this to you and your descendants for ever’, saying it in the surest and most solemn form of gift-giving that can be devised, when it’s understood that I have the right to take it away from you again tomorrow if I want to?

195. I shan’t discuss now whether monarchs are exempt from the laws of their country, but I am sure of this much: they owe subjection to the laws of God and of nature. No body, no power, can exempt them from the obligations of that eternal law. Where promises are concerned, those obligations are so great and so strong that omnipotent God himself can be bound by them. Grants, promises, and oaths are bonds that hold the Almighty. Compare that fact with what some flatterers say to monarchs, ·namely that they are so great that they needn’t keep their promises·. Yet all the monarchs of the world, together with all their courtiers, are by comparison with the great God like a drop in the bucket, or a speck of dust on the balance—inconsiderable, nothing!

196. Here it is in brief: if the conqueror has a just cause, he gets ·through his conquest· a despotic right over the persons of all those who actually aided and supported the war against him, and a right to use their labour and estates to make up for the damages he has suffered and the costs he has incurred (so long as he doesn’t infringe anyone else’s rights). He has no power over such of the people as didn’t consent to the war, or over the children of the captives themselves, and no power over the possessions of either group. So his conquest does not entitle him to have dominion over them, or to pass on such dominion to his posterity. If he tries to take their properties, he is an aggressor, and thereby puts himself into a state of war against them. [The section ends with historical and biblical examples.]

64

Second Treatise John Locke 18: Tyranny

Chapter 17: Usurpation

197. As conquest may be called a foreign usurpation, so usurpation is a kind of domestic conquest. But the equivalence is not exact: a ‘domestic conqueror’ might have right on his side, but an usurper can never do so, because an action counts as a usurpation only if it involves getting possession of something that someone else has a right to. A usurpation, as such, is a change only in who has the government, not in the forms and rules of the government. If the usurper ·goes further, and· extends his power beyond what rightly belonged to the lawful monarchs or governors of the commonwealth ·whom he has dislodged·, he is guilty not merely of usurpation but also of tyranny.

198. The designation of who is to rule is as natural and necessary a part of any lawful government as is the form of the government itself, and is something that was originally established by the people. Compare these two:

•having no form of government at all; •agreeing on a monarchy, without having a procedure for deciding who shall be monarch.

The anarchy will be much alike! Hence all commonwealths with an established form of government have rules also for appointing those who are to share in the public authority, and settled methods of getting them into office. Whoever gets into the exercise of any part of the power by ways other than those prescribed by the laws of the community has no right to be obeyed, even if he doesn’t change the form of the commonwealth; because he is not the person the laws have appointed, and so not the person the people have consented to. And no such usurper—or anyone whose rule is derived from him—can ever be entitled to his position as ruler until the people are free to consent, and do consent, to allow and confirm in him the power he has till then usurped.

Chapter 18: Tyranny

199. Whereas usurpation is the exercise of power to which someone else has a right, tyranny is the exercise of power to which nobody can have a right. That is what happens when someone employs the power he has in his hands, not for the good of those who are under it but for his own private individual advantage. ·It is what happens· when a governor, however entitled ·he is to govern·, is guided not by the law but by his own wants, and his commands and actions are directed not to preserving his subjects’ properties but to satisfying his own ambition, revenge, covetousness, or any other irregular passion.

200. If you doubt this to be true, or to be reasonable, because it is written by a mere lowly subject, I hope you will take it from the authority of a king! King James I in his

65

Second Treatise John Locke 18: Tyranny

1603 speech to the parliament said this:

In making good laws and constitutions, I will always put the welfare of the public and of the whole commonwealth ahead of any particular and private purposes of mine; because I think that the wealth and welfare of the commonwealth is my greatest welfare and worldly happiness. In this respect a lawful king sharply differs from a tyrant: for....the greatest point of difference between the two is that whereas •the proud and ambitious tyrant thinks his kingdom and people are only ordained for satisfying his desires and unreasonable appetites, •the righteous and just king does on the contrary acknowledge that he has been given the task of preserving the wealth and property of his people.

And in his 1609 speech to the parliament he said:

The king binds himself by a double oath to observe the fundamental laws of his kingdom. •Just by being a king he tacitly binds himself to protect not just the people but also the laws of his kingdom. By his oath at his coronation he explicitly binds himself to the same thing.... If a king governing in a settled kingdom stops ruling according to his laws, he thereby stops being a king and degenerates into a tyrant.

And a little after:

Therefore all kings who are not tyrants, or perjured, will be glad to bind themselves within the limits of their laws; and those who ·try to· persuade them otherwise are vipers, pests, against both the king and the commonwealth.

Thus that learned king, who had a good grasp of concepts, distinguishes king from tyrant through this and this alone: •a king limits his power to what the laws allow, and governs for the good of the public, whereas •a tyrant puts his own will and appetite ahead of everything.

201. It is a mistake to think that only monarchies can go wrong in this way; other forms of government are also open to it. Whenever power is put into some hands for the government of the people and the preservation of their properties, and is then diverted from that purpose and used to impoverish, harass, or subdue the people to the arbitrary and irregular commands of those that have the power, then that immediately becomes tyranny, whether the power-holders are one or many. There was one tyrant at Syracuse, but we read of the thirty tyrants at Athens; and the intolerable government of the Ten Men at Rome was no better.

202. Wherever law ends, tyranny begins, if the breach of the law brings harm to someone else; and anyone in authority who exceeds the power given him by the law, using the force at his disposal to do to the subject things that aren’t allowed by the law, thereby stops being an officer of the law; and because he acts without authority he may ·rightly· be opposed, as may any other man who by force invades the right of someone else. This is acknowledged to hold for subordinate officers of the law. Someone who is authorized to arrest me •in the street may be opposed as a thief and a robber if he tries to break into •my house to arrest me—even if I know that his legal authority (and the arrest-warrant in his pocket) empower him to arrest me when I am •out of my house. I’d like to know why this shouldn’t hold just as well for the highest as well as the lowest-ranked officials of government. ·We don’t accept that having great •wealth automatically entitles a man to have even more·. We don’t find it reasonable that the oldest brother, just because he has most of his father’s estate, should thereby have a right to take away any of his younger brothers’ shares; or that a rich man

66

Second Treatise John Locke 18: Tyranny

who possessed a whole county should get from that a right to seize the cottage and garden of his poor neighbour? Being the lawful owner of great riches,....far from being an excuse (let alone a reason) for robbery and oppression, makes it much worse. Well, all of this applies equally to having great •power: having much power isn’t an entitlement to help oneself to more and engage in one’s own kind of robbery and oppression. Exceeding the bounds of authority is no more a right in a great officer of government than in a low-level one, no more justifiable in a king than in a constable. It is indeed worse in the king because •more trust has been placed in him, •he already has a much greater share than the rest of his brethren, and •his education, employment, and counsellors are supposed to have given him more knowledge of the measures of right and wrong.

203. You may want to object:- ‘Then may the commands of a monarch be opposed? May he be resisted whenever anyone finds himself aggrieved and imagines he hasn’t been treated rightly? This will unhinge and overturn all systems of administration, leaving us with nothing but anarchy and confusion instead of government and order.’

204. Here is my answer:- It is wrong to use force against anything except unjust and unlawful force; whoever opposes a government for any other reason draws on himself a just condemnation from both God and man; and my philosophy of these matters doesn’t bring a threat of danger or confusion, as is often suggested. ·Here are four observations in support of this·.

205. First:- In some countries the person of the monarch is sacred, as a matter of law; so whatever he commands or does, his person is still free from all question or violence, not liable to force or to any judicial censure or condemnation. Yet the subjects may oppose the illegal acts of any lower official, or anyone commissioned by the monarch. In those countries, the only way the monarch can lose his personal immunity is by putting himself into a state of war with his people, dissolving the government, and leaving the people to the defence that everyone has in the state of nature. When that happens, who can tell how it will all end? A remarkable example of how it can end is presented to the world by a neighbour kingdom. In all other cases the sacredness of the monarch’s person exempts him, while the government stands, from all violence and harm whatsoever. And this is a wise constitution: for the harm a monarch can do unaided is not likely to happen often, or to go very far. Even if some monarch is weak and ill-natured enough to want to do it, he can’t by his own personal strength subvert the laws or oppress the body of the people. When a headstrong monarch comes to the throne, he may do some troublesome things; but the disadvantages of those are quite outweighed by the peace of the public and the security of the government that comes from having the person of the head of government thus placed out of the reach of danger. For it is safer for the body politic that a few private men should sometimes be in danger of suffering than that the head of the commonwealth should be easily and casually exposed to danger.

206. Second:- This privilege of the king’s person doesn’t confer immunity against questioning, opposition, and resistance for those who use unjust and unlawful force and claim they were commissioned to do this by the king. Here is a plain case of that. Someone has the king’s writ to arrest me, this being a full commission from the king; but he can’t break into my house to arrest me, or carry out this command of the king’s on certain days or in certain places, if the law forbids him to, even if the commission doesn’t state any such exceptions. If anyone breaks the law, the king’s commission

67

Second Treatise John Locke 18: Tyranny

doesn’t excuse him; for the king has his authority only •through the law, so he cannot empower anyone to act •against the law.... The commission or command of any government official ·from the king down to the constable· to do something for which he has no authority is as empty and insignificant as the ‘commission’ or command of any private man. The only difference between the two is that the official has authority to a certain extent and for certain purposes, while the private man has none; ·but the restrictions on the official’s authority are crucial·, because what gives the right of acting is not the •commission but the •authority; and there can be no authority against the laws. But ·when private citizens resist commissioned but unauthorized action by government officials·, notwithstanding such resistance the king’s person and authority are still both secured, and so ·there is· no danger to governor or government.

207. Third:- Consider now a government in which the person of the ruler is not sacred. My doctrine of the lawfulness of resisting all unlawful exercises of power won’t on every slight occasion endanger him or disturb the government; for where the injured party can be relieved and his damages made good by appeal to the law, he can’t claim a right to use force, which is only to be used where a man is prevented from appealing to the law. No exercise of force by the government counts as hostile if it leaves open the possibility of such an appeal; it is only when force closes that door that it puts the user of it into a state of war, and makes it lawful to resist him. •A man with a sword in his hand demands my purse on the highway when I have almost no money with me; this man I may lawfully kill. To •another man I hand £100 to hold while I get off my horse; he then refuses to give it back to me, and draws his sword to defend his possession of it by force if I try to take it back from him. The harm this man does to me may be a hundred or even a thousand times more than the other intended to do to me (I killed him before he really did me any harm); and yet I can lawfully kill the one, and cannot so much as hurt the other lawfully. The reason for the difference is obvious. •The first man used force, which threatened my life, and I had no time to appeal to the law to make me safe. And once my life was taken, it would have been too late to appeal: the law couldn’t restore life to my dead carcass; the loss would have been irreparable; and it is in order to prevent that that the law of nature gave me a right to destroy the man who had put himself into a state of war with me and threatened my destruction. But •the second man did not put my life in danger; so I can have the benefit of appealing to the law and getting reparation for my £100 in that way.

208. Fourth:- If an official uses his power to maintain his unlawful acts and to obstruct the appeal to law for a remedy, this is manifest tyranny and there is a right to resist it; but even in cases like this, if the harm is slight there won’t be resistance that will disturb the government. For if the trouble concerns the cases of only a few private men, though they •have a right to defend themselves and to recover by force what through unlawful force has been taken from them, they will be disinclined to •exercise their right by engaging in a contest in which they are sure to perish. ·And they are sure to perish·, because it is as impossible for a few oppressed men to disturb the government when the body of the people don’t think themselves concerned in it as it is for a raving madman or headstrong malcontent to overturn a well settled state; the people being no more inclined to follow the oppressed few ·into a fight· than to follow the solitary madman.

68

Second Treatise John Locke 18: Tyranny

209. But suppose these illegal acts have affected the majority of the people, or have affected only a few but seem to set a dangerous precedent threatening everyone, so that the people are persuaded in their consciences that their laws are in danger and—along with the laws—their estates, liberties, and lives, and perhaps their religion too. When that happens, I can’t see how the people can be hindered from resisting the illegal force that has been ·or threatens to be· used against them. Such resistance is a difficulty that will confront any government in which the governors have managed to become generally suspected by their people. It is the most dangerous state that governors can possibly put themselves in, but they don’t deserve much pity because the trouble is so easy to avoid. If a governor really does intend the good of his people, and the preservation of them and their laws, the people are bound to see and feel this, just as the children in a family will see that their father loves and takes care of them.

210. But if everyone can see in the government

•claims of one kind, and actions of another;

•skill employed to evade the law;

•prerogative employed contrary to the purpose for which it was given (namely to do good, not harm, to the people);

•the ministers and lower officers of the law chosen with an eye to such purposes, and promoted or dismissed according to whether they further or oppose them;

•various things done as try-outs of arbitrary power: surreptitious favour shown to the religion (though publicly denounced) which is readiest to introduce such power, and the operators in it [= officials of the religion in question?] supported as much as the government can get away with, and, when open support isn’t possible, still ·surreptitiously· approved and liked;

- if a long train of actions show the ·governmental· councils all tending that way, how can a man not be convinced of which way things are going and look around for some way to save himself? Suppose you are in a ship whose captain is steering a course towards Algiers; cross-winds, leaks in his ship, and shortage of men and provisions often force him to head in a different direction, but as soon as the weather and other circumstances allow it he always turns back on course for Algiers. Won’t you conclude that the captain is trying to take you and everyone else in the ship to Algiers? [At that time Algiers was a maximally unattractive destination—a centre for maritime piracy, where many Englishmen were in slavery.]

69

Second Treatise John Locke 19: Dissolution of government

Chapter 19: The dissolution of government

211. Anyone who wants to speak clearly about the dissolution of •government ought first to distinguish that from the dissolution of a •society. What makes a community, and brings men out of the loose state of nature into one politic society, is the agreement that everyone has with everyone else to come together and act as one body and so be one distinct commonwealth. When such a union is dissolved, it is almost always through conquest by a foreign force; for when that happens (so that the people can’t maintain and support themselves as one unified and independent body), the union constituting that body that must necessarily come to an end, returning everyone to the state he was in before, with a liberty to provide for his own safety as he thinks fit, in some other society. Whenever the •society is dissolved, it is certain that the •government of that society can’t survive. Conquerors’ swords often cut off governments at the roots, mangling to pieces the societies and separating the subdued or scattered multitude from the protection of the society that ought to have preserved them from violence. This way of dissolving of governments is too well known—and too much allowed—for me to need to say anything more about it. It doesn’t need much argument to show that when a society is dissolved, its government can’t survive; just as the frame of a house can’t survive when the materials of it are scattered and dissipated by a whirlwind, or jumbled into a confused heap by an earthquake.

212. Governments can be dissolved not only by being overturned from outside but also by being dissolved from within. ·There are two ways for this to happen. I shall discuss one in this and the following eight sections, starting on the second in section 221·.

The first way is by the legislature’s being altered. Civil society is a state of peace among its members; they are kept from the state of war by the provisions they have made for the legislature to act as umpire, ending any conflicts that may arise among of them. So it is •the legislature that unites the members of a commonwealth, combining them into one coherent living body. •It is the soul that gives form, life, and unity to the commonwealth, bringing its various members into relationships of mutual influence, sympathy, and connection. Therefore, when the legislature is broken or dissolved, dissolution and death follow for the society, because the essence of the society, and its unity, consists in its having one will, declared and kept by a legislature established by the majority for that very purpose. The first and fundamental act of a society is the constituting of a legislature.... When one or more other people take it upon themselves to make laws, without being appointed to do so by the people, they are making laws without authority, so the people aren’t obliged to obey; and this is a way for them to come again out of subjection—·no longer under any government·—and be free to constitute for themselves a new legislature as they think best. For they will be entirely at liberty to resist the force of those who try without authority to impose anything upon them. When those whom the society has chosen to be the declarers of the public will are excluded from that role, and their place usurped by others who have not been appointed to it, everyone is free to do what he likes.

213. This is usually brought about by members of the commonwealth who have some power, and misuse it; so it’s hard to think about it clearly, and know who is to blame for it, unless we know the form of government in which it

70

Second Treatise John Locke 19: Dissolution of government

happens. So let us suppose that the legislature is placed in the agreement of three distinct persons. 1. •A single hereditary person, having the constant, supreme, executive power, and with it the power of convoking and dissolving the other two within certain periods of time. •2. An assembly of hereditary nobility. •3. An assembly of representatives chosen by the people to serve for limited periods of time. With a government of that form, four things are evident. ·I shall give them a section each·.

214. First, when such a single person (or king) sets up his own arbitrary will in place of the laws, which are the will of the society as declared by the legislature, then the legislature is changed. What makes something the legislature is its issuing rules and laws that are applied and required to be obeyed; so when laws are set up and rules announced and enforced other than those enacted by the legislature that the society has set up, it is clear that the legislature as been changed. Whoever subverts the old laws or introduces new laws without the authority of fundamental appointment [Locke’s phrase] by the society thereby disowns and overturns the power by which the old laws were made, and in that way sets up a new legislature.

215. Secondly, when the king prevents the legislature from assembling at its due time, or from acting freely to achieve the purposes for which it was set up, the legislature is altered. What constitutes a legislature is not merely •a certain number of men, or •a certain number of men meeting together, unless they have the freedom to discuss and enough time to complete the business of the good of the society. When the freedom or the time is taken away or altered, depriving the society of the ·fruits of· the proper exercise of the legislature’s power, the legislature is truly altered.... He who takes away the freedom or blocks the action of the legislature in its due seasons in effect takes away the legislature and puts an end to the government.

216. Thirdly, when, by the arbitrary power of the king changes are made in •who is to vote ·for members of the legislature· or in •how that vote is to be conducted, without the consent of the people and contrary to their common interests, there again the legislature is altered. For if the voting is done by people other than those whom the society has authorized to vote, or is done in another way than what the society has prescribed, those chosen are not the legislature appointed by the people.

217. Fourthly, if the people are delivered into the subjection of a foreign power, whether by the king or by the legislature, that is certainly a change of the legislature and thus a dissolution of the government....

218. It is obvious why, in a three-part form of government such as I supposed in section 213, the dissolution of the government in these ways is to be blamed on the king. He has at his disposal the force, the treasure and the offices of the state, and he may persuade himself—or be flattered by others into thinking—that as the supreme officer of the law he isn’t under any control. Because of all this, he is the only one in a position to make great advances toward such changes ·of the legislature· with a pretence of lawful authority; and he alone has available to him the means to terrify or suppress any who oppose him, saying that they are factious, seditious, and enemies to the government. In contrast with him, no other part of the legislature or the people as a whole can by themselves try to alter the legislature except by open and visible rebellion...., and when this prevails it has much the same effects as foreign conquest. Besides, the king in such a form of government has the power of dissolving the other parts of the legislature, thereby turning them into private

71

Second Treatise John Locke 19: Dissolution of government

persons; so they can never in opposition to him (or without his agreement) alter the legislature by a law, his consent being necessary to make any of their decrees valid. But if the other parts of the legislature do in any way contribute to any attempt on the government, and either promote such designs or fail to block them when they could have done so, they are guilty of taking part in this, which is certainly the greatest crime men can be guilty of towards one another.

219. There is one more way for such a government to be dissolved, and that is when ·the king·, he who has the supreme executive power, neglects and abandons his function so that laws that have already been made can no longer be •enforced. This is to reduce everything inevitably and immediately to anarchy, and so in effect to dissolve the government. Laws are not made for their own sakes but so as to serve as the bonds of the society that will keep every part of the body politic in its proper place and function; and they can do that only if they are •enforced. When enforcement stops, the government visibly comes to an end and the people become a confused, disorderly, disconnected multitude. When there is no longer any administration of justice for securing men’s rights, and no remaining power within the community to direct the public’s force or provide for its necessities, there is certainly no government left. When the laws can’t be applied it is the same as having no laws, and a government without laws is an absurdity....

220. In cases like these, when the government is dissolved the people are at liberty to provide for themselves by setting up a new legislature that differs from the previous one either in its personnel or its structure or both, depending on what the people find to be best for their safety and welfare. For a society can’t ever through someone else’s fault lose its inborn original right to preserve itself, which it can do only through a settled legislature and a fair and impartial application of the laws the legislature makes. But the state of mankind is not so miserable that they can’t use this remedy until it is too late, ·which is how things would stand if they couldn’t work towards a remedy until the government had entirely collapsed·. When a government has gone—whether by oppression, trickery, or being handed over to a foreign power—telling the people ‘You may provide for yourselves by setting up a new legislature’ is only telling them that they may expect relief when it is too late and the evil is past cure. It amounts to telling them to be slaves first, and then to take care of their liberty; and telling them when their chains are on that they may act like freemen. This is mockery rather than relief. Men can never be secure from tyranny if they have no way to escape from it until they are completely under it. And that’s why they have not only a right to get out of it but also a right to prevent it.

221. That brings us to the second way in which governments are dissolved (·discussion of the first began in section 212·), namely when the •legislature or the •king act contrary to their trust. ·I shall discuss this in two parts. The •legislature will be dealt with in this and the following ten sections; the king will come into section 222, but only as manipulating the legislature. Discussion of the •king as acting other than through the legislature will start at section 232·. The legislature acts against the trust given to them when they try to invade the property of the subject, and to make themselves—or any part of the community—masters of the lives, liberties, or fortunes of the people, having all of these at the disposal of their will.

222.....It can never be supposed to be the will of the society that the legislature should have a power to destroy what everyone aimed to keep safe by entering into society and

72

Second Treatise John Locke 19: Dissolution of government

submitting themselves to legislators of their own making. So when the legislators try to take away and destroy the property of the people or to reduce them to slavery, they put themselves into a state of war with the people, who are thereby absolved from any further obedience and are left to the common escape that God has provided for all men against force and violence. So whenever the legislature breaks this fundamental rule of society and—whether through ambition, fear, folly or corruption—try to grasp for themselves or for anyone else an absolute power over the lives, liberties, and estates of the people, by this breach of trust they forfeit the power the people had put into their hands for quite different purposes. And then the people have a right to resume their original ·natural· liberty, and to set up a new legislature....to provide for their own safety and security.... What I have said here about the legislature in general holds true also for the supreme executive, ·the king·. He has a double trust put in him, both •to have a part in the legislature and •to be in charge of the enforcement of the law; and he acts against both when he tries to set up his own arbitrary will as the law of the society. He also acts contrary to his trust when he either •employs the force, treasure, and offices of the society to corrupt the representatives and win them over to his schemes; or •openly courts the electorate, persuading them to choose the legislators whom he has already won over to his side by persuasion, threats, promises, or whatever—thus getting the electorate to bring in ones who have promised before-hand how they will vote and what legislation they will pass. Regulating candidates and electors in this way, re-shaping the electoral procedures—what is this but digging up the government by the roots, and poisoning the very fountain of public security? The people kept for themselves the choice of their representatives, as the fences around their properties; and the only reason they could have for this was so that the representatives would always be freely chosen, and—having been chosen—would freely act and advise in ways that they judged, after examination and mature debate, to be necessary for the commonwealth and the public good. Representatives can’t do this if they have given their votes in advance, before hearing the debate and weighing the reasons on all sides. For someone to prepare such a ·legislative· assembly as this, and try to set up the declared supporters of his own will as the true representatives of the people and the law-makers of the society, is certainly as great a breach of trust, and as complete an admission that he plans to subvert the government, as could be met with. If there is any doubt as to whether that is what is going on, it will be blown away if rewards and punishments are visibly employed for the same purpose, with all the tricks of perverted law being used to eliminate and destroy all who stand in the way of such a design and refuse to go along with and consent to betraying the liberties of their country. It is easy to see what power in the society ought to be allowed to those who have used their power contrary to the trust with which they were given it; anyone can see that someone who has once attempted such a thing as this can no longer be trusted ·with anything·.

223. You may want to object:

The people are ignorant and always discontented. To base government on their unsteady opinions and uncertain moods is to expose it to certain ruin. No government can last for long if the people can set up a new legislature whenever they take offence at the old one.

I answer, Quite the contrary! It is harder to get people out of their old forms ·of government· than some writers are apt to suggest. It is almost impossible to get them to amend the admitted faults in the system they have grown used

73

Second Treatise John Locke 19: Dissolution of government

to. And if there are any systemic defects, or less deep ones introduced by decay or by the passage of time, it’s hard to get them changed even when everyone sees that there’s an opportunity to do so. This slow reluctance of the people to give up their old constitutions has, in the many revolutions that have occurred in this kingdom recently and in earlier centuries, still kept us to our old legislature of •king, •lords and •commons (or, when we didn’t keep to it, there was a period of fruitless attempts ·to have a different form of government·, after which we returned to the system of king, lords, and commons). And whatever provocations have made the crown be taken from some of our monarchs’ heads, they never carried the people so far as to give it to someone who is not in the same line of descent.

224. ‘But’, it will be said, ‘this hypothesis creates a ferment for frequent rebellion!’ To which I have three answers. •First, It doesn’t do so more than any other hypothesis does: for when the people are made miserable and find themselves exposed to mistreatment by arbitrary power,

praise their governors as much as you will as sons of Jupiter, let them be sacred and divine, descended from heaven or authorized by it, make them out to be anyone or anything you please,

and the same thing will happen! The people who are generally and wrongfully ill-treated will be ready on any occasion to free themselves of a burden that sits heavily on them. They will want an opportunity to do this, and will look for one; and in the changes, weakness and accidents of human affairs they usually won’t have to look for long. Someone who hasn’t seen examples of this in his own lifetime must be very young, and someone who can’t cite examples of it in all sorts of governments in the world can’t have read much!

225. •Secondly, I answer that such revolutions don’t happen with every little mismanagement in public affairs. Great mistakes by the rulers, many wrong and inconvenient laws, and all the slips of human frailty—these will be born by the people without mutiny or murmur. But if a long series of abuses, lies, and tricks, all tending the same way, make the design visible to the people so that they can’t help •feeling what they are oppressed by and •seeing where they are going, it’s not surprising that they should then rouse themselves and try to put the ruling power into hands that will achieve for them the purposes for which government was at first established. When those purposes are not achieved, ·governments based on· ancient names and glittering rituals are no better than the state of nature, or pure anarchy. Indeed, they are worse, because under such governments the inconveniences are as great and as near as in the state of nature, and the remedy ·for them· further off and more difficult.

226. •Thirdly, to the charge that this hypothesis ‘creates a ferment for frequent rebellion’ I answer that ·on the contrary· this doctrine giving the people a power to provide anew for their safety by establishing a new legislature, when their legislators have acted contrary to their trust by invading their property, is the best barrier to rebellion and the best means to block it. Here is why. Rebellion is opposition not to •persons but to •authority, of which the only basis is the constitutions and laws of the government. So those who by force break through, and by force justify their violation of the constitution and laws, are truly and properly rebels. For when men by entering into society and civil-government have excluded force and introduced laws for the preservation of property, peace, and unity among themselves, those who set up force again in opposition to the laws do rebellare,

74

Second Treatise John Locke 19: Dissolution of government

that is, bring back again the state of war [bellare is Latin for ‘make war’, so that ‘rebel’ = rebellare = ‘make war again’]. Those who are most likely to rebel ·against the constitution and the laws· are those who are in power, because of their claim to authority, the temptation of the force they have at their disposal, and the flattery of those around them; and the best way to prevent this evil is to show those likely offenders the danger and injustice of it.

227. In both of the aforementioned cases, where

the legislature is changed,

and where

the legislators act contrary to the purpose for which they were made legislators,

those who are guilty are guilty of rebellion. [The rest of the section explains this. The explanation is very wordy, and can easily be worked out from what has gone before. In brief: someone who changes the legislature or who as a legislator acts contrary to his trust thereby introduces a state of war, he wars-again, he rebels.]

228. Those who say I am laying a foundation for rebellion mean that my doctrine may lead to civil wars or internal unrest. ·What do they infer from that·?

I tell the people •that they are absolved from obedience when illegal attempts are made upon their liberties or properties, and •that they may oppose the unlawful violence of those who were their law-officers, when they invade their properties contrary to the trust put in them.

Do my opponents hold that this doctrine of mine is not to be allowed because it is so destructive to the peace of the world? That would be like saying that honest men may not oppose robbers or pirates because this may lead to disorder or bloodshed! If any harm comes about in such a case, it is not to be charged against him who defends his own right but against him who attacks his neighbours. [The rest of the section jeeringly elaborates this comparison. A typical sample: ‘Who would not think it an admirable peace between the powerful and the weak when the lamb passively yields his throat to be torn by the imperious wolf?’]

229. The purpose of government is the good of mankind. Which is better for mankind: that the people be always exposed to the limitless will of tyranny, or that the rulers be sometimes liable to meet with opposition when they grow exorbitant in the use of their power and use it for the destruction and not the preservation of the properties of their people?

230. Don’t say: ‘Mischief can arise from that whenever it shall please a busy head or turbulent spirit [Locke’s phrase] to want to alter the government.’ Indeed, men like that may stir up trouble whenever they please, but it will be only to their own rightful ruin and perdition. That is because the people, who are more disposed to suffer than to right themselves by resistance, are not likely to rise up until the mischief has become general, and the wicked schemes of the rulers have become visible or their attempts have made themselves felt in the lives of the majority. They are not moved by individual examples of injustice, here and there an unfortunate man oppressed. But if they all become convinced on clear evidence that schemes are being launched against their liberties, and the general course and tendency of things forces them to suspect the evil intention of their governors, who is to be blamed for that? Who can help it if rulers bring themselves under this suspicion when they could have avoided it? Are the people to be blamed if they have the sense of rational creatures, and think of things as they find and feel them?.... I grant that the pride, ambition,

75

Second Treatise John Locke 19: Dissolution of government

and turbulence of private men have sometimes caused great disorders in commonwealths, and factions have been fatal to states and kingdoms. But whether the mischief has oftener begun in

•the people’s irresponsibility and a desire to throw off the lawful authority of their rulers, or in

•the rulers’ insolence and attempts to get and exercise an arbitrary power over their people,

i.e. whether it has usually been

•disobedience or •oppression

that started the disorder, I leave to impartial history to decide. I am sure of this, though. Anyone—whether ruler or subject—who by force tries to invade the rights of either monarch or people, and lays the foundation for overturning the constitution and structure of any just government, is highly guilty of the greatest crime a man is capable of. Such a person must answer for all the mischiefs of blood, looting, and desolation that come on a country when its government is broken to pieces. And he who does it should be regarded as the common enemy and pest of mankind, and treated accordingly.

231. Everyone agrees that •subjects or •foreigners who bring force against the properties of any people may be resisted with force. But it has recently been denied that one may resist •law-officers who do the same thing. As if those to whom the laws give the greatest privileges and advantages automatically get also a power to break those laws, the very laws that put them in a better place than their brethren! Actually, their privileged position makes their offence even worse: in it they •show themselves as ungrateful for the bigger share that the law gives them, and they •break the trust that was put into their hands by their brethren.

232. Anyone who uses force without right (as everyone in society does if he uses force without law) puts himself into a •state of war with those against whom he uses it; and in •that state all former bonds are cancelled, all other rights cease, and everyone has a right to defend himself, and to resist the aggressor. This is so obvious that Barclay himself, that great assertor of the power and sacredness of kings, is forced to admit that it is sometimes lawful for the people to resist their king; and he says it, what’s more, in a chapter in which he offers to show that the divine law blocks the people from every kind of •rebellion! In fact his own doctrine makes it clear that since the people may •resist in some cases, not all resistance to monarchs is rebellion. His words are these. [Locke gives them first in Latin in this section, then in English occupying the whole of the next section.]

233. Someone may ask:

Must the people then always lay themselves open to the cruelty and rage of tyranny? Must they see their cities pillaged and reduced to ashes, their wives and children exposed to the tyrant’s lust and fury, and themselves and their households brought by their king to ruin and to all the miseries of want and oppression—and yet sit still? The common privilege of opposing force with force, which nature allows so freely to all other creatures for their preservation from injury—must men alone be debarred from having it?

I answer that self-defence is a part of the law of nature, and it can’t be denied to the community, even against the king himself; but that law doesn’t allow them to revenge themselves upon him. So if the king in hatred sets himself not merely against this or that person but against the body of the commonwealth of which he is the head, and with intolerable ill usage cruelly tyrannizes over all or many

76

Second Treatise John Locke 19: Dissolution of government

of the people, then the people have a right to resist and defend themselves from injury. But in doing this they must be careful only to •defend themselves, and not to •attack their king. They may make good the damages they have received, but must not under any provocation cross the line of appropriate reverence and respect. They may push back the present attempt but must not take revenge for past violences; for it is natural for us to •defend life and limb, but it is against nature for •an inferior to punish a superior.... So this is the privilege of the people in general, as compared with any private person: particular men....have no other remedy but patience, whereas the body of the people may respectfully resist intolerable tyranny. ·I stress intolerable; for when the tyranny is only moderate they ought to endure it·. [End of quotation from Barclay]

234. That is the extent to which this great advocate of monarchical power allows for resistance.

235. It is true that he has put two limitations on such resistance. First, •it must be done with reverence. Secondly, •it must be without retribution or punishment because an inferior cannot punish a superior. First, it will need some skill to make clear how one is to resist force without striking back, or how to strike with reverence! Someone who opposes an assault with nothing but a shield to take the blows, or in some more respectful posture but without a sword in his hand tries to lessen the assailant’s confidence and force, will quickly come to the end of his resistance and will find that such a defence will only serve to make things worse for him. [Locke now quotes the Latin poet Juvenal to that effect. Then:] This will always be the outcome of such an imaginary ‘resistance’ in which men may not strike back. So someone who is allowed to resist must be allowed to strike. And then let our author or anyone else join a knock on the head or a cut on the face with as much reverence and respect as he thinks fit. For all I know, someone who can reconcile blows with reverence deserves to be rewarded for his ·reconciling· labours by being beaten up only in a civil and respectful manner. Secondly, An inferior cannot punish a superior. That is true, generally speaking, while he is his superior. But resisting force with force is the state of war that levels the ground and cancels all former relations of reverence, respect, and superiority. The only superior/inferior relationship that remains is this: he who opposes the unjust aggressor is his superior in that he has a right when he wins to punish the offender, both for the breach of the peace and for all the evils that followed from it. So Barclay is more consistent with himself when, in another place, he denies that it is ever lawful to resist a king. But in that place he describes two ways in which a king may un-king himself. [Again Locke gives them first in Latin, starting in this section and running on to the end of 236, and then in English in the following two sections.]

237.....The people can never come by a power over the king unless he does something that makes him cease to be a king. When he does that, he divests himself of his crown and dignity, and returns to the state of a private man; and then the people become free and superior, regaining the power that they had....before they crowned him king. But there aren’t many ways for this to happen. After considering it thoroughly I can find only two cases in which a king ceases to be a king and loses all power and regal authority over his people.... The first is, •if he tries to overturn the government, that is, if he plans to ruin the kingdom and commonwealth. An example is Nero, of whom it is recorded that he resolved to cut off the senate and people of Rome, lay the city waste with fire and sword, and then go to some other place. And

77

Second Treatise John Locke 19: Dissolution of government

Caligula is reported to have openly declared that he would no longer be a head to the people or the senate, and that he was thinking of cutting off the worthiest men of both ranks and then retiring to Alexandria; and that he wished that the people had only one neck so that he could kill them all by one blow. When any king harbours in his thoughts such plans as these, and seriously promotes them, he thereby gives up all care and thought of the commonwealth, and consequently loses the power of governing his subjects—just as a master loses command over his slaves when he abandons them.

238. The other case is •when a king makes himself dependent on someone else, and subjects his kingdom—left to him by his ancestors and freely put into his hands by the people—to the command of that other person. Even if the king doesn’t intend to harm the people, he has alienated [here = ‘made to be foreign’] his kingdom: because he has •given up the principal part of royal dignity, namely being immediately under God supreme in his kingdom; and also •because he betrayed or forced his people, whose liberty he ought to have carefully preserved, into the power and dominion of a foreign nation. By this alienation (as it were) of his kingdom he loses the power he had in it previously, without transferring the faintest right to those to whom he wants to give the power; and so by this he act sets the people free, leaving them to behave as they see fit. [End of quotation from Barclay]

239. Barclay, the great champion of absolute monarchy, is forced to allow that in these cases a king may be resisted and stops being a king. Cutting a long story short: when he has no authority he is no king, and may be resisted, for where the authority ceases the king ceases too, and becomes like other men who have no authority. The two circumstances that Barclay mentions don’t differ much from the ones I cited as destructive to governments. The only difference is that he omits the principle from which his doctrine flows, namely the breach of trust involved in •not preserving the form of government that had been agreed on, and in •not aiming to achieve the purpose of government as such, which is the public good and preservation of property. When a king has dethroned himself and entered a state of war against his people, what is to hinder them from prosecuting him—no longer a king—as they would any other man who has made war against them? Barclay and those who agree with him would do well to answer that. Notice that Barclay says that the people may prevent planned harm before it occurs; so he allows resistance when tyranny is still at the design stage. He says that when any king harbours in his thoughts and seriously promotes such designs, he immediately gives up all care and thought of the commonwealth; so that according to Barclay the neglect of the public good is to be taken as an evidence of such a design, or at least as a sufficient ground for resistance. And he gives the reason for all this in these words: ‘Because he betrayed or forced his people, whose liberty he ought carefully to have preserved...’ What he adds, namely ‘... into the power and dominion of a foreign nation’, signifies nothing; because the fault and forfeiture comes from the loss of their liberty, which he ought to have preserved, and not from any facts about which persons the power was handed over to. Whether they are made slaves to members of their own nation or a foreign one, the people’s right is invaded and their liberty lost, just the same; and this is the injury, and against only this do they have the right of defence. And there are instances to be found in all countries which show that what gives offence is not the change of nationality in their governors but the change of government. [Locke then names several writers who agree with his position and who cannot be suspected to be ignorant of our government or to be enemies to it’. And

78

Second Treatise John Locke 19: Dissolution of government

he writes scornfully of those who have endorsed Hooker’s political conclusions while denying his Lockean premises. Their work, he says, can be twisted around by ‘cunninger workmen’ to serve even worse purposes. He describes the latter as men who were willing when it suited them to ‘resolve all government into absolute tyranny, and hold that all men are born to slavery, which is what their skimpy souls fitted them for’.]

240. At this point you are likely to ask:

Who is to be the judge of whether the monarch or legislature have acted contrary to their trust? That they have so acted is the sort of thing that can be spread around among the people by discontented and factious men, when all the king has done is to make use of his legitimate prerogative.

To this I reply, The people should be judge; for who should judge whether a trustee or deputy has acted well and according to the trust reposed in him, if not the person who deputes him? Having deputed him, he must have still a power to discard him when he fails in his trust. If this is reasonable in particular cases of private men, why should it be otherwise in this most important case where the welfare of millions is concerned, and where the threatened evil is greater, and redressing it is very difficult, costly, and dangerous?

241. Furthermore, the question ‘Who is to be the judge?’ can’t mean that there is no judge at all; for when there is no judicature on earth to decide controversies among men, God in heaven is the judge. It is true that God alone is the judge of what is right. But every man is judge for himself, in this case as in all others, of whether another man has put himself into a state of war with him, and whether he should appeal to the supreme judge.

242. If a controversy arises between a king and some of the people, in a matter of great importance where the law is silent, or doubtful, I think the right umpire would be the body of the people. For in cases where the king has a trust placed in him and is dispensed from the common ordinary rules of the law, if any ·private· men are aggrieved and think that the king acts beyond that trust or contrary to it, the body of the people who first placed that trust in him are clearly the best judges of how far they meant the trust to extend. If that way of settling the matter is turned down by the king, or whoever is administering the government, the only court of appeal is in heaven.... ·What we have here is· properly a state of war, in which the only appeal is to heaven; and in that state the injured party must judge for himself when it is fit for him to make such an appeal.

243. To conclude, the power that every individual gave to the society when he entered into it can never revert to the individuals again as long as the society lasts, but will always remain in the community; because without this there can’t be a community, a commonwealth, and that would be contrary to the original agreement. So also when the society has placed the legislative power in any assembly of men, to continue in them and their successors with direction and authority for providing such successors, the legislative power can never revert to the people while that government lasts; because having provided a legislature with power to continue for ever, they have given to it their political power and cannot get it back. But •if they have set limits to the duration of their legislature, and given this supreme power to some person or assembly only temporarily, or •if it is forfeited through the misbehaviour of those in authority, •at the set time or •at the time of the forfeiture the power does revert to the society, and then the people have a right to act as supreme and to continue the legislature in themselves; or to set up a new form of government, or retain the old form while placing it in new hands, as they see fit.

79

Second Treatise John Locke On children

Locke on children

[In this work, especially in section 170, Locke endorses a kindly exercise of parental power. His feeling for children and for how they should be managed was notable, given his circumstances (he was a childless bachelor) and the time and place where he lived. Here is a version of a passage from his work Some Thoughts Concerning Education (at his time ‘education’ often meant more generally ‘upbringing’).]

62. The rebukes and criticisms that children’s faults will sometimes make almost unavoidable should be given in calm, serious words, and alone and in private; whereas the commendations children deserve should be given in the presence of others. This doubles the reward by spreading their praise; and the parents’ reluctance to make the chilldren’s faults public will make the children set a greater value on their own good name, and teach them to be all the more careful to preserve the good opinion of others while they think they have it. Whereas if their misbehaviour is made public and they are exposed to shame, they will take it that their good name is lost; that check on them will be taken off; and the more they suspect that their reputation with other people is already blemished, the less they will care about preserving others’ good thoughts of them.

63. But if children are brought up in the right way, there won’t be as much need for the usual rewards and punishments as we have imagined there is, and as the general practice has established. All the innocent folly, playing and childish actions of children should be left perfectly free and unrestrained as far is consistent with the respect due to others who are present; and that should be interpreted very liberally. These faults (not of •the children but of •their age) should be left to be cured by time and good examples and increasing maturity. If that were done, children would escape a great deal of misapplied and useless correction, which is bad in one or other of these two ways. (1) It fails to overpower the natural ·high-spirited· disposition of childhood; so it is applied more and more often, always ineffectively; and this robs it of effectiveness in cases where it is necessary. (2) It is effective in restraining the natural gaiety of the young, so that it serves only to harm the child’s mental and physical make-up. When the noise and bustle of children’s play proves to be inconvenient, or unsuitable to the place or company they are in (which can only be where their parents are), a look or a word from the father or mother will be enough to get them either to leave the room or to quieten down for a while—that is, this will be enough if the parents have established the authority that they should. But ·on most occasions· this playful mood, which is wisely adapted by nature to their age and character, should be encouraged, to keep up their spirits and improve their strength and health, rather than curbed or restrained. The main skill ·in child-rearing· is to bring some sport and play into everything they have to do.

80

Toleration

conventionally known as “A Letter about Toleration”

John Locke

Copyright ©2010–2015 All rights reserved. Jonathan Bennett
[Brackets] enclose editorial explanations. Small ·dots· enclose material that has been added, but can be read as though it were part of the original text. Occasional •bullets, and also indenting of passages that are not quotations, are meant as aids to grasping the structure of a sentence or a thought. Every four-point ellipsis .... indicates the omission of a brief passage that seems to present more difficulty than it is worth. Longer omissions are reported between brackets in normal-sized type.—Locke wrote this in Latin; there was a contemporary English translation, and the question of how much Locke knew or affected it is controversial. It is fairly accurate, though very wordy; the present version has some debts to it, but the Latin has been consulted at every stage.—The section-breaks and -titles are all added in this version.—About the title: the work was originally published (not by Locke) in the form of a letter, but that was a scam. In his edition of the work (Nijhoff, 1963) Mario Montuori presents the scholarly case for this; and anyone who reads the thing with an intelligent eye will see that Montuori is right: it obviously wasn’t written as a letter. See the note on page 4.
First launched: May 2010
[This single-column (but otherwise unrevised) version by Philosophy Ink derives from the original two-column PDF version at http://www.earlymoderntexts.com. Even Bennett's pagination has been retained since he sometimes makes in-text references to his own page numbers.]

Toleration John Locke

Contents

1: The insincerity of the zealots
2: The role of the civil magistrate
3: What is a church?
4: The limits on toleration
5: The magistrate's role in all this:
6: Church and state: forms of worship
7: Idolatry
8: Church and state: articles of faith
9: Individual conscience
10. What should not be tolerated
11: Gatherings
12: Heresy and schism

Toleration John Locke 1: The insincerity of the zealots

1: The insincerity of the zealots

I have been asked what I think about the mutual toleration of Christians in their different professions of religion; I have to answer freely that I regard such toleration as the chief identifying mark of the true Church. When some people boast of •the antiquity of places and names, or of the pomp of their outward worship; others of •the reformation of their discipline; everyone of •the orthodoxy of their faith (for everyone is orthodox to himself!), this conduct and other behaviour of the same kind are marks of men striving for power and domination over one another much more than marks of the Church of Christ. Even if someone has an absolutely true claim to all these things, if he lacks charity, meekness, and good-will in general towards all mankind, even to those who are not Christians, he certainly falls short of being a true Christian himself. ‘The kings of the Gentiles exercise leadership over them’, said our Saviour to his disciples, ‘but you shall not be so.’ [Luke 22:25] True religion is something different: it exists not to create

•external pomp, or

•ecclesiastical dominance, or

•force ·of any kind·,

but rather to create virtuous and pious lives. Anyone who wants to enlist in Christ’s Church must above all declare war on his own lusts and vices. No-one will do himself any good by calling himself a Christian unless his life is holy, his conduct pure, and his spirit kind and gentle.... I would find it hard to believe that someone who is careless about his own salvation is concerned for mine. It’s not possible for someone who hasn’t really embraced the Christian religion in his own heart to try with all his strength to make other people Christians. According to the Gospel and the apostles, no-one can be a Christian unless he has •charity and •the faith that works through love, not through force. Now, I appeal to the consciences of those who persecute, wound, torture, and kill other men on the excuse of ‘religion’, whether they do this in a spirit of friendship and kindness. What would it take to convince me that they do? I would need to see those fiery zealots

•correcting in the same way their friends and members of their own household for their open sins against the Gospel’s teachings;

•persecuting with fire and sword their own parishioners who are tainted with enormous vices and at risk of eternal damnation if they don’t change, expressing their love and desire for the salvation of their souls by all sorts of cruelties and tortures.

The zealots claim that they are acting out of love and care for men’s souls when they take their estates, maim them with whips, starve and torture them in stinking prisons, and finally kill them. If that is right—if all this is done merely to make men Christians and save their souls—then why don’t these zealots also go after the prostitution, fraud, malice, and so on....that are so conspicuous among their flocks? These and their like are certainly more contrary to God’s glory, to the Church’s purity, and to the salvation of souls, than •any conscientious dissent from ecclesiastical decisions, or •not going to church but leading an innocent life. Why does this zeal for God, for the Church, and for the salvation of souls—zeal that goes all the way to burning people to death—•let pass without criticism moral vices and wickednesses that everyone thinks are flatly contrary to Christian belief, yet •stretch itself to the introducing of

1

Toleration John Locke 1: The insincerity of the zealots

ceremonies or establishing of opinions that are mostly about fine-grained and intricate matters that ordinary folk can’t understand? In these controversies which side is in the right and which guilty of schism or heresy? That will finally be decided when the cause of their separation comes to be judged. [Perhaps Locke meant ‘... judged by God on Judgment Day’; but ‘finally’ could instead point to the last chapter in the present work, where ‘heresy’ and ‘schism’ are defined in ways that make the ‘which is guilty?’ question fairly easy for us to answer.] Anyone who follows Christ, accepts His doctrine, and bears His yoke is not a heretic—even if he cuts himself off from his father and mother or anyone else, and from the public assemblies and ceremonies of his country or anything else.

Sectarian divisions ·within Christianity· may be enormously harmful to the salvation of souls; but concerning such ‘works of the flesh’ as

adultery,

fornication,

personal dirtiness,

sexual misconduct, and

idol-worship

the apostle [Paul] has clearly said that ‘they who do them shall not inherit the kingdom of God’ [Galatians 5:19–21]. So anyone who really cares about enlarging God’s kingdom ought to work just as hard and carefully on rooting out of these immoralities as on wiping out sects. And someone who doesn’t do this—someone who is cruel and implacable towards those who differ from him in doctrine, but is indulgent towards vices and immoralities that are just as much at odds with the label ‘Christian’—well, let him •talk as much as he likes about the Church, his •actions prove that he is concerned not with God’s kingdom but with something else [or the Latin may mean: ‘... but with some other kingdom’]. Someone who intensely desires that another man be saved acts on that desire by having the other man die in agony, still unconverted—that seems very strange to me and I think it would seem strange to anyone else; and surely no-one will ever believe that such behaviour can come from love, from benevolence, from charity. If someone

•holds that men should be compelled by fire and sword to profess certain doctrines and conform one kind of exterior worship, and pays no attention to their morals;

—if someone

•tries to convert people to ‘the faith’ by forcing them to profess things that they don’t believe and allowing them to behave in ways that the Gospel does not permit—

it’s clear that he wants his own group to have as many members as possible; but he thinks the group is a Christian church?—no-one will believe that! No wonder these people use weapons that don’t belong in the Christian armoury: they aren’t fighting for true religion and the Christian Church. If they sincerely wanted the good of souls, as the Captain of our salvation did, they would follow the perfect example of that Prince of peace, who sent out His troops—to subdue the nations and pull them into His Church—armed not with •swords or other weapons but with •the Gospel of peace and with the holiness of what they had to say. This was actually a more efficient way of going about it, with armies of heavenly legions, than could be achieved in the other way by any son of the Church, however powerful, with all his battalions.

Tolerating those who differ from us in matters of religion is so fitting to the Gospel and to reason that it seems monstrous for men to fail to see this clearly. I don’t want here to go on about the pride and ambition of some, the intemperate passion and uncharitable zeal of others; those are faults that may be inevitable in any human affairs, though no-one will

2

Toleration John Locke 2: The role of the civil magistrate

outright admit to them.... But I do want to help putting an end to the activities of (1) people who plead a concern for ‘the public good and obedience to the laws of the land’ as an excuse for their persecution and unchristian cruelty, and of (2) those who expect to get away with libertinism and licentiousness on grounds of ‘religion’; that is, in short, stopping anyone from imposing on himself or others by the claim that he is (1) loyal and obedient to the monarch or (2) sincere in his worship of God. To achieve this, it is utterly necessary that we draw a precise boundary-line between (1) the affairs of civil government and (2) the affairs of religion. If we don’t, there will be no end to the controversies arising between those who have (or at least pretend to have) (2) a concern for men’s souls and those who have (or at least pretend to have) (1) a care for the commonwealth.

2: The role of the civil magistrate

[The word ‘magistrate’ [Latin magistratus] will be used here, in a sense that was common in early modern times, to stand for whoever it is that makes and enforces a state’s laws. That includes magistrates in our sense of the word, but also high court judges, legislators, monarchs, and so on. In a given case the magistrate might be a committee, or a system; Latin doesn’t distinguish ‘he’ from ‘it’; but ‘he’ will be used throughout this version. ]

The commonwealth seems to me to be a society of men constituted only for the purpose of preserving and promoting the public good.

By ‘the public good’ I mean: life, liberty, freedom from bodily illness and pain, and the possession of things such as money, land, ·houses·, furniture, and so on.

The civil magistrate’s job is....to secure, for the people in general and for each one in particular, the just possession of these worldly things. If anyone tries to violate the laws governing this, he should be deterred by the fear of punishment, consisting of the lessening or outright loss of the goods that he otherwise might and ought to enjoy. Because no-one willingly allows himself to be punished by the loss of any of his goods, let alone his liberty or his life, the magistrate in punishing those who violate any other man’s rights is armed with the force and strength of all his subjects.

I shall now present some arguments which seem to me to show conclusively that •the magistrate’s jurisdiction doesn’t extend beyond these civic concerns, •that all civil power, law and dominion is restricted to the protection of the public goods I have listed, and that •it can’t and oughtn’t to be extended to the salvation of souls.

(1) The care of souls is not committed to the civil magistrate any more than it is to other men. It isn’t committed to him by God, because it seems that God hasn’t ever given any man the authority to compel someone else to join his religion. And such a power can’t be given to the magistrate by the people, because no-one can be so unconcerned about his own salvation that he blindly leaves it to someone

3

Toleration John Locke 2: The role of the civil magistrate

else—whether monarch or subject—to tell him what faith or worship to embrace. And anyway •the life and power of true religion consists in faith, •·faith involves believing·, and •no-one can just believe what someone else tells him to believe, even if he wants to. Whatever we ·audibly· say, whatever outward worship we conform to, if we aren’t fully convinced that what we say is true and how we worship is pleasing to God,....we’ll merely have set up obstacles to our salvation....by adding •hypocrisy and •contempt of God’s majesty to our catalogue of sins.

(2) It can’t be up to the magistrate to take care of souls, because his power consists only in outward force, whereas true and saving religion consists in the inward faith of the soul, without which nothing can be acceptable to God, and which the nature of the human mind won’t allow to be compelled by any outward force. Confiscation of goods, imprisonment, torture—nothing like that can make men change their inward judgments about things.

[Locke’s next few words might suggest that this work was written as a letter to the person who claimed to have been its recipient; but here and elsewhere Locke uses ‘You say:’ to introduce thoughts that he knew that man would not have had. These are addressed simply to the reader, whoever he or she may be. On page 27 he uses ‘you say’ and the like in addressing a heretic.]

But you say: ‘The magistrate can use arguments that will draw the heterodox to the truth, and effect their salvation.’ So he can, but so can anyone else. In teaching, instructing, and correcting error by reason, he can certainly do what any good man can fittingly do; being a magistrate doesn’t stop him from still being human and Christian. But it is one thing to persuade, another to command; one thing to press with arguments, another with judicial rulings.... The civil power should not ·try to· establish any articles of faith or doctrine, or any forms of worship, by the force of its laws. Laws without penalties have no force, and in our present context penalties are just silly, because they have no power to change anyone’s mind.... The only way to change men’s opinions is through light, and you can’t produce light ·in someone’s mind· by torturing him.

(3) It can’t be the civil magistrate’s job to care for the salvation of men’s souls, because even if laws and penalties could change men’s minds, that would do nothing for the salvation of their souls. Even if there were only one truth, one road to the heavenly home, what hope is there that more men would be led into it if they had to •walk out on the light of their own reason, •oppose the dictates of their own consciences, and •blindly submit to the will of their governors and worship God in the way that was established by law in the countries where they were born? In the variety of opinions in religion, the narrow way into heaven would be narrow indeed! It would be open only to those from one geographical region; whether a man received eternal happiness or eternal misery would depend on where he was born—which is utterly absurd and not worthy of God.

I could have presented other considerations leading to the same conclusion; but the ones I have given seem to me sufficient to show that the civil government’s power relates only to the public good, attending only to the care of the things of this world and having nothing to do with the world to come.

4

Toleration John Locke 3: What is a church?

3: What is a church?

Let us now consider what a church is. A church seems to me to be a free society of men who voluntarily come together to worship God in a way that they think is acceptable to Him and effective in saving their souls.

I repeat: a ‘free’ society that men join ‘voluntarily’. No-one is born a member of a church; otherwise the religion of parents and grandparents would be inherited by the children in the same way that they inherit wealth and land—and you can’t imagine anything more absurd than that. So there it is: No-one is by nature bound to any particular church or sect; everyone voluntarily joins the society in which he thinks he has found the creed and mode of worship that is truly acceptable to God. He joined that communion in the hope of salvation, and that hope is the only reason he can have for staying there. If later on he discovers something erroneous in the doctrine or unsuitable in the worship, he should be just as free to leave that society as he was to join it in the first place. He can’t be held by any bonds except what come from the certain expectation of eternal life. A church, then, is a society of members voluntarily uniting for that purpose.

What we have to consider now is what power this church has and what laws it is subject to.

No society, however free it is, and however slight the basis is for its existing—whether it is a society

•of scholars for doing philosophy,

•of merchants for transacting business, or

•of men of leisure for conversation and the exchange of ideas,

—can survive and not fall to pieces unless it is regulated by some laws; and the same holds for any church. Place and time of meeting must be agreed on; conditions for membership and for exclusion must be established; and so on.... But since the members of this society ·or church· joined it freely and without coercion, as I have shown, it follows that the right of making its laws must belong to the society itself—or anyway to those whom the society has by common consent authorised to do this.

But you say: ‘No society can be a true church unless it has a bishop or presbyter with ruling authority derived—through an uninterrupted succession—from the apostles themselves.’ ·I have three things to say in reply to that.·

(1) Show me the edict by which Christ imposed that law on His Church—I mean one that says this clearly and explicitly. I have a point in demanding this, namely that Christ seemed to imply the opposite, when he promised us that ‘wheresoever two or three are gathered together’ in His name He will be in the midst of them [Matthew 18:20]. Think about it: does an assembly that has Christ in the midst of them lack anything needed to make it a true church? It certainly doesn’t lack anything needed for the salvation of souls, and that is all that matters.

(2) Consider those who lay so much stress on a continuous succession of church rulers coming down from Christ’s founding of the Church: look at how greatly they have disagreed among themselves! These disagreements ·over which of them is ‘the true Church’· puts us in a position to think about it and to choose the church of our preference.

(3) I’ll admit that your church has a ruler established by as long a succession as you like, if you’ll admit that I am free to join the society that I believe contains what I need for the salvation of my soul....

5

Toleration John Locke 3: What is a church?

It is fair to ask those who are so solicitous about ‘the true Church’ the following question. Consider these two:

•The conditions for belonging to the Church consist purely in things that the Holy Spirit has in the Scriptures explicitly declared to be necessary to salvation;

•Men may impose their own inventions and interpretations on others as if they were of divine authority, and may establish by ecclesiastical laws—as absolutely necessary to the profession of Christianity—things that the Holy Scriptures don’t mention or anyway don’t explicitly command.

My question is this: Which of those is more agreeable to the Church of Christ? Someone who requires for ecclesiastical communion things that Christ doesn’t require for eternal life may go ahead and create a society that fits his opinion and his purposes; but a society based on laws that are not Christ’s, which excludes from its membership people whom He will one day receive into the Kingdom of Heaven—how can that be called a church of Christ?.... The Gospel often declares that the true disciples of Christ must suffer persecution; but I can’t find anywhere in the New Testament that the Church of Christ is to persecute others, and force others by fire and sword to embrace her faith and doctrine.

The purpose of a religious society (I repeat) is the public worship of God and through that the acquisition of eternal life. That should set the limits •to discipline within such a society and •to all ecclesiastical laws. Nothing should or could be transacted in this society relating to public goods or the possession of land; no force is to be used here on any occasion whatsoever, for force belongs wholly to the civil magistrate, and the ownership of external goods is under his jurisdiction.

You say: ‘Then what sanction can ecclesiastical laws have if they can’t be backed up by force?’ I answer:.... The ‘arms’—·the ‘force·’—by which the members of this society are kept in line consist in exhortations, warnings, and advice. If these don’t succeed in correcting the delinquents and redirecting those who stray, the only thing the society can do with these stubborn and obstinate people for whom there is no hope of reformation is to throw them out. This is the last and utmost ‘force’ of ecclesiastical authority. In such a punishment the whole effect of the punishment is that the offender stops being a member of that church; nothing more.

Having settled these things, let us turn now to the question of the limits on official toleration.

6

Toleration John Locke 4: The limits on toleration

4: The limits on toleration

·BETWEEN A CHURCH AND ITS MEMBERS·
No church is obliged as a matter of toleration to retain as a member anyone who, after warnings, continues obstinately to offend against the society’s laws. The laws are what hold the society together; if members could break them with impunity, the society would collapse. Still, care should be taken that the process of excommunication—what is said and what is done—doesn’t involve anything by which the person in question is physically or financially harmed. For all force (I repeat) belongs only to the magistrate; no private persons should ever use force except in self-defence. Excommunication doesn’t and can’t deprive the excommunicated person of any civil goods that he formerly possessed: all those things are matters for the civil government and are under the magistrate’s protection. The whole force of excommunication consists in the society’s declaration that

one of its members is being separated from the main body—·amputated, as it were·—and with the ending of that connection there is also an end to that person’s participating in certain activities that the society allows to its members.

These are activities that no-one has a civil right to engage in; a person doesn’t suffer a civil injury if a church minister refuses him the bread and wine (in celebrating the Lord’s Supper) which was bought with someone else’s money.

·BETWEEN PRIVATE PERSONS·
No private person has any right to encroach in any way on another person’s civil goods because he declares his allegiance to another church or religion. Anything that a man has as a matter of human rights or civil rights is to remain inviolably his. These are none of religion’s business. Whether the man is Christian or pagan, he is to be kept safe from violence and injury. Indeed, we should go beyond mere justice, adding benevolence and charity; the Gospel commands this, reason urges it, and it is favoured by the natural fellowship we are born into. [That is our fellowship merely as human beings; our •natural membership of that group stands in contrast with our •voluntary membership of a church or other society.] If someone strays from the right path, that is his misfortune, not yours; and your belief that he will be miserable in the after-life is not a reason for you to give him a bad time in his present life.

·BETWEEN CHURCH AND CHURCH·
What I say about toleration between private persons who differ in religion applies also to particular churches; they relate to one another pretty much as private persons do, with none of them—even ones to which the civil magistrate belongs—having any kind of jurisdiction over any other. The civil government can’t give a church any new rights, any more than a church can do that for the civil government. A church starts as a free and voluntary society, and it retains that status whether or not a magistrate joins it or leaves it. The magistrate’s joining doesn’t give a church the power of the sword, and his leaving doesn’t deprive it of its right to instruct and to excommunicate. This is the basic unchangeable situation of a spontaneous society: it has the power to remove any of its members who break its rules; and it can’t, through the acquisition of new members, come to have jurisdiction over anyone who doesn’t belong to it. So there should be, between churches as between private persons, equity and friendship with no claims of superiority or jurisdiction.

7

Toleration John Locke 4: The limits on toleration

For an example that may help to clarify this, let us suppose that the city of Constantinople [today’s Istanbul] contains two churches, one of Calvinists and the other of Arminians [= roughly ‘Dutch protestant anti-Calvinists’]. Will anyone say that one of these churches has a right to confiscate the goods of the members of the other (we see this happening in some places) or to exile or execute them, just because they differ in some doctrines and ceremonies, while the Turks stand around laughing at how cruelly Christians rage against Christians? If one of these churches does have this power of ill-treating the other, •which of them is it? and •why? No doubt someone will answer that it’s the orthodox church that has authority over the erroneous or heretical one. This is an inflated way of saying nothing. Every church is orthodox to itself and erroneous or heretical to the others;....so that the controversy between these churches about the truth of their doctrines and the correctness of their worship is a stand-off; and no judicial authority, in Constantinople or anywhere else, can give a judgment that settles it. That decision is to be made only by the Supreme Judge of all men. To Him alone belongs the punishment of those who are in error....

And even if we did know for sure which of these two quarreling churches was in the right, that wouldn’t give to that church the right to destroy the other. Churches have no jurisdiction in worldly matters, and anyway fire and sword are not proper instruments for correcting men’s errors and informing them of the truth. Suppose, however, that the civil magistrate is inclined to favour one of the churches and to give them his sword with permission to use it to chastise the dissenters as they pleased. Will anyone say that a Christian church can get jurisdiction over its brethren from a Turkish emperor? [See note on ‘magistrate’ on page 3.] An unbeliever who doesn’t himself have any authority to punish Christians for the articles of their faith can’t confer such an authority on any society of Christians, giving them a right that he doesn’t have himself. And the reason why that is so in Constantinople is equally a reason in any Christian kingdom. The civil power is the same everywhere; the civil power that a Christian prince can give to a church is the same as what a heathen prince can give—namely nothing.

It is worthwhile to notice that the most hostile of these defenders of truth, these opposers of error, these protestors against schism, hardly ever let fly with their burning zeal for God unless they have the civil magistrate on their side. But when the magistrate gives them the upper hand, the peace and charity that they have been maintaining are immediately laid aside. When their civil power isn’t adequate ·for the task of suppressing rival churches·, they can bear most patiently and harmlessly the otherwise frightening epidemic of idolatry, superstition, and heresy in their neighbourhood. They don’t freely and vigorously •argue against errors that are in favour with the magistracy. Yet the only way to propagate truth is through reasoning and •argument, combined with gentleness and benevolence.

In short: no individual or church or commonwealth has a right to attack the civil rights and worldly goods of anyone on pretence of religion. If you disagree, think about what a pernicious a seed of discord and war, what a powerful provocation to endless hatreds, rapines, and slaughters you—·or anyway your opinion·—is offering to mankind. No peace and security among mankind—let alone common friendship—can ever exist as long as people think that governments get their authority from God and that religion is to be propagated by force of arms.

·BETWEEN CLERICS AND OTHERS·
Let us see what the duty of toleration requires from those who are distinguished from the rest of mankind (‘the laity’, as they like to call us) by some ecclesiastical character and

8

Toleration John Locke 4: The limits on toleration

office—bishops, priests, presbyters, ministers, and so on. This isn’t the place to explore the origins of the clergy’s power and dignity. I’ll just say this: wherever their authority comes from, its source is ecclesiastical; so it should be kept within the bounds of the Church and not extended to civil affairs, because the Church is absolutely separate and distinct from the commonwealth. The boundaries of each are settled and immovable. •Mixing together these two societies which are utterly distinct in

•how they originated,

•what they are for, and

•what they do

is tantamount to jumbling together heaven and earth—and two things can’t be more distinct than those! So no church official, whatever his rank may be, can deprive another man of liberty or of any part of his worldly goods on the grounds that there is a religious difference between them. What isn’t lawful for the whole Church can’t be lawful for any of its members.

It’s not enough for an ecclesiastic to abstain from violence, plunder and all sorts of persecution. Someone who claims to be a successor of the apostles, and takes on the role of teacher, ought to impress on his hearers the duties of peace and goodwill towards all men, heretical and orthodox.... He should urge all his flock—private persons and any magistrates there may be there—to charity, meekness, and toleration, and try to cool down all the heat and unreasonable hostility towards dissenters that a man may be led into •by his own fiery zeal for his own sect or •by the crafty manipulations of others. I won’t go into details about how—and how much—Church and state would profit if pulpits everywhere proclaimed this doctrine of peace and toleration; if I did, I might seem to be coming down too hard on men whose dignity I don’t want to be diminished by myself or anyone else. I’ll just say that that is how it ought to be; and if anyone purporting to be a minister of God’s word and a preacher of the gospel of peace teaches otherwise, either he doesn’t understand his duties or he neglects them, and ·either way· he will be answerable to the Prince of peace for this. If Christians are to be told—·and they certainly are·—not to retaliate even if someone inflicts on them ‘seventy times seven’ injuries [Matthew 18:22], how could it be right for them to ‘retaliate’ against people who haven’t done them any harm? I mean people who are merely minding their own business, and merely want—whatever common opinion may think—to worship God in a way that they think is acceptable to Him and to cling to the religion that gives them their best chance of eternal salvation. In issues of bodily health in private life, everyone suits his own convenience, and follows the course that he likes best. No-one complains that his neighbour is managing his affairs badly. No-one is angry with someone else for an error committed in sowing his crops or choosing a husband for his daughter. No-one scolds a spendthrift for wasting his money on drink.... But if any man •doesn’t regularly go to church, or •doesn’t, in church, exactly follow the established ceremonies, or •doesn’t bring his children to be initiated in the rites of some church or other, this immediately causes an uproar. Everyone is ready to avenge this great crime, and the zealots can hardly restrain themselves from punishing the man in advance of his being formally tried and convicted and then condemned to the loss of liberty, goods, or life. If only the ecclesiastical orators in all the sects would put their energies into •arguments that would correct the errors of dissidents rather than into •punishing the dissenters themselves. They shouldn’t make up for their lack of reasons by using the instruments of force, which are unseemly in a Churchman’s hands. They shouldn’t reinforce their eloquence or learning

9

Toleration John Locke 5: The magistrate’s role

with an appeal to the magistrate’s authority; if they do, they’ll create a suspicion that despite their front as lovers of the truth they are really using fire and sword in the pursuit of worldly dominance. It won’t be easy to convince intelligent men that that someone who—dry-eyed and content with himself—delivers his brother to the executioner to be burned to death is acting purely from a strong desire to save that brother from the flames of hell in the world to come.

5: The magistrate’s role in all this

Let us now consider magistrate’s role in this matter of toleration; it is certainly a big one.

I have shown that the care of souls is not the magistrate’s business,....which consists in prescribing laws and enforcing them through a penal system; whereas charitable care, which consists in teaching, warning and persuading, is something that any man is free to do. [Locke writes that sentence with two made-up-Latin words authoritativa and charitativa—as it were ‘authoritocracy’ and ‘charitocracy’. Neither word occurs again in this work.] So the responsibility for each man’s soul is his; it is to be left to him. You say: ‘What if he neglects the care of his soul?’ Well, what if he neglects the care of his health? or of his estate? They are nearer to the magistrate’s jurisdiction than the man’s soul is; so is it all right for the magistrate to set up a law explicitly forbidding people to become poor or sick? Laws try to secure that a person’s goods and health are not harmed by fraud or violence on the part of others; but they don’t try to secure them against negligence bad management by the person himself.... •Suppose a prince wanted to force his subjects to accumulate riches: is he to make a law requiring them to become merchants or musicians? Or to force everyone to become a shopkeeper or metal-worker, because some people thrive and grow rich in these occupations? •Or suppose he wants to make his subjects preserve the health and strength of their bodies. Will he forbid them by law to consult any but •Roman physicians and require them to live according to •their prescriptions? No medicine or chicken soup that wasn’t prepared in the Vatican or in a Geneva shop—really?

You say: ‘There are a thousand ways to wealth, but only one way to heaven.’ Well said! And especially by people who want to force men to take this or that way; for if there were several ways to heaven, there would be no shadow of a case to be made for compulsion.

Well, now: suppose that I am marching vigorously along the road which, according to the sacred geography, leads straight to Jerusalem; why do people beat and harass me? ·They say that it is· because

•I am wearing the wrong kind of boots; or

•my hair isn’t cut in the right way; or

•I haven’t been washed clean [= ‘baptised’]; or

•I eat meat as I walk (or some other food that I eat for the sake of my stomach); or

10

Toleration John Locke 5: The magistrate’s role

•I avoid certain detours that seem to me to lead to brambles or precipices; or

•I choose, amongst several paths leading the same way, the one that looks straightest and cleanest; or

•I avoid the company of travellers who are more jolly than they ought to be; or

•I avoid the company of travellers who are more gloomy than they ought to be; or

•I follow a guide who is clothed in white or crowned with a mitre; or

•I follow a guide who is not clothed in white or is not crowned with a mitre.

Only superstition or hypocrisy could connect •such frivolities with religion or the salvation of souls; but if we think straight about the matter we’ll see that •they are the sorts of things that make enemies of Christian brethren who agree on the substantial and truly fundamental part of religion.

Suppose we grant to these zealots who condemn all dissent from their ways of doing things that these differences of detail—·what I have listed as ‘frivolities’·—lead people to follow different roads. What use can we make of that? Only one road truly leads to eternal happiness—but which one? We aren’t sure! I can studiously search for my own answer to this; and that will give me as good a chance of finding the way to heaven as I could get by letting the question be answered by the laws of the land. ·Suppose that· I have a weak body, sunk under a wasting disease for which (I think) there is one only remedy, but I don’t know what it is. Should the magistrate prescribe a remedy for me, just because there’s only one and we don’t know what it is? If there is only one way for me to escape death, does that make it safe for me to do whatever the magistrate ordains? These are things that everyone ought to inquire into for himself, earnestly and thoughtfully trying to get the answers by his own endeavours, not treating this knowledge as the special possession of some kind of men. Monarchs are born with more power than other men, but in nature they are equal. The right to rule, and practised skill in ruling, don’t bring with them secure knowledge of other things, least of all of true religion.... But suppose that •the way to eternal life probably is better known by a monarch than by his subjects, or at least that •in the prevailing uncertainty we’ll do best by obeying his dictates. You say: ‘If he ordered you to earn your living as a merchant, would you beg off because you doubted if you could succeed in that trade?’ I answer: I would become a merchant on the monarch’s command, because if I failed at that he is well able to make up for my loss in some other way. If he really does (as he says) want me to thrive and grow rich, he can set me up again when unsuccessful ·trading· voyages have broken me. But that’s not how things stand with the life to come. If I take the wrong road with regard to that, I am undone, and the magistrate can’t repair my loss or ease my suffering.... What security can be given for the kingdom of Heaven?

You may say: ‘The secure judgment about the affairs of religion comes not from the civil magistrate but from the Church. What the civil magistrate does is to order us to follow the Church’s decisions in our actions and our beliefs—to ensure by his authority that no-one acts or believes in the business of religion otherwise than the Church teaches. The Church is the source of judgment about religious matters, and the magistrate makes obedience to the Church’s judgments a matter of law which everyone—the magistrate included—is required to obey.’ I reply: Anyone can see that the label ‘the Church’, which was venerable in the time of the apostles, has often been used in more recent times to throw dust in people’s eyes. In our present context, it does nothing for us. The one narrow road to heaven isn’t

11

Toleration John Locke 5: The magistrate’s role

better known to the magistrate than to private persons; so I can’t safely be guided by him, who probably knows as little about the way to heaven as I do, and who certainly isn’t as concerned for my salvation as I am. Ever so many kings of the Jews led the blindly following Israelites into idolatry and thereby into destruction. [Re ‘king’ and ‘magistrate’, see note on page 3.] Yet you tell me to cheer up and accept that everything is now safe and secure, because what the magistrate is enforcing are not his religious decrees but those of the Church! Of what church? Certainly the one he likes best. ‘He who compels me by laws and penalties to join some church isn’t bringing his own judgment into this’—a likely story! What’s the difference between his leading me himself and his delivering me over to be led by others? I depend on his will either way; he determines my eternal state either way.... If the religion of any church becomes true and saving because it is lavishly praised by its own prelates and priests and hangers-on, what religion will ever be regarded as erroneous, false, and destructive? I am doubtful concerning the doctrine of the Socinians; I am suspicious of both the Papist and Lutheran forms of worship; will it be ever safer for me to join one of those churches on the magistrate’s command, because in religion his commands are all based on the authority and advice of the doctors of that church?

The fact is that a church (if a convention of clergymen making decrees must be called by that name) is usually more apt to be influenced by the ·royal· court than the court is to be influenced by a church. How the church fared under orthodox and Arian emperors is very well known. And if you want something more recent, look to the recent English examples of Henry VIII, Edward VI, Mary, and Elizabeth: see how easily and smoothly the clergy adapted their decrees—-articles of faith, form of worship, everything—to the inclinations of those kings and queens. But those kings and queens had such different views in religion, and ordered such different religious conduct, that no sane man (I almost said ‘except an atheist’) will say that a sincere and upright worshipper of God could—without offence to his conscience or his veneration for God—obey all of them. What more is there to say? A king lays down the law for another man’s religion on the basis of •his own judgment or •the ecclesiastical authority and advice of others—it’s the same thing!....

But the crucial point that absolutely settles this controversy is this: even if the magistrate’s opinion in religion is sound, and the road he tells me to follow really is the one endorsed by the Gospel, if I am not thoroughly convinced of that in my own mind I won’t reach salvation by following it. No road that I travel along against the dictates of my conscience will ever bring me to the home of the blessed. I can grow rich by the use of skills that give me no pleasure; I can be cured of a disease by remedies that I have no faith in; but I can’t be saved by a religion that I distrust or a worship that I dislike. It’s pointless for an unbeliever to put on a performance; what God cares about is faith and inner sincerity.... Amid all the aspects of religion that may be doubtful, one thing is certain: a religion that I don’t believe to be true can’t be true for me or useful for me....

12

Toleration John Locke 6: Church and state: forms of worship

6: Church and state: forms of worship

Now that we have freed men from in any way dominating one another in matters of religion, what are they now to do? Everyone knows and acknowledges that God ought to be publicly worshipped; otherwise why the pressure to attend ·religious· assemblies? So men....should enter into a religious society in which they meet

•to instruct and improve one another,

•to declare to the world that they worship God and offer him such service as they aren’t ashamed of and as they think worthy of Him and acceptable to Him,

•by the purity of doctrine, holiness of life, and decent form of worship to draw others to the love of the true religion, and

•to perform other religious things that can’t be done by each private man on his own.

I call religious societies churches. The magistrate, I say, ought to tolerate them, because what they are doing is something that it is lawful for any individual to do, namely to take care of the salvation of his soul. And this holds equally for a national church and for independent congregations.

There are two main aspects to any church—(1) outward form and rites of worship and (2) doctrines; and these must be dealt with separately if the whole matter of toleration is to be clearly understood. ·(1) will be the topic of this chapter and the next; (2) will be taken up in chapter 8 on page 17·.

(1a) The magistrate has no power to enforce by civil law—in any church, even his own—the use of any rites or ceremonies in the worship of God; not only because these churches are free societies, but also because no form of divine worship is justifiable unless those who practise it think it is acceptable to God. Anything that is not done in good faith is wrong in itself and not acceptable to God. It is self-contradictory to •allow a religion the purpose of which is to please God and •command its members to behave in ways that will displease God.

[The rest of this chapter says a lot about ‘things that are indifferent’ (Latin indifferens). The term has a very general meaning of ‘neither to one side or the other’ of some polarity. In our present context res indifferentes apparently has to mean ‘actions that aren’t in themselves either morally required or morally forbidden. But then why should Locke and his imagined critic both imply that perhaps the civil law can only concern actions that are ‘indifferent’? The preparer of this version has no suggestions to offer.]

You say: ‘Are you denying that the magistrate has any power regarding indifferent things? If he isn’t allowed that, there is nothing for law-making to do.’ No, I readily grant that indifferent things, and perhaps only they, are subject to legislative power. But it doesn’t follow that with respect to something indifferent the magistrate may ordain anything he likes. The rule and standard for all law-making is the public good. If something isn’t useful to the commonwealth then it may not be required by law, however indifferent it is.

(b) Also, things that are utterly indifferent in their own nature are taken out of the magistrate’s reach when they are brought into a church and used in the worship of God, because in that use they have nothing to do with civil affairs. The church’s only concern is the salvation of souls, and it is none of the commonwealth’s business what ceremonies it uses for this purpose. The use or non-use of a ceremony by a religious assembly makes no difference at all to the life, liberty, or estate of any man. [Locke gives an example: a magistrate may require the washing of children because

13

Toleration John Locke 6: Church and state: forms of worship

he thinks it helps to prevent disease, but it doesn’t follow from this that he is entitled to require churches to baptise children. Then he adapts the baptism example to a different slant on the argument:] Let us apply the last case to the child of a Jew, and the thing speaks for itself. A Christian magistrate may well have subjects who are Jews; if we accept that it’s wrong to harm a Jew by compelling him against his conscience to do in his religion something that is in its nature indifferent, how can it be all right to do this to a Christian?

(c) Things that are in their own nature indifferent can’t by any human authority be made any part of the worship of God. Why not? Precisely because they are indifferent! Indifferent things don’t have in themselves any power to propitiate the Deity, so no human power or authority can give them enough dignity and excellency to be able to do that. In the common affairs of life the use of indifferent things that God hasn’t forbidden is free and lawful, and therefore in those things human authority has a place. But it’s not like that with religion. Indifferent things are lawful in the worship of God only if God Himself has instituted them and by some positive command ordered that they be a part of the worship that he will accept from poor sinful men. And when God angrily asks us ‘Who required this?’, He won’t be satisfied with the answer ‘The magistrate commanded it’! If civil jurisdiction goes that far, what can’t be lawfully be introduced into religion? What hodgepodge of ceremonies, what superstitious inventions, might not be imposed on worshippers against their consciences but on the magistrate’s authority? For most of these ceremonies and superstitions would consist in the religious use of things that are in their own nature indifferent; there’s nothing wrong with them except that God isn’t their author. The sprinkling of water and the use of bread and wine are, in their own nature and in everyday life, entirely indifferent; could they have been introduced into religion and made a part of divine worship except by divine institution? If any human authority or civil power could have done this, couldn’t it also command the eating of fish and drinking of ale in the holy banquet as a part of divine worship? Why not the sprinkling of animals’ blood, purifications by water or fire, and countless other such things? Although these things are indifferent in common uses, when they are brought into divine worship without divine authority they are as abominable to God as the sacrifice of a dog.... So indifferent things are under the power of the civil magistrate, but that doesn’t allow them to be imposed on religious assemblies, because in the worship of God they cease to be indifferent....

You say: ‘If no aspect of divine worship is to be left to human discretion, how is it that churches themselves have the power to order when and where etc. worship is to be conducted?’ My answer to that involves distinguishing •the parts of worship from •the circumstances of worship. Something is a part of the worship if it is believed to be appointed by God and to be pleasing to Him, which makes it necessary. Circumstances are not in this way necessary. Of course worship must occur at some time in some place; but which time and place is left open, so they are indifferent.... ·Note that the part/circumstance distinction depends on what is believed to be pleasing to God·. For example: among the Jews the time and place of worship and the clothing of those who officiated in it were not mere circumstances, but a part of the worship itself; if any of those were varied in any way, they had—·they thought·—no chance of its being acceptable to God; whereas to Christians....these are mere circumstances of worship which each church can vary as it sees fit. [Locke adds a qualification: the institution of the sabbath as a day to be set apart for worship is a part and not a circumstance of Christian worship.]

14

Toleration John Locke 7: Idolatry

(d) Just as the magistrate has no power to •impose by his laws the use of any rites and ceremonies in any church, so also he has no power to •forbid the use of any rites and ceremonies that are already accepted, approved, and practised by a church; because doing that would destroy the church itself as an institution whose sole purpose is to worship God freely in its own way.

You say: ‘So if some congregations chose to •sacrifice infants, or (as the primitive Christians were falsely accused) •to engage in promiscuous sexual intercourse, or •to do any other such dreadful thing, the magistrate would be obliged to tolerate these actions because they are committed in a religious assembly?’ I answer: those things are not lawful in everyday life or in private homes, so they aren’t lawful in the worship of God either. But if people who had gathered for religious purposes wanted to sacrifice a calf, I deny that that should be prohibited by a law. The calf’s owner can lawfully kill his calf at home and burn any part of it he likes; for this does no harm to anyone; and for the same reason he may kill his calf also in a religious meeting. Whether doing this is pleasing to God is for the calf-killers to think about. The magistrate’s only role is to ensure that the commonwealth isn’t harmed and that no individual suffers personal or financial harm. If the interests of the commonwealth required all slaughter of beasts to be suspended for a while, so as to rebuild stocks that had been destroyed by some extraordinary epidemic, it’s obvious that in that case the magistrate can forbid all his subjects to kill any calves for any purpose. But that law would be made about a political matter, not a religious one; what it prohibits is not •sacrificing calves but •killing them.

This shows us how a church differs from the commonwealth. Something that is lawful in the commonwealth can’t be prohibited by the magistrate in the church.... If any man can lawfully take bread or wine....in his own house, the law oughtn’t to deprive him of that same liberty in his religious worship; though in the church the use of bread and wine is very different because there it is applied to the mysteries of faith and rites of Divine worship. But things that are forbidden by law because in their ordinary use they are harmful to the public ought not to be permitted to churches in their sacred rites. But the magistrate should be very careful not to misuse his authority by oppressing some church, on the pretext of securing the public good.

7: Idolatry

You say: ‘What if a church is idolatrous—is that also to be tolerated by the magistrate?’ I answer: What power could the magistrate have to suppress an •idolatrous church that couldn’t somewhere somewhen be used to ruin an •orthodox one? Don’t forget that the civil power is the same everywhere, and that the religion of every monarch is orthodox to him. If the civil magistrate in Geneva, for instance, is given a power that would enable him to wipe out by violence and

15

Toleration John Locke 7: Idolatry

blood the religion [he means the Roman Catholic church] that is there wrongly regarded as idolatrous, by the same rule another magistrate, in some neighbouring country, may oppress the orthodox religion [he means the Reformed Church centred in Geneva], and in India the magistrate may oppress the Christian religion. Either the civil power can change •everything in religion, according to the monarch’s pleasure, or it can change •nothing. If it is once allowed to use laws and penalties to introduce •something into religion, there will be no way of setting limits ·to such interference·: it will be lawful to alter anything according to the rule of truth—i.e. what the magistrate fancies to be the truth. So no man is to be deprived, on account of his religion, of anything that he values. Not even ·native· Americans, who are subjects of a Christian monarch, are to be punished in any way for not accepting our faith and worship. If they think that by observing the rites of their own country they are pleasing God and securing happiness, we should leave this to God and to them.

I’ll tell you how this situation came about, starting at the beginning. A small weak group of Christians with no possessions arrive in a pagan country; they beg the inhabitants—appealing to their common humanity—to help them with the necessities of life; those necessities are supplied, habitations are granted, and Christians and pagans come together as one body of people. The Christian religion takes root in that country, and spreads, but isn’t yet stronger ·than the pagan religion·. At that time peace, friendship, faith, and equal justice are preserved amongst them. After a while the Christian party does become more powerful ·than the other·, because the magistrate becomes a Christian. Then immediately all compacts are to be broken and all civil rights violated, so that idolatry may be wiped out; and unless these innocent pagans—

•strict observers of the rules of equity and the law of nature, who

•in no way offend against the laws of the society—

give up their ancient religion and accept a new and strange one, they are to be turned out of the lands and possessions of their forefathers and perhaps deprived of life itself. And so we see •what can be done by zeal for the church combined with the desire for control, and •how easily greed, theft and ambition are cloaked in the pretext of religion and of the care of souls.

If you think that idolatry should be rooted out by laws, punishments, fire, and sword, the above story applies to you, with only the names changed. Neither pagans in America or dissenting Christians here in Europe can rightly be deprived of their worldly goods on religious grounds.

You say: ‘But idolatry shouldn’t be tolerated, because it is a sin.’ If you said ‘Idolatry should be avoided, because it is a sin’, that would be right. But its being a sin doesn’t imply that it should be punished by the magistrate. It’s not for the magistrate to wield his sword in punishing everything that he thinks is a sin against God. Covetousness, uncharitableness, idleness, and many other things are generally agreed to be sins, but no-one has ever said that they should be punished by the magistrate. That is because they don’t interfere with other people’s rights, and don’t disturb the public peace. Even the sins of lying and perjury are nowhere punishable by laws, except in special cases; and even in those the operative feature is not •the behaviour’s real wickedness or its offence against God but rather •the injury done to the offender’s neighbours and to the commonwealth. And what if in another country a Moslem or a pagan monarch sees the Christian religion as false and offensive to God; is it all right for him to wipe out the Christians for that reason and in that way?

16

Toleration John Locke 8: Church and state: articles of faith

You say: ‘By the law of Moses, idolaters were to be rooted out.’ True; but the law of Moses is not obligatory to us Christians. Nobody claims that everything generally enjoined by the law of Moses ought to be practised by Christians.... A promulgated law is binding only on those to whom it is given. ‘Hear, O Israel’ sufficiently limits the obligations of the law of Moses to that people. This is answer enough to those who urge the authority of the law of Moses for inflicting capital punishment on idolaters. But I will go into this matter in a bit more detail.

[Locke completes this chapter with a couple of pages of biblical scholarship, making two points. (a) The Jewish commonwealth to which the laws of Moses were issued was an absolute theocracy, in which the magistrate—the chief legislator—was God. So there was there no distinction between religious law and civil law; there could be capital punishment for religious offences because the latter were also civil offences. This doesn’t hold for any Christian commonwealth. (b) The Mosaic law against idolatry was aimed only at Israelites, Locke says: ‘In the very place where it is ordered that an Israelite idolater should be put to death it is provided that foreigners should not be oppressed (Exodus 22:20,21).’ He goes through some further historical ins and outs, which don’t contribute to the general discussion of toleration. Then:]

So much for (1) outward worship. Let us now turn to (2) faith. [See the numbering of items on page 13.]

8: Church and state: articles of faith

[The next paragraph speaks of ‘practical’ and ‘speculative’ doctrines. Here ‘practical’ = ‘having to do with morality’, and ‘speculative’ = ‘having to do with non-moral matters of fact’. We can’t say ‘speculative’ = ‘factual’ because, as you’ll see in a moment, Locke holds that there are moral facts, i.e. that practical propositions are true. In (4) on page 21 Locke smudges the speculative/practical line by implying that ‘There is no God’ is a practical proposition.]

(2) Some religious doctrines are practical and some speculative. Both consist in the knowledge of truth, but ·they differ in how they relate to the human condition·: speculative propositions terminate simply in the understanding, while practical ones relate to the will and to conduct.

·SPECULATIVE ARTICLES OF FAITH·
So speculative opinions—so-called articles of faith—can’t be imposed on any church by the law of the land. Why not? Because •they are matters of belief; •what we believe doesn’t depend on our will; and •a law requiring people to do something they can’t do would be absurd. But I’ve said enough about this already. ‘Well, let men at least say that they believe’—i.e. save their souls by lying to men and to God. What a lovely religion that is! The only reason the magistrate could have for imposing such a law is that he thinks this is a way to save men’s souls; but if that is what he thinks, he shows how little he understands the road to salvation.

17

Toleration John Locke 8: Church and state: articles of faith

Another reason why the magistrate oughtn’t to forbid the professing or teaching of any speculative opinions in any church is that such opinions haven’t the slightest relevance to the civil rights of the subjects. If a Roman Catholic believes that something that another man calls bread is really the body of Christ, this isn’t harming the other man. If a Jew believes that the New Testament is not the word of God, this belief has no effect on anyone’s civil rights. If a pagan has that belief about both Testaments, that shouldn’t expose him to punishment as a pernicious citizen, because it makes no difference to the magistrate’s power or the people’s welfare. I readily grant that these opinions are false and absurd; but the ·civil· law is concerned not with •the truth of opinions but with •the safety and security of the commonwealth and with each individual’s goods and person. And there’s nothing wrong with that. The truth will do well enough if it is left to its own devices.... It isn’t taught by laws, and has no need of force to get an entrance into men’s minds—unlike errors, which profit from outside help!.... So much for •speculative opinions; now let us turn to •practical ones.

·PRACTICAL ARTICLES OF FAITH·
·Whereas speculative religious opinions have nothing to do with the civil law, the same is not true of speculative religious opinions·. Living well—by which I mean living in a way that is morally good—is a considerable part of religion and true piety and is also the business of the civil government; it is crucial to the safety of men’s souls and of the commonwealth. So moral actions belong to the jurisdiction of both

•the outward and inward courts;

•the civil and domestic governors;

•the magistrate and the conscience.

So we have to be on guard lest one of these jurisdictions infringes on the other, creating discord between the keeper of the public peace and the overseer of the soul. But there won’t be any difficulty about this if we remember what I have said about the limits of these two governments.

Every man has an immortal soul that is capable of eternal happiness or misery. Its happiness depends on his believing and doing the things that he needs to believe and do if he is to obtain God’s favour—the things that are prescribed by God for that purpose. Two things follow from this. (1) Having these beliefs and performing these actions are mankind’s chief obligations, and we should work as hard and carefully as we can to find out what they are and to perform them, because nothing in this world outweighs ·what is at stake in· eternity—there’s just no comparison. (2) Because one man doesn’t violate the rights of another by his false beliefs and improper manner of worship, and one man’s perdition does no harm to another man’s affairs, the care of each man’s salvation belongs only to himself. I don’t mean this to condemn all charitable warnings and attempts to steer men away from error, which are indeed a Christian’s greatest duty. Anyone may try to promote another man’s salvation by using as many urgings and arguments as he pleases, but not by any use of force and compulsion, any attempt to dominate. In these matters, no-one is obliged obey someone else’s warnings or advice further than he himself is convinced....

But besides his immortal soul, a man also has his temporal life here on earth; this is fragile and of uncertain duration, and therefore he needs support for it that he can’t get and keep without working hard: the things we need if we are to live well and cheerfully are not spontaneously produced by nature, so that’s something else we have to work at ·in addition to the things that bear on the salvation of our souls·. But men are so dishonest that most of them would rather steal the products of other men’s labours than take the trouble to provide for themselves; so there is a need for some way of •letting men keep what they have

18

Toleration John Locke 9: Individual conscience

acquired through honest work, and also of •preserving their liberty and strength so that they can continue such work; and this has required men to enter into society with one another so that by mutual assistance and joint force they may make each of them secure in his possession of the things that contribute to comfort and happiness in this life—while leaving to each man the care of his own eternal happiness. [Locke adds that civil societies are formed also for defence against attacks from outside, and explains that all of this works only if there is ‘the magistrate’ who has power to punish. This account of society, he says, explains how magistracy began, what it is used for, and what its limits are; he repeats that in all of this there is nothing about beliefs or actions that are needed for the salvation of souls; and he sums up:]

With regard to eternal salvation, everyone should do what he in his conscience thinks is acceptable to the Almighty, on whose good pleasure and acceptance depends his eternal happiness. Obedience is due first to God and then to the laws ·of the land·.

9: Individual conscience

But you say: ‘What if the magistrate officially commands something that seems to the conscience of some private person to be wrong?’ I answer: if government is faithfully administered and the magistrate really is concerned for the public good, this won’t often happen. But if it ever does happen, I say, that such a private person should refuse to perform the action that his conscience condemns, and should submit to the punishment for this if it isn’t morally wrong for him to undergo it. When a law intended for the public good is privately judged by someone to be wicked, that doesn’t invalidate the law or create an excuse. But if the law really does concern things that lie outside the magistrate’s authority (e.g. commanding people to accept a strange religion....), then men are not obliged to obey that law against their consciences. Political society is instituted purely to secure each man’s possession of the things of this life. Each man’s soul and other heavenly matters don’t belong to the commonwealth and can’t be subjected to it; they are left entirely to the man himself....

But you say: ‘What if the magistrate believes that some law about those matters is for the public good?’ I answer: Just as the private erroneous judgment of any particular person doesn’t exempt him obeying the law, so also the private judgment (for that’s what it is) of the magistrate doesn’t give him any new right of imposing laws on his subjects—a right that wasn’t conferred on him in the constitution of the government, and wasn’t ever in the power of the people to grant—and this holds with extra strength if the magistrate is trying to enrich and advance his followers and co-religionists with goods stolen from others. Another question: ‘What if the magistrate believes that he has a right to make such laws and that they are for the public good, and

19

Toleration John Locke 10. What should not be tolerated

his subjects believe the contrary? Who shall judge between them?’ I answer: ‘God alone—there’s no earthly judge to decide between the supreme ·earthly· magistrate and the people. On the last day—·the Day of Judgment·—God will treat everyone according to his deserts, i.e. according to his sincerity and uprightness in trying to promote piety, and the public welfare and peace of mankind’. You say: ‘What’s to be done in the meantime?’ I answer: ‘Each person’s chief concern should be for his own soul, and after that for public peace; though there aren’t many people who, viewing the wilderness of the contemporary world, will think they are looking at peace. [Locke is here echoing a famous line by the historian Tacitus, who imagines a British warrior saying about the Romans Ubi solitudinem faciunt, pacem apellant—where they create a wilderness they call it ‘peace’.]

There are two sorts of contests amongst men, one managed by law and the other by force; and their nature is such that whenever law stops, force begins. But the magistrate’s power in the various different kinds of nations is not part of my present concern. I only know what usually happens when controversies arise without a judge to settle them. You say: ‘So the magistrate, being the stronger, will prevail.’ No doubt you right; but our present question concerns what ought to happen, not what probably will happen.

10. What should not be tolerated

To get down to details now, I have four main things to say.

(1) The magistrate should not tolerate any doctrines that are contrary to human society or to the moral rules that are needed for civil society to survive. But there are very few such doctrines in any church; because it would be hard for a sect to become so lunatic as to teach, as a matter of religious doctrine, things that clearly undermine the foundations of society and are therefore condemned by the judgment of all mankind; because that would endanger their own interests, their peace, their reputation, everything.

(2) An evil that is less visible but more dangerous to the commonwealth occurs when men claim for themselves and their co-religionists some special prerogative that does in fact conflict with the civil right of the community but is covered over with a glittery show of deceitful words. For example: no sect teaches explicitly and openly

(a) that men aren’t obliged to keep their promises;

(b) that monarchs may be dethroned by those who differ from them in religion; or

(c) that they alone have dominion of all things.

For if these were proposed thus nakedly and plainly, they would soon attract the attention of the magistrate and arouse the commonwealth to be on its guard against the spreading of such a dangerous evil. Yet these things are said, though in other words. (a) Those who teach that promises to heretics needn’t be kept mean that the privilege of breaking promises belongs only to themselves, because they do—or easily could when they found it convenient—declare that

20

Toleration John Locke 10. What should not be tolerated

everyone who doesn’t belong to their sect is a heretic. (b) What can they mean when they say that kings who are excommunicated forfeit their crowns and kingdoms? They are obviously claiming for themselves the power to depose kings, because they claim that their hierarchy has the sole right to excommunicate anyone. (c) Those who maintain that dominion is founded in grace are in effect claiming the possession of all things; for they....believe themselves to be the truly pious and faithful. People like these—

who attribute to those who are faithful, religious, and orthodox—i.e. to themselves—any special privilege or power in civil matters; or who on pretence of religion claim any sort of authority over people who aren’t members of their ecclesiastical communion

—have no right to be tolerated by the magistrate. Nor do those who refuse to accept and teach the duty of tolerating all men in matters of religion. What doctrines like these signify is that these people are ready on any occasion to seize the government and take possession of the estates and fortunes of their fellow subjects, and that all they want from the magistrate is to be tolerated until they have enough power to carry this out.

(3) A church can’t have any right to be tolerated by the magistrate if it is constituted on a basis such that anyone who joins it is thereby giving himself over to the protection and service of a different monarch. For this would establish a foreign jurisdiction in his own country; the magistrate would be allowing enemy soldiers to be enlisted from among his own people.

[If you aren’t to be needlessly puzzled by what comes next, you need to know that Locke is thinking of a situation in which the magistrate allows a church whose members owe allegiance to a foreign power because he himself belongs to such a church. This was written in 1685, when the Roman Catholic James II was on the English throne, and there were fears that he might bring into England some of France’s notably brutal ways of suppressing Protestants. This text was first published in 1689, the year after James II was bloodlessly driven into exile.]

The frivolous and fallacious distinction between the Court and the church is no help here [He must mean that that distinction would be frivolous if... etc.], especially when both Court and church are equally subject to the absolute authority of the same person, who not only has power to persuade the members of his church to do whatever he likes—either as purely religious, or as contributing to the good of religion—but can also order them to do it on pain of eternal fire. It would be absurd for anyone to claim to be a Moslem only in his religion and in everything else a faithful subject of a Christian magistrate, if he admits that he is bound to give blind obedience to the Mufti of Constantinople, who himself •is entirely obedient to the Ottoman Emperor and •invents the ‘oracles’ of that religion to suit himself. And this Moslem living among Christians would renounce their government even more openly if he acknowledged the supreme magistrate in the state to be also the head of his church.

(4) No-one should be tolerated who denies the existence of God. Promises, covenants, and oaths, which are the bonds of human society, can have no hold on an atheist: this all dissolves in the presence of the thought that there is no God. And atheists can’t claim on religious grounds that they should be tolerated! As for other practical opinions, including ones that have some error in them, there’s no reason why they shouldn’t be tolerated as long as they don’t tend to establish domination over others or claim civil impunity for the church in which they are taught,

21

Toleration John Locke 11: Gatherings

11: Gatherings

It remains for me to say something about the assemblies that are thought to present a challenge to this doctrine of toleration because they commonly are thought to be hotbeds of sedition and dissent. Perhaps some of them have been—not because of anything special about assemblies as such but rather because of special features of those assemblies in particular, e.g. troubles relating to oppression and lack of freedom. These accusations would stop if the law of toleration were so settled that all churches had to •declare toleration as the basis for their own liberty, and •teach that....nobody ought to be compelled in matters of religion either by law or force. Establishing this one thing would take away the basis for all the anger and disturbances on grounds of conscience, leaving these assemblies as calm and peaceful as any other gatherings. But let us look in more detail into the accusations against assemblies.

You say: ‘Assemblies and meetings endanger the public peace and threaten the commonwealth.’ I answer: If that is right, then why are there so many meetings every day in markets and law-courts and town squares?

You say: ‘Those are civil assemblies. What I am objecting to are ecclesiastical ones.’ I answer: You seem to think that assemblies that are altogether remote from civil affairs are the ones that are most apt to make trouble for them!

You say: ‘The members of civil assemblies differ from one another in matters of religion, whereas these ecclesiastical meetings are groups of people who all have the same ·religious· opinion.’ I reply: Do you really think that agreement in matters of religion amounts to a conspiracy against the commonwealth? or that denying men the freedom to assemble would make them less likely to agree in religious matters?

You say: ‘Civil assemblies are open and free for anyone to enter into, whereas religious gatherings provide a better setting for the hatching of secret plots.’ I reply: On the contrary, many civil assemblies are not open to everyone, e.g. meetings of guilds and the like. And if some religious meetings are private, whose fault is that? those who want them to be public or those who forbid it?

You say: ‘Religious togetherness brings men’s minds extremely close together, which is a reason to fear them.’ I reply: Then why isn’t the magistrate afraid of his own church? why doesn’t he forbid their assemblies as things dangerous to his government?

You say: ‘Because he himself is a part of them, the head of them.’ I reply: You seem to forget that he is also a part of the commonwealth, and the head of the whole people!

This is how things stand. The magistrate is afraid of other churches, but not of his own, because he is kind and favourable to his church but severe and harsh toward the others. He is indulgent towards his coreligionists, allowing them almost any liberty; members of other churches he uses as slaves and, however blamelessly they live, he rewards them with galleys, prisons, confiscations, and death. He cherishes and defends the members of his own church and continually scourges and oppresses the members of the others. Let the tables be turned; or let those dissenters merely enjoy the same privileges in civil affairs as his other subjects, ·his coreligionists·, and he will quickly find that these religious meetings need not be feared: if men enter into

22

Toleration John Locke 11: Gatherings

seditious conspiracies, they are led to it not by religion in their meetings but their sufferings and oppression. Just and moderate governments are everywhere quiet, everywhere safe; injustice and tyranny are always resisted. I know that seditions are often raised on religious pretexts; but it’s also true that often people are ill-treated and made to live miserably on religious pretexts. Believe me, the troubles that arise don’t come from •any special features of this or that church or religious society, but from •something that all mankind have in common. namely that when they are groaning under a heavy burden they try to get out from under the yoke that hurts their necks.

Try this thought-experiment. Suppose that religion is set aside and that men are classified on the basis of physical features, and that those who have (say) black hair or grey eyes don’t enjoy the same privileges as other citizens; that

•they aren’t allowed to buy or sell, or live by their trades;

•as parents they don’t have control of their children’s education;

•they are all either excluded from the benefit of the laws, or meet with biased judges;

do you doubt that these people—marked off from others by the colour of their hair and eyes, and drawn together by one common persecution—would be as dangerous to the magistrate as any others who had come together on religious grounds? People come together for trade and profit, for idly drinking together, for being with neighbours, for being with coreligionists; but there’s only one thing that brings people together to plan sedition, and that is oppression.

You say: ‘Are you really willing to have people meet for divine service against the magistrate’s will?’ I answer: Why ‘against his will’? Their coming together is lawful and necessary. ‘Against his will’, you say: that’s what I am complaining about; it is the root of all the mischief. Why are assemblies in a church more frowned on that ones is a theatre or a market? Those who meet in a church are not more wicked or more trouble-making than those who meet elsewhere.... Take away the legal discrimination against them, by changing the laws take away the penalties they are subjected to, and everything will become safe and peaceable.... And all the various dissident churches, as guardians of the public peace, will watch one another so that nothing may be changed in the form of the government, because they can hope for nothing better than what they already enjoy—that is, equality with their fellow-subjects under a just and moderate government. [‘magistrate’—‘monarch’—see note on page 3.] Now if the church to which the monarch belongs is regarded as the chief support of any civil government simply because the monarch is kind and the laws are favourable to it, the government will be even more secure when all good subjects, whatever church they belong to, enjoy the same favour of the monarch and the same benefit of the laws, because they will all become the common support and guard of it....

* * * * *

To sum up the position I have been urging: let every man enjoy the same rights as every other. Is it permitted to worship God in the Roman manner? Then let it be permitted to worship in the Geneva form also. Is it permitted to speak Latin in the market-place? Then let those who want to speak it also in the church. Is it lawful for any man in his own house to kneel, stand, sit, or take any other position? to clothe himself in white or black, in short or in long garments? Let it be lawful to eat bread, drink wine, or wash with water in the church. Anything that is left free by law in everyday life situations, let it be free also in divine worship in a church.

23

Toleration John Locke 11: Gatherings

Let no man’s life, or body, or house, or estate, suffer any kind of harm on these accounts....

If anything happens in a religious meeting that is seditious and contrary to the public peace, it should be punished in exactly the same way as if it had happened in a public square. These meetings ought not to be sanctuaries for trouble-makers and rogues.... No-one at such a meeting ought to be blamed for the presence there of a law-breaker. Everyone should be accountable for his own actions, and no man is to be laid under a suspicion or odium for the fault of another: those who are seditious, murderers, thieves, robbers, adulterers, slanderers etc. ought to be punished and suppressed, whatever church they belong to—even if it’s the magistrate’s church. But those whose doctrine is peaceable and whose manners are pure and blameless ought to be on equal terms with their fellow-subjects.

If people of one religious persuasion are allowed to come together for religious ceremonies, celebrations of feast days, listening to speeches and public worship, the same permission should also be given to Arminians, Calvinists, Lutherans, Anabaptists, and Socinians. Let me tell you the truth about this, openly, man to man: neither pagan nor Moslem nor Jew should be shut out from the republic because of his religion. •The gospel commands no such thing. •It isn’t wanted by the Church, which ‘judgeth not those who are without’ (1 Corinthians 5:12). And •it isn’t demanded by the commonwealth, which takes in everyone who is honest, peaceable, and hard-working. Shall we allow a pagan to deal and trade with us yet not allow him to worship God? If we allow Jews to have private houses amongst us, why shouldn’t we permit them to have synagogues? Is their doctrine more false, their worship more abominable, or civil peace more endangered by their meeting in public than in their private houses? But if these things can be granted to Jews and pagans, should any Christians be worse off than they are in a Christian commonwealth?

You say: ‘Yes, they should be, because they are more given to factions, tumults, and civil wars.’ I answer: Is this the fault of the Christian religion? If it is, then the Christian religion is the worst of all religions and oughtn’t to be •professed by you or •tolerated by any commonwealth.... But this isn’t what Christianity is like; it is indeed more strongly opposed to covetousness, ambition, discord, property-disputes etc. than any other religion that has ever existed—and it is the most modest and peaceable. So we must look elsewhere for the cause of the evils that are blamed on religion; and if we think straight about the matter we’ll find that the entire cause has to do with my present topic, ·toleration·. What has produced all the religious quarrels and wars that have occurred in the Christian world is not •the (inevitable) diversity of opinions but rather •the (avoidable) denial of toleration to those who are of different opinions. The •heads of the church, driven by greed and an insatiable hunger for control, have exploited the magistrates’ ambition (often out of control) and the (always stupid) superstition of the multitude, arousing the populace against those who dissent from •themselves, by preaching to them, contrary to the laws of the Gospel and to the precepts of charity, that schismatics and heretics should be deprived of their possessions and wiped out. In this they have mixed together two things that are really utterly different, the church and the commonwealth.

When men are stripped of the goods they have acquired by honest work, industry, and, contrary to all the laws of equity, human and divine, are exposed to other men’s violence and robbery, it is very difficult for them to put up with this patiently. Especially when they are otherwise entirely blameless, and the ‘reason’ for this treatment lies

24

Toleration John Locke 11: Gatherings

right outside the magistrate’s jurisdiction and is a matter for the individual’s conscience and the salvation of his soul, for which he is accountable only to God.

When these men, growing weary of the evils under which they labour, eventually come to think it lawful for them to resist force with force, and to defend their natural rights (which are not forfeitable on account of religion) with arms as well as they can, what else could we expect? To learn that this has in the past been the ordinary course of things, study history; to know that it will continue in the future, think! It is bound to be like that as long as the principle of religious persecution goes on prevailing with the magistrate and the people, and as long as those who ought to preach peace and harmony go on deploying all their skill and strength to arouse men to arms and sound the trumpet of war. It would be astonishing that magistrates should allow these incendiaries and disturbers of the public peace if we couldn’t see that they have been invited by them to a share of the spoils, and have been led to make use of their covetousness and pride as means to increasing their own power. [In that difficult sentence, Locke evidently means that the magistrate allows the disturber to make trouble because the magistrate has been invited by the disturber to share in the spoils of the trouble; so that the disturber is using the magistrate’s greed and pride as a means to the disturber’s increasing his own power. Clearly the disturbers of the peace in question are not •the restless and rebellious oppressed people with which this paragraph began, but •their oppressors—the leaders of the favoured church who disturb the peace by preaching intolerance against other churches.] For who does not see that these good men—·these disturbers of the peace·—are ministers not so much of the gospel as of the government, and that by flattering the ambition and supporting the dominion of monarchs and men in authority they are doing their best to promote in the commonwealth the tyranny that they couldn’t in any other way have established in the church? That’s how church and state come to work together. If each of them would stay within its own bounds—one attending to the worldly welfare of the commonwealth, the other to the salvation of souls—there couldn’t possibly be any discord between them....

I beg God Almighty to bring it about (1) that the gospel of peace comes to be preached; (2) that civil magistrates—trying harder to make their own consciences fit God’s law, and less hard to bind other men’s consciences by human laws—direct all their counsels and endeavours in a fatherly way to promote the worldly good of all their children, except ones who are arrogant, ungovernable, and injurious to their brethren; and (3) that all ecclesiastics who pronounce themselves to be the successors of the Apostles—walking peacefully and modestly in the Apostles’ steps, and not getting mixed in with state affairs—apply themselves wholly to promoting the salvation of souls.

25

Toleration John Locke 12. Heresy and schism

12: Heresy and schism

It may be worthwhile to say a little about heresy and schism. A Moslem isn’t and can’t be either a heretic or a schismatic to a Christian; and if anyone leaves the Christian faith and joins Islam, that doesn’t make him a heretic or a schismatic—it makes him an apostate and an infidel. This is entirely uncontroversial; and it shows that men of different religions can’t be heretics or schismatics ·relative· to one another.

What we have to look into, then, is ·how the concepts of heresy and schism work in relation to· men who are of the same religion. It’s clear those who have the very same rule of faith and worship have the same religion, and those whose faith and worship are different belong to different religions. That is because everything that belongs to that religion is contained in that rule, so that those who have the same rule belong to one and the same religion, and those who haven’t don’t. Thus Moslems and Christians are of different religions because Christians take the Holy Scriptures as the rule of their religion, and Moslems take the Koran. And by that criterion there can be different religions amongst Christians. Papists and Lutherans, though both profess faith in Christ and are therefore called ‘Christians’ are not of the same religion, because Lutherans acknowledge only the Holy Scriptures as the rule and foundation of their religion, while Papists have as their rule not only the Holy Scriptures but also traditions and the decrees of Popes....

·WHAT HERESY IS·
From this it follows •that heresy is a split in ecclesiastical communion between men who have the same religion but differ on some doctrine that isn’t contained in the rule ·that defines the religion·; and •that among those who recognize only the Holy Scriptures as their rule of faith, heresy is a split in their Christian communion concerning doctrines that aren’t explicitly contained in Scripture. This split ·among Christians· can happen in either of two ways.

(1) It happens when the greater part of the church—or the stronger part (thanks to the magistrate’s patronage)—separates itself from the rest, excluding them from the church’s communion because they refuse to declare their belief in certain opinions that aren’t explicitly stated in Scripture. What makes a group heretical is not the smallness of their numbers or the authority of the magistrate; someone is a heretic if (and only if) is it he who on the basis of such opinions divides the church into parts, introduces names and marks of distinction, deliberately creates a split because of those opinions. [Locke is saying, then, that in the situation described at the start of this paragraph it is the bigger or stronger faction that is heretical, not the remainder.]

(2) Heresy occurs when someone separates himself from the communion of a church because the church doesn’t publicly profess certain opinions that the Holy Scriptures don’t clearly teach.

Both these—·the group and the individual·—are heretics because they are wrong about fundamentals, and obstinately go against prudence and knowledge. When they specified that the Holy Scriptures were to be the only foundation of faith, they also gave a fundamental status to certain propositions that are not in Scripture, and because others won’t accept these additional opinions of theirs as necessary and fundamental, they create a split in the church either (2) by withdrawing from it or (1) by expelling others from it. It doesn’t help their position to say that their favoured opinions fit with Scripture and with the analogy of faith. If they are

26

Toleration John Locke 12. Heresy and schism

drawn up in the words of Scripture, there can be no question about them, because all Christians acknowledge those things as being divinely inspired and therefore fundamental. But if you (·I’m speaking to a heretic now·) say ·only· that the items you want to be professed are consequences of what is in Scripture, I say

believing and professing things that seem to you agreeable to the rule of faith—well done!

but

trying to force those things down the throats of people who don’t see them as indubitable Scriptural doctrines—not well done!

To create a split because of things like these, which aren’t and can’t be fundamental, is to be a heretic. I don’t think that any man is so lunatic as to dare to hawk his consequences and interpretations of Scripture as ‘divine inspirations’ and to put •the articles of faith that he has constructed on a par with •the authority of Scripture. I know some propositions are so evidently agreeable to Scripture that they can’t be denied to be consequences of it; and there can’t be any difference of opinion about those. ·And just for that reason, they aren’t relevant to our present topic of heresy, where by definition there always is a difference of opinion. Returning now to that topic (and again I am addressing the heretic)·: However clearly it seems to you that something-or-other follows from Scripture, you shouldn’t force it on others because you believe it to be agreeable to the rule of faith—or not unless you think it would be fair enough for other doctrines to be imposed on you in the same way. That would involve you in having to accept and profess all the different and contradictory opinions of Lutherans, Calvinists, Arminians, Anabaptists, and so on—opinions which the manufacturers of symbols, systems and confessions pass out to their followers as genuine and necessary deductions from the Holy Scripture. I’m amazed at the rash arrogance of men who think that they can explain things necessary to salvation more clearly than the Holy Ghost, the eternal and infinite wisdom of God.

·WHAT SCHISM IS·
So much for •heresy, a word that in common usage is applied only to the doctrinal part of religion. Let us now consider •schism. This is a crime like heresy, for both these words seem to me to signify an ill-grounded split in an ecclesiastical communion, arising from things that are not necessary ·to the faith·. But ordinary usage, which determines what is correct in language, has determined that •heresy relates to errors in faith and •schism to errors in worship or discipline; so I am following that distinction.

Schism, then....is a split made in the communion of a church because of something in divine worship or ecclesiastical discipline that is not a necessary part of the faith. Nothing in worship or church discipline can be necessary to Christian communion apart from what was commanded, in so many words, by Christ our legislator or by the Apostles ·speaking· under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit.

What I say is this: Someone who doesn’t deny anything that the Holy Scriptures teach explicitly, and doesn’t create a split because of something that isn’t clearly contained in the sacred text—whatever label any sect of Christians slap on him, and however many of them say that there’s nothing Christian about him—cannot be either a heretic or a schismatic.

27